<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dead faith anatomized a discourse on the nature, and the danger, with the deadly symptoms of a dead faith in those who profess the faith of Christ. / By Samuel Mather ...</title>
            <author>Mather, Samuel, 1651-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09525</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80923150</idno>
  <idno type="VID">191924</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240862044</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80923150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W19821</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">80923150</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191924)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2895:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dead faith anatomized a discourse on the nature, and the danger, with the deadly symptoms of a dead faith in those who profess the faith of Christ. / By Samuel Mather ...</title>
                  <author>Mather, Samuel, 1651-1728.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24, 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bartholomew Green, and John Allen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston in New England, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface, p. 1-24 (1st group) signed: Cotton Mather.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Boston Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191924:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191924:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:191924:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:191924:2"/>
               <hi>A Dead Faith Anatomized</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE ON The <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Danger,</hi> With the <hi>Deadly Symptoms</hi> OF A Dead Faith In those Who profess the <hi>Faith of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL-MATHER,</hi> Pastor of the Church at <hi>Windsor,</hi> in the Colony of <hi>Connecticut.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Hoc est Retia Salutis Expandere.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON in New England,</hi> Printed by <hi>Bartholomew Green,</hi> and <hi>John Allen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="book_plate">
            <pb facs="tcp:191924:3"/>
            <p> This <hi>Book</hi> belongs to <hi>The</hi> NEW-ENGLAND<hi>-Library,</hi> Begun to be collected by THOMAS PRINCE, upon his entring <hi>Harvard-College,</hi> July 6. 1703; and was given by <add>said Prince to remain therein forever</add>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:191924:3"/>
            <head>Preface.</head>
            <p>THAT Great Preacher of the Gospel, and <hi>Insatiable Admirer of the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> our Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> in all his Writings, but especially in the Epistle, which he wrote unto the <hi>Romans,</hi> [which was by <hi>Melancthon</hi> well called, <hi>The Protestants Confession of Faith,]</hi> as well as his Epistle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> does abundantly maintain this Article of our <hi>Faith, That a man is not Justified by the works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jesus Christ. Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith</hi> is a Receiving of, and a Relying on, the <hi>Gift of Righteousness</hi> from God, by our Lord Jesus Christ; or, the Consent of a Distressed Soul, to be <hi>Justified,</hi> by Gods <hi>Graciously Imputing</hi> unto him, the <hi>Obedience</hi> which the Lord Jesus Christ, as our <hi>Surety,</hi> yielded unto God, on the behalf of His Elect. This <hi>Faith</hi> doth <hi>Justify</hi> a Sinner, not <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> it is a <hi>Work;</hi> but <hi>Organically</hi> &amp; <hi>Relatively;</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>smuch as it is the <hi>Instrument,</hi> by which a man <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pprehends the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, as freely Tendred unto the Sinner in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191924:4"/> Gospel; Tis only in this Regard, that <hi>Faith,</hi> &amp; no <hi>Grace,</hi> but <hi>this Faith,</hi> ha's the Honour to <hi>Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy</hi> us. This is the <hi>Good old way,</hi> of arriving unto <hi>Rest;</hi> and, <hi>Aliter qui Vadit, cadit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But every <hi>Jewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ha's a <hi>Counterfeit.</hi> And, <hi>How shall a man know, that his Faith in the Righteousness of the Lord Jesus Christ, for his Justification, is not a Counterfeit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To answer that Case, the Blessed Apostle <hi>James,</hi> under the <hi>Inspirations of the Almighty,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares unto us, the <hi>Marks</hi> of a <hi>Justifying Faith;</hi> and those <hi>Marks</hi> are, the <hi>Works</hi> which it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually disposes the Believer unto.</p>
            <p>Now among the Admonitions of the Apostle to this purpose, there is a special Remark due to that, in Jam. 2. 20. <hi>Wilt thou know, O vain man, that Faith without works is Dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reader will presently observe in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable passage; both the Character of the <hi>Faith,</hi> which does not produce and promote <hi>Good Works,</hi> in the <hi>man</hi> that hath it: It is a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> it will be of no use unto the man in whom it is; it can do nothing for him: and then, the Character of the <hi>Man</hi> who ha's this <hi>Faith;</hi> He is a <hi>vain man;</hi> he seems, and he boasts, to <hi>have,</hi> what he hath <hi>not;</hi> and he flatters himself with <hi>Hopes</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver shall be made Good unto him. So that, we are now Assured, <hi>A Workless Faith is a Worthless Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who Professedly handles the Doctrine of <hi>Justification,</hi> does plainly assert, That no man
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191924:4"/> living is <hi>Justified</hi> by <hi>Works,</hi> but a man is <hi>Justifyed</hi> only by <hi>Faith. James</hi> does nevertheless assert, That a man is <hi>Justified</hi> by <hi>Works,</hi> and a man is not <hi>Justified</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> only. And yet, however some of the Ancients, as well as <hi>Luther,</hi> stumbled at this <hi>Appearance of Contradiction,</hi> the Assertions do not Contradict one another at all. <hi>Paul</hi> treats of our <hi>Justification</hi> before <hi>God,</hi> and the Right unto Everlasting Life, therein granted unto us, which is only by <hi>Faith</hi> in our Lord Jesus Christ. <hi>James</hi> treats of that which may manifest our <hi>Justification</hi> unto <hi>men,</hi> that See &amp; Hear, our Profession of our <hi>Faith;</hi> and here <hi>Works</hi> are significant. The <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> of a man, may be distressed with a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Accusation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, A man may be Accused of <hi>Iniquity;</hi> It may be said, <hi>Thou hast broken the Law, and thereby wronged the Name, of God, and the terrible penalty of that Law, now belongs unto thee.</hi> The Answer to this <hi>Accusation</hi> is to be, <hi>My Lord Jesus Christ ha's fully obey'd the will of God, and suffered the penalty due to me for my Disobedience; and I do by Faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on this Righteousness of my Lord Jesus Christ, for my Acceptance with God for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A man may be Accused of <hi>Hypocrisy;</hi> It may be said, <hi>Thou Talkest of thy Faith; but is it not meer Talk? How canst thou prove, that thy Faith is any more, than what is in the very Devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves?</hi> The Answer to this <hi>Accusation</hi> is, <hi>The works of a Sanctified man, which I am doing every Day, are the Proof of my Faith.</hi> According hereunto it is asserted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191924:5"/> by <hi>Paul,</hi> That a man is <hi>Justified alone by Faith:</hi> but it is asserted by <hi>James,</hi> That a man is <hi>not Justified by a Faith which is alone.</hi> The Question discoursed by <hi>Paul</hi> is, <hi>How a Guilty Person may come to be Acquitted by the Lord, from all the Guilt that lies upon him?</hi> The Answer to this Question, is, Not by any <hi>Works</hi> of our own, but only by the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, which is, on our part, only by <hi>Faith</hi> applied unto us. The Question discoursed by <hi>James,</hi> is, <hi>Whether a man pretending to Faith in the Righteousness of the Lord Jesus Christ, shall be saved, though he continue without the works of an Holy Life, agreeable thereunto?</hi> The Answer to this Question is, <hi>No,</hi> Such a man ha's no <hi>Saving Faith</hi> at all. And that <hi>James</hi> is to be taken in that sense, is evident from This: He does insist upon the Instance of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and yet <hi>Abraham</hi> was a <hi>Justified man,</hi> Thirty years, before those <hi>Works,</hi> which are said here to <hi>Justify</hi> him. Upon the whole then, we see <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, or, indeed, never contrdicting. And we are Advised after all; Tis a <hi>Vanity</hi> in any man to <hi>Profess,</hi> that he ha's a <hi>True Faith</hi> in the Lord Jesus Christ, if his <hi>Faith</hi> be not <hi>Fruitful</hi> in those <hi>Good Works,</hi> which may <hi>Justify</hi> the mans <hi>Profession.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are Two very Important <hi>Cases,</hi> about which the Thoughts of every Christian, cannot but be Exercised; and we will here bestow some of our Thoughts thereupon.</p>
            <p>The first <hi>Case</hi> which a Christian, must Consider, if he would be a <hi>Christian,</hi> is,</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:191924:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>What are those <hi>Good Works,</hi> which a True Faith, will Quicken &amp; Incline the Believer unto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we may thus conceive of them; <hi>Good Works,</hi> are <hi>Sincere Essayes</hi> to observe the <hi>Law of God.</hi> Our God hath given us a <hi>Rule of Life,</hi> in that which we call, <hi>The Moral Law.</hi> None of our <hi>Works</hi> are <hi>Perfectly Good,</hi> if in any point they fall short of that <hi>Rule.</hi> But none of our <hi>Works</hi> do <hi>Perfectly</hi> come up to the <hi>Rule,</hi> as long as we are lodg'd in <hi>this Body which is to Dy.</hi> The <hi>Best men</hi> alive, when they look upon the <hi>Best Works</hi> of their Lives, may cry out, with one of the Ancients, <hi>Terret me tota vita mea, nam apparet mihi, aut Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum, aut tota Sterilitas;</hi> The <hi>Sinfulness,</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranness,</hi> of all my <hi>Life,</hi> strikes me with a <hi>Deadly Terror</hi> of Soul! Nevertheless, there are <hi>Sincere Essays</hi> towards <hi>Perfection,</hi> which all Believers are Conscientiously making every Day. Now these <hi>Essayes</hi> are <hi>Good,</hi> in the Merciful Reckoning of God, our <hi>Father</hi> in our Lord Jesus Christ. Tho' none of our <hi>Sincere Essayes</hi> at <hi>Well-doing</hi> are such <hi>Good works</hi> as to <hi>Justify</hi> us, before that Thrice <hi>Holy God,</hi> who is of <hi>Purer eyes than to behold Evil,</hi> &amp; whose <hi>Pure Eyes</hi> yet <hi>behold</hi> in our <hi>Good Works,</hi> a world of <hi>Evil:</hi> Yet our <hi>Sincere Essayes</hi> are pleasing unto our God, who by His Good <hi>Spirit</hi> ha's Excited them, &amp; Assisted them; and, <hi>Whose workmanship we are, Created in Christ Jesus unto Good works, which God hath before ordained, that we should walk in them.</hi> Such Good <hi>Works,</hi> as our <hi>Prayers,</hi> are, as tis said, in Prov. 15. 8.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191924:6"/>
               <hi>The Delight of the Lord;</hi> and such Good <hi>Works,</hi> as our <hi>Alms,</hi> are, as tis said, in Heb. 13. 16. <hi>The Sacrifices where-with God is well pleased.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, to speak strictly, <hi>Good Works</hi> must have these Four Ingredients to render them <hi>such.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First; The <hi>Matter</hi> of our <hi>Works</hi> must be, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Law</hi> of God, or, His <hi>Will</hi> Revealed in His <hi>Word.</hi> The Prophet could say, in Mic. 6. 8. <hi>He hath shewed thee, O man, the thing that is Good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to Do Justice, and to Love Mercy, and to walk Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God. Good Works</hi> must be such, as the Lord hath <hi>shewn</hi> to us, that He hath <hi>Required</hi> of us. They are no <hi>Good Works,</hi> whereof our God may say, <hi>Who hath required 'em?</hi> Works of <hi>Piety,</hi> are <hi>Good Works;</hi> for we have the <hi>Word</hi> of our God for them; as in Psal. 92. 1. <hi>It is a Good Thing to give Thanks unto the Lord.</hi> Works of <hi>Charity</hi> are <hi>Good Works;</hi> for we have the <hi>word</hi> of our God for them; as in Heb. 13. 16. <hi>To Do Good, and to Communicate, forget not.</hi> No works are <hi>Good,</hi> but such as are contained in the <hi>Two Tables</hi> of the <hi>Ten Commandments;</hi> the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But unto the Constitution of <hi>Good Works,</hi> it is not enough, that the <hi>matter</hi> of what we do, be according to the <hi>Law</hi> of God. Men may do <hi>Works</hi> that shall be <hi>Good</hi> for the <hi>matter</hi> of them, and yet, <hi>Every work of their Hands be unclean, saith the Lord. Plowing</hi> is Lawful, and <hi>Praying</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:191924:6"/> is Lawful; and yet these <hi>works</hi> may be sinful in the Doer of them. Wherefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Manner</hi> of our <hi>Works,</hi> must be Right, as well as the <hi>Matter</hi> of them. A man may incur the Wrath of God, by his <hi>Good Works,</hi> if he do them not in any <hi>manner</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Law,</hi> as they should be done. We find, in 1 Chron. 15. 13. <hi>The Lord our God</hi> is offended at those who <hi>Seek Him not after the due Order.</hi> No meer <hi>External Actions</hi> are to be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed <hi>Good Works;</hi> there must <hi>Internal Cautions</hi> go along with them; else they are but the <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>Good Works,</hi> without the <hi>Form. Good Works</hi> must be done with <hi>Regular Circumstances,</hi> if they would be called, <hi>Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Design</hi> of our <hi>Works</hi> must be Right, as well as the <hi>manner</hi> of them. The <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign</hi> which the <hi>Law</hi> of God has assigned for our <hi>Good Works,</hi> is, That the Great God, may be acknowledged, and magnified, and glorified: And the <hi>Gospel</hi> of God, coming in, has assigned a further <hi>Design</hi> for them; namely, To express our <hi>Gratitude</hi> unto our Lord-Redeemer, for His Redeeming of us. Thus 'tis Enjoined, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 30. <hi>Whatever ye do, do all to the Glory of God.</hi> An <hi>Evil Intention</hi> will utterly spoil any <hi>Good Works,</hi> tho' they were otherwise never so <hi>Good.</hi> And a meerly <hi>Selfish Intention</hi> is an <hi>Evil</hi> one. <hi>Good Works</hi> must all be done, with an Eye, to the <hi>Honour</hi> of God, and the <hi>Service</hi> of Christ, before any <hi>Temporal Advantage</hi> to <hi>Self:</hi> else the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191924:7"/>
               <hi>Best Sacrifices</hi> are but an <hi>Abomination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Good Works</hi> must proceed from a <hi>Good <hi>Principle;</hi>
               </hi> or otherwise they will have no <hi>Real Goodness</hi> in them. Waters that Flow from a bitter and a poison'd <hi>Fountain,</hi> can't be <hi>Good.</hi> A <hi>Good Heart,</hi> Like a <hi>Good Fountain,</hi> must be the <hi>Principle,</hi> from whence <hi>Good Works</hi> are to flow. We are told, in Mat. 12. 35. <hi>A Good man, out of the Good Treasure of the Heart, bringeth forth Good Things.</hi> A <hi>Good Principle</hi> within, is a <hi>Good Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the Heart. Works</hi> done meerly from a Principle of <hi>Slavish Fear,</hi> or <hi>Fleshly Love,</hi> are not <hi>Good,</hi> tho' they be never so <hi>Good.</hi> There must be a <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Respect unto God in Christ,</hi> woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us unto all our <hi>Good Works,</hi> or else they are <hi>Stark Naught.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, must be in us, as a <hi>Vital Principle,</hi> for our <hi>Good Works,</hi> or else they are <hi>Dead Works,</hi> every one of them. Hence, no <hi>Good Works</hi> were ever done by any one <hi>Unregenerate</hi> man, since the World began; for every <hi>Unregenerate</hi> man is destitute of the <hi>Principle,</hi> which is to be acted in them: the most <hi>Splendid Works</hi> of the Unregenerate, are but (as <hi>Austin</hi> call'd them) <hi>Splendid Sins</hi> before the Lord.</p>
            <p>And now there is a Second <hi>Case</hi> which a Christian has to consider, that so he may be stirred up, and helped on, to do those <hi>Good Works</hi> by which he may approve himself indeed a Christian.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:191924:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Where Lies the <hi>Necessity</hi> of Good Works, in a Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Belsever, to Justifie the Faith, which he is a Professor of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we do know this; That our <hi>Good Works</hi> are not <hi>Antecedently</hi> necessary unto our <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification</hi> before the God of Heaven. For <hi>Good VVorks</hi> cannot be done by any man, <hi>until</hi> he be <hi>Justified.</hi> Until a man be <hi>United</hi> unto the Lord Jesus Christ, who is our <hi>Life,</hi> he is a <hi>Dead man:</hi> and what <hi>Good Works</hi> can a <hi>Dead man</hi> do? This is a thing <hi>Livelily</hi> Preached unto us, by our Lord Himself, in the fifteenth Chapter of <hi>John; The mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.</hi> Hence that common saying of <hi>Austin, Bona Opera sequuntur Justificatum, non praecedunt Justificandum.</hi> No, nor is <hi>Faith</hi> it self, <hi>As</hi> doing of <hi>Good Works,</hi> that which Entitles us unto the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, for our <hi>Justification;</hi> 'Tis <hi>Faith,</hi> only <hi>As</hi> it Layes Hold on the <hi>Righteousness of the Lord Jesus Christ, for the chief of Sinners,</hi> that <hi>Justifies</hi> us; And until this be done, we cannot be carried forth unto any <hi>Good Works</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>But then, <hi>Good Works,</hi> are <hi>consequently</hi> necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon our <hi>Justification.</hi> 'Tis indeed said, That <hi>God Justifies the Ungodly;</hi> but then, He does not Leave them <hi>Ungodly</hi> when He hath <hi>Justified</hi> them. Well, And where Lies the <hi>Necessity?</hi> Truly, if we would not be <hi>vain men,</hi> we must <hi>Know</hi> such Things as these.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:191924:8"/>
            <p> First, <hi>Wilt thou know, O man?</hi> That it is in the very <hi>Nature</hi> of a <hi>Justifying Faith,</hi> to put a man upon the Doing of <hi>Good Works. Faith</hi> is a <hi>Purifier</hi> of the <hi>Heart:</hi> [Acts 15. 9.] and so, it cannot but be a <hi>Purifier</hi> of the <hi>Life.</hi> The same <hi>Faith,</hi> which Embraces the Lord Jesus Christ, as a <hi>Priest,</hi> for <hi>Atonement,</hi> (and <hi>As</hi> doing this, it <hi>Justifies!)</hi> Embraces Him also, as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> &amp; as a <hi>King:</hi> Now this <hi>Prophet</hi> will <hi>Instruct,</hi> &amp; this <hi>King</hi> will <hi>Injoin,</hi> our doing of <hi>Good Works</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. A <hi>Justifying Faith,</hi> Receives Christ the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer,</hi> and the <hi>Intercessor;</hi> and in that Notion, it <hi>Justifies:</hi> But is this all? No, it also, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Col. 2. 6. <hi>Receives Christ the Lord.</hi> Now <hi>Good Works</hi> are by that <hi>Lord</hi> Required. 'Tis no <hi>True Faith,</hi> which any man hath, if it be not for a <hi>whole Christ.</hi> The Devil said unto our Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>What have we to do with thee, Thou Holy One?</hi> If a man would be concerned with our Lord Jesus Christ, only as a <hi>Merciful</hi> One, and a <hi>Gracious</hi> One, and not likewise as an <hi>Holy</hi> One, that man has no more <hi>Faith</hi> than a <hi>Devil! Justifying Faith</hi> is a <hi>Tree,</hi> which cannot but have the <hi>Good Fruits</hi> of <hi>Good Works</hi> growing upon it. It is the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of God, that <hi>Creates,</hi> and that <hi>Bestows,</hi> a <hi>Justifying Faith,</hi> wherever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is; and that <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> cannot suffer any Soul, in which He dwells, to be wholly Remiss about the <hi>Good Works</hi> which are agreeable unto His <hi>Holiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Briefly; 'Tis in the very <hi>Nature</hi> of a <hi>Saving</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:191924:8"/>
               <hi>Faith</hi> to be a <hi>Working Faith.</hi> The Scriptures of Truth, assure us, in Gal. 5. 6. <hi>Faith works, by Love.</hi> It was well said, therefore by <hi>John Hus, Ubi Bona Opera non apparent ad extra, ibi Fides non est ad intra: Faith</hi> is not <hi>within,</hi> if <hi>Good VVorks</hi> are not <hi>without. Faith</hi> must become <hi>visible,</hi> and (as hath been sometimes said) <hi>Incarnate,</hi> by <hi>Good VVorks</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>Again; <hi>Wilt thou know, O man?</hi> That <hi>Good works</hi> are no <hi>Small part</hi> of the <hi>Great Salvation,</hi> which is the Hope and claim of all the <hi>Justified.</hi> Our Lord Jesus Christ hath <hi>Redeemed</hi> us by His Blood; What for? We are informed, in Tit. 2. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>4. <hi>To purify unto Himself, a peculiar People, zealous <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f Good works.</hi> The following words, <hi>Let no man despise thee, Calvin</hi> thinks them spoken to the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi> because <hi>People</hi> often don't care to Hear of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>his; but it is a Thing to be <hi>spoken with all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hority.</hi> A main Thing, Bought for us by the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, is, that we may be made Happy, by our Enjoying a <hi>Resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lance</hi> of that <hi>Righteousness,</hi> in our own doing of <hi>Good works,</hi> wherein we shall be conformed unto His Exemple. The <hi>Doing of Good works,</hi> is one main Thing, in that <hi>Blessedness,</hi> which our Lord <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>esus Christ hath purchased for us, in His being made a <hi>Curse</hi> on our behalf: And a man ha's no True <hi>Faith</hi> in him, until he be thus perswaded! Very grand is the mistake of men, about <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Salvation</hi> is not meerly our <hi>Fruition</hi> of the <hi>Good Things</hi> reserved for us, in the unseen and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191924:9"/> state; but <hi>Salvation</hi> lies also in our <hi>Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> of <hi>Good works</hi> leading thereunto. Our <hi>Captivity</hi> to the <hi>Devil,</hi> is that from which we are in our <hi>Salvation</hi> rescued: and that <hi>Captivity</hi> keeps a man from doing of <hi>Good works.</hi> For a man to be set at <hi>Liberty</hi> from the <hi>Devil,</hi> and so to do those <hi>Good works,</hi> which are contrary to the <hi>Works of the Devil,</hi> This, This is our <hi>Salvation.</hi> A mans being made Able and Willing to Do <hi>Good works,</hi> like the <hi>Good Angels</hi> of Heaven, This is the <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> which <hi>Faith</hi> does make out after; Tis the <hi>End of our Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Salvation of our Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore; <hi>Wilt thou know, O man?</hi> That the <hi>Commandment</hi> of Heaven hath made <hi>Good works</hi> incumbent on every man on Earth. Tis true, when we are in our Lord Jesus Christ, we are not under a <hi>Covenant of works.</hi> Our own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Good works,</hi> is not now, the <hi>Condition</hi> of our <hi>Entering into Life.</hi> But still, the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> does not Release us, from all Obligation, to <hi>do</hi> those <hi>Good works,</hi> which once were the Terms of our <hi>Entering into Life;</hi> the Language of it is that in Rom. 3. 31. <hi>Do we then make void the Law through Faith? God forbid: Yea, we Establish the Law.</hi> Because we are under the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> are we not still obliged unto all that <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> all that <hi>Watchfulness,</hi> all that <hi>Exactness,</hi> which was demanded in the <hi>Old Covenant? God forbid!</hi> Yea, we do still so <hi>Establish the Law,</hi> that if we fail in any one thing, tis our <hi>Sin,</hi> it should be our <hi>Grief,</hi> it will be our <hi>Shame;</hi> and we must, with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:191924:9"/>
               <hi>Contrition</hi> of Heart, make our Confession, <hi>That we come short of our Duty.</hi> Indeed, because we cannot but continually Transgress, and, <hi>In many things we offend all,</hi> therefore the <hi>New-Covenant</hi> ha's provided a <hi>Remedy</hi> for us: Tis only the <hi>Good works</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ Reputed <hi>Ours,</hi> that cause us to <hi>stand as without Fault before the Throne of God.</hi> But we must own it still, as a <hi>Fault</hi> in us, a <hi>Fault</hi> worthy of Death, whenever we miss of doing any Thing, that is demanded as a <hi>Duty,</hi> in the <hi>Old Covenant:</hi> There is a <hi>Sin,</hi> in <hi>Every Transgression of the Law;</hi> a Sin to be Confessed, Bewayled, Abhorred. Yea, and our Lord Jesus Christ in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> doth, How often? Repeat those Precepts; in Math. 5. 16. <hi>Let your Light so shine before men, that they may see your Good works:</hi> and in Tit. 3. 8. <hi>This is a Faithful saying, That they which have Believed in God, should be careful of Good works:</hi> and in 1 Joh. 2. 1. <hi>These Things write I unto you, that ye do not Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover; <hi>Wilt thou know, O man?</hi> That without <hi>Good works</hi> we are Abominably &amp; Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusably <hi>Ungrateful</hi> unto our Lord Jesus Christ, who hath done so many <hi>kind works</hi> for us? The <hi>Evangelical Reason</hi> for our <hi>Good works,</hi> is, That we may show our <hi>Thankfulness</hi> unto Him, <hi>Who ha's Loved us, and given Himself for us;</hi> unto Him, <hi>Who ha's Loved us, and washed away our Sins, in His own Blood.</hi> If a man have the least Grain of True <hi>Faith</hi> in him, he will make that Enquiry before our Lord Jesus Christ, in Psal. 116. 12. <hi>What</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:191924:10"/>
               <hi>shall I render to the Lord, for all His Benefits?</hi> Now the Reply that <hi>Faith</hi> makes to this Enquiry, is the same that our Lord Himself makes; <hi>Let those Good works be done, which may adorn the Doctrine of God the Saviour!</hi> It was argued, in Rom. 12. 1. <hi>I beseech you Brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye present your Bodies, a Living Sacrifice, Holy, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, which is your Reasonable Service.</hi> Even so, All the Return, which our Lord Jesus Christ expects from us, for all His <hi>Mercies,</hi> is, <hi>That we Devote our selves unto the Service of our Lord:</hi> And <hi>Faith</hi> says, That this is a Thing infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely <hi>Reasonable.</hi> Where <hi>Faith</hi> has been infused into the Heart of any man, there is no <hi>Motive</hi> unto <hi>Good VVorks</hi> more powerful than this upon him. If he could think, <hi>I sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l escape Hell, yea, I shall merit Heaven, by my good works!</hi> This were not such a powerful motive to <hi>good works,</hi> for an <hi>Heart</hi> that has <hi>Faith</hi> in it, as to think, <hi>I shall by my good works Glorify, my Blessed Lord Jesus Christ, who has done so much for me!</hi> That man has no <hi>Faith</hi> in him, on whom this motive has not a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>constraining</hi> operation. For us to be without <hi>good works,</hi> would be an horrible Reproach unto the Lord Jesus Christ, as if He were, <hi>A Patron of Sin,</hi> and as if He were a <hi>God that had pleasure in wickedness, and evil might dwell with Him.</hi> Now a True <hi>Faith</hi> wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never let a man be so <hi>wicked</hi> as thus to <hi>Reproach</hi> the Lord. <hi>Foolish and Unwise</hi> are all they, that thus <hi>Requite the Lord!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, <hi>VVilt thou know, O man?</hi> That an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191924:10"/> Heart set for the Doing of <hi>Good Works,</hi> is a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification,</hi> and a <hi>Preparation</hi> of them that shall <hi>Inherit</hi> the Recompences of <hi>Everlasting Life.</hi> There is no passing into the most Holy Heavens, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being, as 'tis expressed in Col. 1 12. <hi>Made meet to be Partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</hi> All the Partakers of the Heavenly <hi>Inheritance,</hi> are doing of <hi>Good Works</hi> therein for ever; they do nothing but <hi>Good works</hi> there throughout Eternal Ages. Now, except a man have an Heart for <hi>Good works</hi> [in <hi>Conversion,</hi> Mat. 18. 3.] given unto him, he is not <hi>meet</hi> for that <hi>Inheritance,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into there <hi>Enters nothing that shall Defile.</hi> The <hi>Good works</hi> which our weekly <hi>Sabbath</hi> is to be fill'd withal, make it very wearisome unto an <hi>Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed</hi> Soul: they say, <hi>What a weariness is it?</hi> When the Sanctification of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> was lately Urged upon a grave Ceremonious Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he reply'd, <hi>What? Would you have a man be upon the Rack, a whole Day together?</hi> Truly, The Eternal <hi>Sabbath,</hi> which our Glorious <hi>Jesus</hi> carryeth all His People into, Men will be <hi>weary</hi> of it, it will be a <hi>Rack</hi> unto them, they won't be suited in it, if they should not have an Heart for <hi>Good works</hi> inspired into them; none but those that are thus <hi>pure in Heart,</hi> will be fit for the Beatifick <hi>Sight</hi> of the most <hi>Holy God.</hi> Our God must <hi>work us for that self-same thing,</hi> [2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.] or, else the <hi>Thing</hi> would be Distastful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us: now, 'tis by a <hi>Spirit</hi> for <hi>Good works,</hi> that. He does <hi>work</hi> us up hereunto. And He hath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191924:11"/> warned us, in Heb. 12. 14. <hi>Wiihout Holiness, no man shall see the Lord.</hi> Tho' we shall not go to Heaven <hi>For</hi> our <hi>Good works,</hi> we cannot go to Heaven <hi>without</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Now what should be the Result of our Thoughts upon these Two <hi>Cases</hi> thus offered, but This?</p>
            <p>We are to be advised, first of all; That we do not Expect, to be <hi>Justified</hi> by our <hi>Good works,</hi> or to Do any <hi>Good works</hi> until we are <hi>Justified,</hi> in our Believing on the Lord Jesus Christ. It is of no little Importance unto us, That our <hi>Good works</hi> have their due place in our <hi>Divinity:</hi> and many Treatises of such <hi>Divinity</hi> as the English Nations has been of later years Defiled and Abused with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, have not only been <hi>Ineffectual</hi> to procure those <hi>Good Works,</hi> which they have pretended for, but also been really <hi>prejudicial</hi> thereunto, for their want of This. We must Beware how we go to patch up a <hi>Righteousness</hi> of our own, out of those <hi>Good works</hi> whereto God may Enable us, or do like them, who in Rom. 10. 3. <hi>Being ignorant of Gods Righteousness, and going about to establish their own Righteousness, have not submitted themselves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Righteousness of God.</hi> There is not a more fatal <hi>Rock</hi> for the Shipwrack of a Soul, than this! When Sinners are <hi>Awakened,</hi> with the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions of the Divine Vengeance pursuing of them, for their Sins, this is the <hi>First Thing</hi> that they usually betake themselves unto: They fly <hi>First</hi> unto the <hi>Good Works</hi> of a <hi>Reformation</hi> in their faulty Lives. No, O <hi>vain man; Wilt thou</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:191924:11"/>
               <hi>Know?</hi> Thy <hi>First Flight</hi> should be unto the Lord Jesus Christ, for His <hi>Righteousness</hi> to be conferred upon the most Loathsome Sinner out of Hell; and that thou mayst, <hi>Be found in Him, not having thy own Righteousness, which is of the Law, but that which is thro' the Faith of Christ, the Righteousness which is of God by Faith.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>vain</hi> Imagination that thou mayst not Believe on the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, for thy <hi>Justification,</hi> until by doing of <hi>Good works</hi> thou art made <hi>Fit</hi> for the <hi>Imputation</hi> of that <hi>Righteousness.</hi> Many say, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they would Lay Hold on the Lord Jesus Christ, and on His Righteousness, but they <hi>dare not,</hi> because they are <hi>not Fit for Him.</hi> Alas, this also is but another and a finer strain, to set up our own <hi>Righteousness.</hi> How, <hi>Not Fit?</hi> The wretched circumstances of thy Soul, that make thee say, <hi>Not Fit,</hi> are thy very <hi>Fitness.</hi> We must come to our Lord Jesus Christ <hi>For</hi> those things, which the preposterous Hearts of men would come unto Him, <hi>With.</hi> It is an Error for men to venture their Everlasting Interest upon the Lord Jesus Christ, under this Encouragement, <hi>That they have attained unto such and such Godly Dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as will Recommend us unto Him;</hi> We must go to Him, and His <hi>Righteousness,</hi> and venture to cast our selves upon it, as <hi>Recommended</hi> by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but our own Horrible <hi>misery,</hi> thereunto. Certainly, It will never make <hi>Sincere Converts,</hi> to talk of <hi>Rapping off mens Fingers from catching Hold of Christ, before they are fit for Him.</hi> 'Tis our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191924:12"/>
               <hi>Catching Hold of Him,</hi> that must make us <hi>Fit for Him,</hi> and for every <hi>Good work!</hi> We shall do <hi>Good Works</hi> when we have come utterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>them,</hi> unto the Lord Jesus Christ, first, for a share in the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of the <hi>Good Works</hi> which <hi>He</hi> did for us, and then, for the Assistance to Do <hi>Good Works</hi> our selves, in a measure Like unto them. Well, and when we have Done our <hi>Good Works,</hi> we must after all, Remember this, That we are to <hi>Renounce</hi> them all; Renounce all <hi>Dependence</hi> on them for the purchase of the Divine Favour unto us. When some told our Dying <hi>Herbert,</hi> the many <hi>Good works</hi> which he had been doing in his Life, he only said, <hi>Good Works, if sprinkled with the Blood of Christ!</hi> It is the <hi>Blood of Christ,</hi> and not our <hi>Good works,</hi> that must be of any value with us. They that Build their <hi>Faith</hi> on their <hi>Good works,</hi> Build on a <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Foundation:</hi> The <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> were sound in this Article; <hi>(Justin Martyr</hi> will clear it:) That we are Justified only by a wonderful <hi>Commutation</hi> between our Lord and us, <hi>He</hi> taking our <hi>Guiltiness,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> having His <hi>Righteousness:</hi> 'Tis well declared by <hi>Cyprian, Non aspernatur Dei Filius carnem Hominis induere, ut cum peccare ipse non posset, aliena peccata portaret. Immortalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te interim posita, fieri se mortalem patitur, ut Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens pro Nocentium Salute Perimatur:</hi> 'Tis well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who Expounding that pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage in the Psalms, <hi>I restored that which I took not away,</hi> applies it unto our Lord Jesus Christ. <hi>q. d.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:191924:12"/>
               <hi>Others robbed God of His Glory, but I</hi> (says our Lord) <hi>have restored it again; the Sins by which twas' done, they were mine by Imputation, tho' never mine by Inhoerency.</hi> The <hi>Protestant Reformers</hi> were so full in this Article, That they did not scruple to say, <hi>Amisso Articulo Justificationis, simul amissa est tota Doctrina Christiana;</hi> and as they Liv'd and Dy'd in the Judgment of that Martyr, whose Expiring words, were, <hi>Behold, a marvellous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, my Lord has my Guiltiness, and I have His Righteousness!</hi> thus, they have generally ever since been clear in it, until some of Late, have dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened the Truth, under pretence of preserving the Interests of <hi>Holiness;</hi> Albeit, as our Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Owen,</hi> says, <hi>I am not satisfied, that any of those, who at present oppose this Doctrine, do in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Righteousness, and the Exercise of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Graces, surpass those who in the Last Ages, both in this and other Nations, firmly adhaered unto it.</hi> Yea, some of the <hi>Papists</hi> themselves, have been under such <hi>Convictions,</hi> as have compelled them to Subscribe unto this Article; especially, when the Approaches of <hi>Death,</hi> have given them with a <hi>Lively Sense</hi> to feel themselves going to appear before the Judgment-Seat of God. <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestus,</hi> the Arch-bishop of <hi>Magdeburgh,</hi> when he was near his Death, was comforted by a Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, who told him, <hi>That the merit of his Good works, would make sure a place in Heaven for him;</hi> whereupon the Dying man cryed out, <hi>Nullo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> I will <hi>by no means trust unto the merit of any</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:191924:13"/>
               <hi>Good works, done by any man whatever, but the Good works of Christ are sufficient for me! Bellarmine</hi> himself, who had Lived so Blamelesly, that he was not conscious of his ever having once told a <hi>Lye,</hi> and when he came to <hi>Auricular Confession</hi> he could find nothing to mention, without Looking back so far as his Childhood, yet when his Death was arresting him, he durst no more trust unto the merit of his <hi>Good works,</hi> but would have that clause inserted in his Will, That he desired the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Receive him, <hi>Non ut oestimator meriti, sed ut Largitor veniae;</hi> Not on <hi>Merit,</hi> but in <hi>Mercy!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we are in the next place to be Advised, That having first <hi>Believed</hi> on the Lord Jesus Christ, that we may be <hi>Justified,</hi> we do then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in those <hi>Good works,</hi> which are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Genuine Symptoms of <hi>Believers;</hi> those <hi>Good works,</hi> which the Oracles of Heaven call, <hi>The Fruits of Righteousness.</hi> We should, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle speaks, in 1 Cor. 15. 58. <hi>Always abound in the work of the Lord.</hi> The Bible has no <hi>Good words</hi> any where, for those <hi>Antinomian</hi> Wretches, with whom <hi>Good works</hi> are despised &amp; neglected: It spits nothing but Sulphureous Fire, in the Faces of those <hi>Libertines!</hi> If we are destitute of <hi>Good works,</hi> we have none but a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> and a <hi>Dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith</hi> will very little befriend a <hi>Dead Soul.</hi> To have no <hi>Good works</hi> then, is a woful Thing: and, the Praemonition is, in Math. 3. 10. <hi>Every Tree which bringeth not forth Good Fruit, is hewn down, &amp; cast into the Fire:</hi> What then will be the Wo, how wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191924:13"/> will be the Doom of those that are full of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil works,</hi> and bring forth much of that <hi>Evil Fruit,</hi> which grows on the <hi>Vine of Sodom, &amp; in the Field of Gomorrah?</hi> Sad will it be for us to perish among <hi>Unbelievers,</hi> after we have seemed mightily to <hi>Believe;</hi> &amp; after a fair show of our <hi>Faith,</hi> to be Damn'd among, <hi>The workers of Iniquity.</hi> Surely, If we would with the <hi>Joy of Faith,</hi> be Satisfied, that the <hi>Seal of the Holy Spirit,</hi> which we seem to have, when we Entertain our Assurance, <hi>That the Righteousness of God, which is by the Faith of Jesus Christ is upon us,</hi> is not a Cheat, a Sham, a Self-deluding <hi>Enthusiasm,</hi> it becomes us, with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>Good works,</hi> to <hi>Exercise our selves, at keeping a Conscience void of Offence towards God and man.</hi> It becomes us, to Ponder, How much we <hi>Owe</hi> unto our Lord Jesus Christ, and Study, How to <hi>Serve</hi> the Lord that has <hi>Bought</hi> us; &amp; with <hi>Good works</hi> alwayes to be at work for Him. It becomes us, to forethink, How little Time we have to be <hi>Working</hi> in, how near we are to the Time where there can be no <hi>Working,</hi> and to Do as many <hi>Good works,</hi> as we can in our Time; yea, to call our selves unto a <hi>Daily Account,</hi> with unspeakable Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if we have let one Day pass without many of them. It becomes us even to raise our <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Natural,</hi> as well as <hi>Religious works,</hi> unto the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Good works,</hi> by the most Frequent, most Explicit, &amp; most Ennobling <hi>Dedications</hi> of all our <hi>Works,</hi> unto the Lord. So, it will not be long before we <hi>rest from our Labours,</hi> but <hi>our Works will follow us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:191924:14"/>
            <p> These Things being so, 'tis a Great Service un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Souls of men, to supply them, with <hi>Rules of Trial,</hi> by which they may <hi>Examine</hi> themselves, as well concerning their <hi>Faith,</hi> as concerning the <hi>Good works,</hi> which they pretend unto. Now, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate his Neighbours with such <hi>Rules of Trial,</hi> the Reverend Author of the Ensuing Discourse, ha's permitted their Desires to be gratified in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of it. The Discourse is what was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto a <hi>Popular Auditory,</hi> for which cause, the Reader must not wonder, if he find some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of <hi>Inculcation</hi> in it: he will seek in such a Discourse, <hi>Non Scientiam, sed Saporem;</hi> and no doubt, he will find what he seeks. But such was the <hi>Savour</hi> which it left upon the minds of the Hearers, when it was delivered, as that the Notes thereof are here come abroad, for them to <hi>Rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> yet more thoroughly upon that, wherein they have already found themselves not a little Edified. The Author is <hi>known,</hi> throughout the Churches of the famous and happy Colony, to none of the least whereof he hath for many years been a faithfull Pastor; <hi>Known,</hi> for his Piety, Gravity, and Usefulness, more than any Recommendations of mine can render him: and my <hi>Relation</hi> to him, will easily excuse me as well as his <hi>Modesty</hi> forbid me, for saying any more. Nor have I any thing further to add, but my Hearty Prayers, That these <hi>Good Works</hi> of this Worthy Person, may be so <hi>Profitable</hi> among the People of God, in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as may fully answer the <hi>Holy Designs,</hi> of him that has thus offered unto the <hi>Service of the Tabernacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Cotton Mather.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191924:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Dead Faith</hi> Anatomized</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>James 2. 20.</bibl>
               <q>But wilt thou know, O Vain Man, that Faith without Works is Dead?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> had abundantly taught (as appears in divers of his Epistles) that man is Justified by <hi>Faith</hi> alone, without <hi>Works:</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 28. <hi>Therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that a man is Justified by Faith, without the deeds of the Law.</hi> Gal. 2. 16. <hi>Knowing that a man is not Justified, by the Works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jesus Christ.</hi> This Doctrine did this Apostle much insist upon, especially in the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> but now mentioned: neither did any of the Apostles of Christ teach otherwise, or contrary
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191924:15"/> thereunto: howbeit, it seems there were some, that made an ill use of <hi>this Doctrine,</hi> as also they did of some <hi>other</hi> things, in <hi>Pauls Epistles.</hi> See 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16. Some be like there were then that did turn the <hi>Grace of God into Wantonness,</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be Saved <hi>by Faith</hi> (not knowing indeed what <hi>Faith</hi> is) and so to Live a loose and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less <hi>Life:</hi> (and thus it is with many, in these <hi>our</hi> times, wherein the Gospel hath been so abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly Published, and with so much perspicuity and clearness.) These, and such like persons, this Apostle <hi>James</hi> rebuketh, and endeavoureth to rectifie. He had told them in <hi>verse</hi> 17. that <hi>Faith without Works is dead:</hi> in this <hi>20th. verse,</hi> he inculcateth, and presseth the same Doctrine again; and he sheweth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is such a thing as a <hi>Dead Faith:</hi> this is plainly implied in the words.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He sheweth <hi>what</hi> this <hi>Dead Faith</hi> is, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Faith without Works:</hi> such a <hi>Faith</hi> as hath not <hi>Good Works</hi> to be the fruits thereof: that <hi>Faith</hi> which doth not bring forth <hi>good fruit,</hi> is a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> and hence can be no evidence of <hi>Life</hi> in that Soul, where it is found.</p>
            <p n="3">3 He calleth him a <hi>vain man,</hi> that would, from any thing that had been taught, by any of the Holy Apostles, gather any other conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He affectionately expostulates the case with such, in those words, <hi>but wilt thou know,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>q d.</hi> wilt thou understand, and be convinced?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191924:15"/> it is easy to see the Error here, unless men be willingly and wilfully ignorant: <hi>wilt thou know,</hi> &amp;c. it is true, we read of some that <hi>hold fast deceit, and refuse to return.</hi> Jer. 8. 5. and many such there be in our days also.</p>
            <p>But the point of Doctrine is this: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="doctrine">
                        <head>DOCTRINE.</head>
                        <p>That there is such a thing as a Dead Faith, with which some under the Gospel do deceive themselves.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>They think that they have <hi>Faith,</hi> or do Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and that they shall be <hi>Saved,</hi> but in the issue they are disappointed, and ashamed of their <hi>hopes;</hi> and how fearful is it, when so it is! See <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 31. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 116. Such are at last <hi>Led forth with Workers of Iniquity,</hi> as <hi>Psal.</hi> 125. <hi>ult.</hi> and to them will Christ profess, and say, <hi>I never knew you: depart from me,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 23. A <hi>Dead Faith</hi> is a <hi>deadly</hi> thing: A Soul-ruining thing. A true, a <hi>Living Faith</hi> Saveth; but this we speak of is contrary, it ruins and undoeth men, because it <hi>deceiveth</hi> them: and yet this is all the <hi>Faith</hi> that many have, who yet think that they have something that will stand by them.</p>
            <p>The first thing that I shall do, in handling this point, is to shew in general, That there is such a thing as a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> a Faith that is not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191924:16"/> a true Saving Faith, and yet the Scripture calls it a <hi>Faith,</hi> a <hi>Believing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. See the verse before the Text: <hi>Thou Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievest that there is one God, thou dost well; the Devils also believe and tremble.</hi> The <hi>Heathens</hi> say that there are many Gods: thou art no <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> it is well, so far; yet remember the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils</hi> believe too, and tremble: So then, a man may <hi>believe,</hi> and be <hi>affected</hi> also, with what he doth believe, and yet his <hi>Faith,</hi> for all that, be no other than a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> tho' you should see a man to <hi>believe and tremble;</hi> or, to <hi>believe and rejoyce,</hi> as Mat. 13. 20. this proves not his Eaith to be a lively, or a <hi>Living Faith.</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 3. there is a <hi>lively hope,</hi> or a <hi>living hope,</hi> or an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livening hope, under which, <hi>Faith</hi> is included, from whence this <hi>Hope</hi> ariseth: for <hi>hope</hi> is (as it were) the <hi>Daughter of Faith:</hi> So on the other hand, there is a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> yea, where there is much affection stirring, as will more appear, by and by: when persons find their affections much moved towards Spiritual Things, they are apt to be taken with it, and to conclude that there is some true <hi>Grace</hi> in them, but alas, it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times proves otherwise: a multitude of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices</hi> will not prove true Grace to be. <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. 11. so neither will abundance of <hi>affections</hi> prove a mans Faith to be a lively or a living Faith: In this case, it is not so much the <hi>quantity,</hi> as the <hi>kind</hi> or <hi>quality</hi> that is to be considered. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they miss it much, that think, that <hi>true</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:191924:16"/>
               <hi>Grace</hi> differs from that which we call <hi>common Grace,</hi> only in degree: Let common affections, such as be often found in Unsound Professors, be enlarged never so much, this will not alter a mans Estate God ward; he may be a deeper, and a more profound <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> but this will not make a man sincere; for that which is <hi>naught</hi> can never come to be <hi>good by increasing:</hi> hast thou affections God-ward, so had they. <hi>Isa.</hi> 58. 2. consider then, not so much how great they be, as whether they be of the right kind, or sort: a little true <hi>Gold</hi> will be accepted, when a heap of <hi>Counters</hi> will be rejected wholly, as Coin that will not pass at all. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 24. we read of <hi>True Holiness,</hi> or, <hi>Holiness of Truth:</hi> So there is <hi>True Love,</hi> &amp;c. a little of it is better than <hi>Gold;</hi> but abundance of affections may be towards Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Things, and yet <hi>no Truth;</hi> no Spiritual Life; it is a <hi>Dead</hi> Soul still; and abiding as it is, will be a <hi>Damned</hi> Soul too, e're long.</p>
            <p n="2">2. See Joh. 2. 23, 24. <hi>Many believed in his Name, but Jesus Christ knew them, and would not trust himself with them:</hi> Mark it, it is said, <hi>Many believed in his Name.</hi> Why did not Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himself to them? the reason was, he knew all men; and he knew that their Faith was but a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> and would not hold, and abide the Furnace: for as <hi>Gold is tried</hi> in the Furnace, so shall every mans <hi>Faith</hi> be <hi>tryed,</hi> one time or other. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 7. and <hi>happy are they, whose Faith on tryal, is found unto praise, and honour, and glory,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:191924:17"/>
               <hi>at the Appearing of Christ.</hi> Christ knew all men, and he knew that such as now Cried, <hi>Hosanna to the Son of David,</hi> would some of them e're long, cry, <hi>Crucify him, Crucify him, away with him:</hi> and truly, we may see something of this often, how common and frequent is it for such as for a season were much affected, and taken with the <hi>Word of Christ</hi> (as it is called, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16.) in the Publick Dispensation of it, to turn quite about, and quarrel with it; of such <hi>Paul</hi> complains, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 14, 15, 16. <hi>they received him as an Angel, they could have pluck'd out their Eyes for him once; yet now he was become their Enemy, for telling them the truth;</hi> the case was quite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with them: little do persons think, many times, what they <hi>shall be,</hi> and the reason is, they know not what they <hi>are at present.</hi> 2 King. 8. 12, 13. <hi>Hazael</hi> seemed at present to abhor the thoughts of doing such a great wickedness, as the Prophet foretold that he would do: <hi>Is thy Servant a Dogg, that he should do this great thing?</hi> Alas, he did not know his own <hi>heart,</hi> what a <hi>Dogg</hi> he was, what a furious beast he would prove in time. And thus it is with many, while yet they are under restraints, and feel not what cursed <hi>Hearts,</hi> and <hi>Natures</hi> they have; es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when under common <hi>Convictions,</hi> they cannot think, that they shall ever be, or do, as they see many others do: yet sometimes such as these come to be found among the worst of men: their Faith and Affections issue in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191924:17"/> highest degrees of wickedness: tho' other some are still held under restraints, and they wear out all their time in <hi>Formality,</hi> and in an <hi>Unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Profession</hi> of Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. See Luk. 8. 13. where we read of some, <hi>That receive the Word with joy, and yet they have no root, and for a while believe, and yet fall away in a time of Temptation.</hi> Mark what is said of them: they <hi>Received the Word;</hi> they did not wholly reject it, as many others did; and they received it with <hi>joy</hi> too; and they <hi>believed for a season;</hi> and yet fell away in a time of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for they had <hi>no root;</hi> their Faith was a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> whatever it seemed to be; thus i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> is with many under the Gospel, they are much affected with the <hi>Word</hi> for a time, they hear i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> gladly, as also <hi>Herod</hi> sometime did. <hi>Mark</hi> 6. 20▪ and they shew much <hi>love</hi> to it, as they did, <hi>Ezek</hi> 33. 31. and they <hi>believe</hi> the Word, but it is bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> yet it may deceive not only them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but others too, seeing there is so much joy and affection with it: there are many that have been much taken with their own affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and undone by them; they joy in their <hi>own joy,</hi> and at last <hi>ly down in sorrow;</hi> see Isa 50. <hi>ult. Walk in the light of your fire:</hi> do so a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> long as you will, and if it be never so long, ye<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the end will be to <hi>Ly down in Sorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. See Act 8. 13. <hi>Simon believed, and was bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tised,</hi> &amp;c. yet verse 21, 23. see what is said o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> him; he was <hi>in the gall of bitterness, &amp; in the bon<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:191924:18"/>
               <hi>of Iniquity:</hi> see how much he was wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is said, he <hi>believed,</hi> the Word had some effect in him, and upon him: some entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Word had with him; and he was <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized;</hi> now he makes a <hi>Publick Profession</hi> of the true Religion, and so to do, was in those days a great thing, as much as a mans life, and all he had in this World, was worth: also he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Phillip,</hi> and was much affected with what he saw, <hi>he wondred</hi> it is said, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet <hi>his heart was not right in the sight of God:</hi> in his <hi>own sight</hi> perhaps it was; and many precious ones did hope well of him, for a season: but he was in a miserable condition: he believed, but his Faith was a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> and hence left him, in his sins still; and in them he perished, for ought appears to the contrary. Let us see one Instance more.</p>
            <p n="5">5. See Psal. 106. 12, 13. compared with <hi>Psal.</hi> 78. 35, 37. for in both places he speaks of the same people, and it is said, <hi>They believed his Word, and sang his praise: but soon forgat his Works; they remembred that God was their Rock, and the High God their Redeemer; yet their heart was not right with him.</hi> And how are many wrought upon, when some <hi>Special Providence</hi> helps to set on the word; great <hi>Awakenings,</hi> and strange <hi>Enlightnings</hi> they have; they Seek God, they <hi>Enquire early after him;</hi> there is much Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for they <hi>return,</hi> and these things work on unto a seeming good issue of Faith in Christ as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191924:18"/> their <hi>Redeemer; they remembred that the Lord was their Rock, and their Redeemer,</hi> and yet all is but a <hi>Dead Faith:</hi> thus it is with many.</p>
            <p>When Persons <hi>Conversions</hi> want due, and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expected <hi>Reformations,</hi> we judge their work was not a thorow work; and so when persons have had great <hi>Convictions,</hi> and have been in much trouble, and all dyeth away, after a while, without any work of <hi>Faith</hi> at all, such cannot be in any good, or right way: but when much trouble for sin, and about a mans Estate, issues <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n a work of <hi>Faith,</hi> and comfort from some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise; we hope well of such many times, but if <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t be, (as oft it is) but a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ion is sad, and the <hi>end</hi> like to be misery for ever: If never so many <hi>Promises</hi> come to a mans mind, and if never so much <hi>Comfort</hi> arise <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>here-from; yet if a person do take <hi>comfort</hi> (as many do) and yet not take <hi>Christ,</hi> his comfort <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hall be taken from him, some time or other: yea, if he take <hi>Christ</hi> also, as many do, after a <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ort, yet if it be not by a <hi>Lively Faith,</hi> (and what that is we shall shew) it profits him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hing: many will say, <hi>Lord, Lord, we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hesied in thy Name, and in thy Name have cast out Devils,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet he will profess that he never knew <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hem; and they must depart from him for ever:</hi> see Mat. 7. 21, 22. many think they have <hi>Christ,</hi> who yet indeed fall short of him: not knowing <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>im indeed, <hi>Whom to Know is Life Eternal,</hi> Joh. 17. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. nor knowing the way to him, nor what it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191924:19"/> to believe aright in him: they believe, but their Faith is a <hi>Dead Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The point being thus far confirmed, in the next place, we shall Enquire more particularly, <hi>What</hi> this <hi>Dead Faith</hi> is, and <hi>Why</hi> it is so called; and we must endeavour to make some discovery of it, and to distinguish it from that which is a <hi>true Saving Justifying Faith:</hi> Now the Apostle tells us, that <hi>Faith without Works is dead:</hi> And the Enquiry may be, How may we understand that?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ</hi> 1 It is a sure Evidence that a mans <hi>Faith</hi> is a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> when it is <hi>without Works;</hi> or when it is <hi>alone:</hi> Indeed <hi>Works</hi> don't <hi>Justify</hi> us, they have no hand in that at all: it is <hi>Faith only</hi> that Justifies us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 28.<hi>—A man i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Justified by Faith without the deeds of the Law</hi> Rom. 5. 1. <hi>Therefore being Justified by Faith,</hi> &amp;c<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yet it is also true, that that <hi>Faith</hi> which is <hi>alone</hi> is not a <hi>Justifying Faith:</hi> and therefore as Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>text, verse 18. <hi>Shew me thy faith without thy works, saith the Apostle.</hi> This is the miserabl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> delusion that many are held in, they believe (a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they say) and they trust in Christ, and ther<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they rest themselves, but they take no due car<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>good works:</hi> ask them where their <hi>Faith</hi> is they do think they can tell you: but alas! wher<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> are their <hi>Works?</hi> where is their <hi>Repentance,</hi> thei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Mourning</hi> for <hi>Sin,</hi> where is thei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mortification</hi> of Corruptions? See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> where is their <hi>daily Watch,</hi> and <hi>Warfare;</hi> thei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:191924:19"/>
               <hi>Fighting,</hi> and <hi>Wrestling,</hi> of which the Scripture speaks? Where be their <hi>Tears,</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Cryes,</hi> and <hi>Sighs</hi> and <hi>Groans Unutterable?</hi> these alas are not; and what saith our Apostle in this case? <hi>Wilt thou know, Oh! vain man, that Faith without Works is dead? hast thou Faith, shew it by thy Works:</hi> it is in <hi>vain</hi> to talk of <hi>Faith</hi> without <hi>Works</hi> answerable: when persons profess, that they believe, and trust in Christ, but do not <hi>walk</hi> in any measure answerably, they deceive themselves; yet many such there be, <hi>They Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess to know God, but in works deny him.</hi> Tit. 1. <hi>ult.</hi> they say they believe in Christ, but their <hi>Conversation</hi> saith otherwise; and their secret <hi>Walk</hi> is otherwise; Oh! it is a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> however such <hi>deceive their own hearts:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not every kind, or sort of <hi>good works</hi> that will evidence a mans <hi>Faith</hi> not to be a <hi>dead</hi> faith: for they in <hi>Psal.</hi> 78. forenamed, <hi>sought God, they returned, they enquired early after God.</hi> Also <hi>Herod</hi> Mark 6. 20. <hi>heard John gladly, and did many things.</hi> So those in Isa. 58. 2. <hi>Sought him daily, and asked of him the Ordinances of Justice; they took delight in approaching unto God:</hi> yet were they not upright before God: there are many that are full of <hi>good works. Isa.</hi> 1. 11. They have a <hi>multitude</hi> of them; they are good for the <hi>matter</hi> of them: and yet God abhors them, because they proceed from no other than a <hi>Dead Faith.</hi> See at large, Isa. 1. 13, 14, 15. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they made great account of their <hi>Works,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191924:20"/> they would not have so abounded in them; yet the Lord did not accept them: nay, all was <hi>Iniquity, a Trouble to him, and he was wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to bear them.</hi> Some are full of <hi>good works,</hi> (as we may call them) and of good desires, and of good affections; and yet their <hi>Faith</hi> is naught, it is but a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> and this is so plain from the fore-named Instances, as that there is no room to make any objection. And those <hi>good works,</hi> (as they seem to be) when searched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are but <hi>dead works,</hi> tho' seemingly never so full of <hi>Life;</hi> and hence they are all as rotten, and unsound things. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1. we read of <hi>dead works:</hi> and indeed all a mans <hi>works</hi> are such, until he come to a true <hi>Faith</hi> in Christ; his most affectionate <hi>Prayers,</hi> yea, his highest Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are but <hi>dead works;</hi> tho' a person afflict (not his Body only, but) his very Soul; yet God will <hi>take no knowledge of it.</hi> Isa. 58. 3. and how many be in such a case as this is, and how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable are they, <hi>wretched, naked, and know it not.</hi> Rev. 3. 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>works</hi> that the Apostle here speaks of are not such as are only <hi>Moral,</hi> but <hi>Evangelical,</hi> and in that sense <hi>good: Works Evangelically good,</hi> will evidence a true <hi>Faith,</hi> but no other works, how many, or how good soever they be: We shall therefore open this particular a little, and shew when a persons <hi>works</hi> may be said to be <hi>Evangelically good:</hi> for I would not mention any thing to Enlighten our way, and then by men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191924:20"/> a thing in <hi>general</hi> only, leave the matter in a manner as much in the dark as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>Two things then make our good works to be <hi>Evangelically Good.</hi> (1.) They must be <hi>from:</hi> and (2) <hi>Unto</hi> the Lord. And if they be the first, they will be the latter: we shall therefore chiefly consider the former, <hi>viz.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our <hi>good works</hi> are <hi>from the Lord,</hi> and shew what is the import, and meaning of that expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.—Now they are from <hi>him, when we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him,</hi> and <hi>deny our selves</hi> in all we do: when so to do is the frame and disposition of our hearts: when there is that <hi>Principle</hi> in us, that Enableth us (through Divine Assistance) so to do; and disposeth our hearts to desire that we actually, and daily do it, tasting (at least at times) a precious <hi>sweetness</hi> in that <hi>way of living and doing,</hi> together with a dislike of the contrary in our selves. See Isa. 26. 12. <hi>Lord</hi> (say they) <hi>thou hast wrought all our works for us, or in us.</hi> I <hi>Live,</hi> saith Paul, <hi>yet not I but Christ lives in me.</hi> Gal. 2. 20. Also see Gal. 5. 22, 23. All our <hi>good works</hi> are <hi>fruits of the Spirit;</hi> and God would have us own all our <hi>fruits</hi> to be from him: hence he tells us, Hos. 14. 8. <hi>From me is thy fruit found.</hi> So then if you think you have <hi>good works,</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether you can <hi>deny</hi> your selves in them, and <hi>acknowledge</hi> God in them all: Perhaps you say, <hi>I Live,</hi> but do you say also, <hi>yet not I but Christ,</hi> &amp;c. If your works be from <hi>God</hi> (in that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191924:21"/> sense we are speaking of) <hi>God</hi> will own them, accept them &amp; reward them: what is <hi>his own,</hi> he will acknowledge and reward it in us, though it be never so little, and never so much des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pised in our own eyes, or in the eyes of others. Zech. 4. 10. <hi>The day of small things</hi> is apt to be <hi>despised:</hi> yet what are (in some sense) <hi>small things,</hi> are sometimes <hi>great things: Poor Prayers</hi> as we count them, small performances, little weak things, are <hi>great things,</hi> when they are fruits of the Spirit; works of faith and love; and they will when we meet them again another day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be such, as we can hardly acknowledge them to have been ours: Math. 25. 37<hi>—Lord when saw we thee an hungry:</hi> Lord, when did we <hi>Pray,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Believe</hi> in such manner, and perform such duties? &amp; then shall all be opened, and made plain; and the <hi>Lord</hi> shall have the <hi>Glory</hi> of his <hi>own works,</hi> in his, and <hi>they</hi> the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>But some may say, who is there that will not own all his <hi>Works</hi> to be of <hi>God,</hi> and deny himself in them? This may seem to be no great matter: did not the Pharisee do so. Luk. 18. 11. <hi>God, I thank thee,</hi> &amp;c. he seems to acknowledge <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Grace,</hi> in what he was, and did, or had attained unto in Religion: and so it is with many still, who are yet unsound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. A <hi>verbal</hi> acknowledgment is an easy thing many times, and especially when a <hi>Good Education</hi> leads us to own the truth; many have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:191924:21"/> a <hi>form of knowledge, and of the truth, being instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 2. 18, 20. to <hi>speak good words,</hi> is no hard matter: this many can do in Praying, in Preaching, and in discourse with others, and have excellent <hi>Gifts</hi> indeed, who yet are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the thing that we are speaking of; and there be divers things that concur to it: it may be a man hath been <hi>well Educated,</hi> he hath lived where this truth hath been generally acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all; visibly opposed by none, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently inculcated; and hence he goes with the stream, he gives a <hi>common assent</hi> to the truth, and owns in words, <hi>That a man of himself, is Nothing that is good.</hi> Also <hi>common experience</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es persons something of this: there is hardly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, that endeavours to do any thing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious works, but he finds something of his <hi>ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> to do what he should: unsound ones have some experience of themselves as well as others; and many go far, that yet fall short at last: this <hi>Paul</hi> knew; and hence that 1 Cor. 9. 27. a man may be able to teach others, and yet himself be a <hi>Cast away:</hi> Education, common experience, and <hi>industry</hi> meeting together, may, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less doth carry many a man far, and make him see in somewhat, nay, <hi>much</hi> in Religion, when as he is but like them. Rev. 3. 1. <hi>Who had a name <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o live, but were dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A thorow <hi>sight</hi> of a mans own <hi>nothingness</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s a <hi>great thing,</hi> and very far different from what <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s in unsound ones. I shall endeavour to make <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ome discovery of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:191924:22"/> 1. It is not only <hi>Notional,</hi> or <hi>Doctrinal,</hi> but it is <hi>Experimental</hi> also: a man doth not only hear it, or read it in some good book, but he doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>feel,</hi> and <hi>find</hi> it, as he said, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 21. <hi>I find then a Law,</hi> &amp;c. how did he know that there was such a Law of Sin in him? such a sinful heart, and nature, why, saith he, <hi>I find</hi> it: he had bitter experience of it: he saw it not only in some book: <hi>but in his members, warring there,</hi> verse 23. he <hi>felt</hi> it in himself; and so must you <hi>feel</hi> your own Nothingness and Inability, or else you will never be throughly convinced of it, and suitably affected with it. A man may hear it, and be affected with it, but this goes but a little way; till a man comes to find, and feel, there will want <hi>deepness,</hi> Mat. 13. 5. as the <hi>Stony Ground</hi> did: when a man <hi>sees</hi> and <hi>feels,</hi> this will be something indeed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This knowledge and thorow conviction of a persons own Nothingness, uses not to come <hi>easily:</hi> a man is brought to it through much <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty,</hi> and <hi>opposition:</hi> that which is <hi>easily</hi> gotten, is <hi>hardly good:</hi> Mat. 7. 14. but it may be you come <hi>lightly</hi> by your knowledge of your selves; Oh! take heed that you be not deceived, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, many be. Now I say, it is not <hi>easily</hi> obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that upon divers accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that the heart of man is <hi>Naturally</hi> so averse unto it: there is a marvellous opposition in mans <hi>carnal heart</hi> against it: it is impossible but that it must be an exceeding <hi>bitter,</hi> yea, a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191924:22"/>
               <hi>killing</hi> thing to a mans carnal heart to see his heart, so far forth as it is <hi>carnal;</hi> and every mans heart is so, in some degree at least, and most mens hearts are wholly and only <hi>carnal:</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 1. Such as are in Christ are yet <hi>carnal</hi> in some measure, but others are <hi>wholly.</hi> so: and hence some opposition against this knowledge, and the increase of it, will be found in the best; how much more in those that are yet <hi>Unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> in whom as yet pride, ignorance, and secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity do reign, with divers other lusts, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions? To illustrate this a little: Suppose a man <hi>Rich</hi> in this World; or suppose that he have but a little, and that which he hath, whatever it be, got with <hi>much labour,</hi> and difficulty, will such an one <hi>easily</hi> part with what he hath, and sit down upon a dunghil? or if a man hath thought himself to be <hi>Rich,</hi> at least worth something, if such an one come suddenly to see himself to have been <hi>deceived,</hi> and not worth one mite, how will it trouble him? especially, when he sees at present no way to recover what is lost; nay, sees that he can never do it. Such like is the case we are now speaking of. Some Ungodly Ones think, they are <hi>Rich</hi> in Spiritual Things. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17. and whatever any may say, or think to the contrary, there is no secure, unconvinced Sinner, but what thinks he hath <hi>more</hi> than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he hath; most think they have <hi>ability</hi> to turn to God, and promise themselves that in their own time they will do it: and what <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:191924:23"/> do they make in times of sickness, danger, when fears are upon them: Others please them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in thinking that they be bad, yet not <hi>so</hi> bad, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and hence hope to deal with God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Pardon</hi> of Sin, and acceptance at an <hi>easy rate:</hi> however there is something in <hi>themselves,</hi> upon which they have a secret dependance, and relyance; and are not themselves aware how it is with them. Now for such an one to be strip'd of all, to suffer the <hi>loss of all,</hi> yea of those things which were once <hi>gain</hi> to him, as he speaks, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7, 8. this will not be easy; nay, it wil be a <hi>killing thing:</hi> for these things are a mans <hi>Life,</hi> until a better Way be discovered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Rom. 7. 9. <hi>I was alive once,</hi> (that is in his own conceit,) <hi>but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I dyed.</hi> Consider then; Know you what it is to <hi>Dy?</hi> nay, to be <hi>Slain,</hi> as verse 11.<hi>—It slew me:</hi> Is it a light or small matter? Oh! when the real tryal shall come, it will be found otherwise; nay, it may be, you know nothing of that LIFE that should be taken away; and so are <hi>alive</hi> still, as <hi>Paul</hi> once was, but indeed <hi>dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In that persons will hardly believe, or be thorowly convinced of their own <hi>Nothingness,</hi> until they have tryed the matter; they will first <hi>try</hi> whether they can do nothing, before they will be convinced throughly that so it is indeed. Nothing but their own <hi>Experience</hi> will convince them, for what else can be supposed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191924:23"/> to do it? there is nothing in themselves to do it, until <hi>experience</hi> do it: there is something of the <hi>Law</hi> in all mens hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14. out not one tittle of <hi>this:</hi> man in his first estate was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keep the <hi>Law</hi> of God; and he knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that he can do so still, save what he doth <hi>experience</hi> to the contrary. And very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will be believe his own <hi>experience</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; he will <hi>try,</hi> and <hi>try,</hi> and <hi>try</hi> again, and <hi>try</hi> the matter out to the utmost, before that he will indeed yield the case, and sit down hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled under that acknowledgment: <hi>viz. I am Nothing, I can do nothing that is good.</hi> It is true, the <hi>word</hi> shews it plainly, that we in our selves are <hi>nothing;</hi> and that in us <hi>dwells no good thing:</hi> but the <hi>word</hi> in this thing is no more believed than in other things; and <hi>Ignorance, Atheism</hi> and <hi>Unbelief</hi>are ruling or reigning things, in every Unconverted mans heart. Hence tell a man what you will, and let him in words own what he will concerning his own <hi>Nothingness;</hi> yea, though he think he doth believe it; yet when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he shall be in good earnest about his Soul, by a powerful awakening, he will try what he can do, before he will yield, and fit down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conviction before mentioned; he will <hi>work,</hi> and he will <hi>try;</hi> yea he will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, until he have wrought himself unto <hi>death,</hi> and then will be own himself to be a <hi>dead man;</hi> and then, and not till then, will God shew him the <hi>way unto life:</hi> he must <hi>despair</hi> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191924:24"/> himself, before he will, or can indeed <hi>believe</hi> in <hi>Christ.</hi> Now a man doth not easily come to take such pains, as we have been speaking of; it must be a <hi>great awakening</hi> to bring him to it; they must be <hi>hard driven</hi> that shall <hi>travel</hi> thus far, especially if we consider what opposition is in all mens hearts against any thing which is good, or tendeth thereunto: <hi>Sin</hi> within, and <hi>Satan</hi> without, will do their utmost to hinder: it is folly to expect any other.</p>
            <p>And further consider this: we say, persons will <hi>try</hi> what they can do, when awakened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will be convinced that they can do nothing: for how can it be otherwise? what shall a poor Sinner do? Shall he <hi>sit still,</hi> and ly quietly in his Sins? No, he <hi>shall not,</hi> he <hi>cannot:</hi> the terror of the Lord makes him afraid; there is <hi>no rest in his Soul now by reason of his sin,</hi> and the danger that he is in thereby: well then, shall he fall in with the <hi>way of the Gospel?</hi> He should indeed, but he cannot: for he is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thereof, as they were. <hi>Rom.</hi> 20. 3. though he have heard much of it, yet he understands i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not; though he think he doth, yet he doth not; nay, till God shew it, he cannot know it, it is <hi>foolishness</hi> to him, 1 Cor. 2. 14. Hence the first thing a man doth naturally when awakened, is to seek to <hi>Save himself,</hi> and when he finds he cannot, he will despair in himself, and is so fa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> prepared for to hear of a <hi>new, and living way,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which nature knoweth <hi>nothing,</hi> though of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191924:24"/>
               <hi>Law</hi> it knows something. So then, this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a mans <hi>nothingness</hi> doth not use to come easily.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This knowledge of a mans self, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingness, is an <hi>heart affecting thing:</hi> it goes to a mans <hi>heart,</hi> when he is made to see his own heart, and to know himself: not only the <hi>head</hi> is enlightned, but the heart is much affected also. There be many that have much knowledge in their <hi>heads,</hi> but they have <hi>hardned hearts;</hi> they have <hi>head knowledge,</hi> but they want <hi>heart know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> And hence that in Jer. 24. 7. <hi>I will give them an heart to know &amp;c.</hi> But that which I am now to open, and shew is this, <hi>viz.</hi> that this self knowledge, <hi>or knowledge of ones self</hi> is an heart affecting thing. And so it is, for (1.) It fills a man with <hi>shame;</hi> when he comes to see him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, he is <hi>ashamed</hi> of himself: as he said when he saw and viewed his own, and others sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. Ezr. 9. 6. <hi>O my God, I am ashamed, &amp; blush.</hi> And every new discovery of a mans own self to himself hath something of this Effect on him. In <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 18—We read of the <hi>shame</hi> of a Persons <hi>Nakedness:</hi> when Persons are strip'd <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> they are <hi>ashamed:</hi> and so it is much more, when Persons are made to see their own <hi>Spiritual Nakedness,</hi> or <hi>Nothingness,</hi> they will then be <hi>asham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Jer. 2. 26. <hi>A thief is ashamed when found,</hi> or discovered. So is a Person when he comes to have his own heart <hi>discovered</hi> to him; and he that never was <hi>ashamed</hi> of himself, never yet <hi>saw</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:191924:25"/> himself as he ought to see. (2.) It <hi>abaseth</hi> a man, it lowereth and takes down a mans Spirit in him, which is naturally very <hi>high,</hi> and <hi>lifted up in him:</hi> it makes and keeps a man <hi>poor in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as Math. 5. 3. There are some such; but Persons do never come to be <hi>such,</hi> until they come to <hi>see themselves.</hi> See what <hi>Paul</hi> saith of himself. Eph. 3. 8. he calls himself, <hi>less than the least of all Saints:</hi> and it was no complement; he speaks his heart in those words; and every one that sees himself aright can say after him, in some measure. But in <hi>Preparation work</hi> a man doth not see himself to be <hi>Little,</hi> but, <hi>Nothing,</hi> quite <hi>Nothing</hi> that is good, and this wonderfully <hi>abas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> a man, and lays him very low, in his own eyes: and it is meet that he should be in <hi>his own eyes,</hi> what he <hi>is indeed:</hi> for why should he live in ignorance, &amp; in self deceivings? (3.) It even <hi>breaks the heart</hi> in a man, when he sees <hi>himself,</hi> and also the <hi>Evil</hi> that is in <hi>Sin.</hi> There is such a thing as a <hi>broken heart;</hi> though few ever feel it, and but a few understand what it is. <hi>Isa.</hi> 61. 1. And this <hi>sight</hi> breaks the <hi>heart;</hi> it doth not only ashame, and abase a man, but breaks the heart, or doth give a great stroke towards it; and this is a great thing: For (1.) When the heart is indeed once <hi>broken,</hi> all the world cannot <hi>heal</hi> it again: Until the <hi>Blood of Christ</hi> be applyed, there is <hi>no healing:</hi> If Christ don't heal, there is none else that can. <hi>Daubing,</hi> as the Prophet calls it <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 10. is indeed very dangerous. But in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191924:25"/> this case it availes nothing, when God wounds, and breaks the heart indeed, there is none that can <hi>heal,</hi> but he only that <hi>wounded:</hi> it is his work. (2.) The <hi>Spirit failes,</hi> if the Lord dont step in and help. For both these, See <hi>Isa.</hi> 57. 15, 16. &amp; 61. 1. Now then consider these things. Did you ever know, or feel what a <hi>broken heart</hi> is? if not, you never saw your own <hi>nothingness</hi> aright: and all your <hi>Good Works,</hi> are but an Abomination before the Lord, how many and good soever they be, or seem to be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This knowledge of a mans <hi>Nothingness,</hi> makes him to <hi>abhor</hi> his own <hi>Righteousnass,</hi> and to magnify that of <hi>Christ.</hi> That is, this ever fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows there upon, when God will do good unto any: you have both these in that one place: See <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8. (1.) He accounts all that he had before he knew Christ, as <hi>Loss;</hi> yea as <hi>Dung:</hi> his <hi>Good Works,</hi> his Prayers, his Tears, his good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, or what ever else he had of like nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he <hi>knew Christ:</hi> what doth he do with them all? he throws them all out upon the <hi>Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill;</hi> all is <hi>loss,</hi> and <hi>dross,</hi> and <hi>dung,</hi> in comparison of Christ, and the knowledge of him. Let such as read consider; Sirs, do you know what this means, to <hi>suffer loss,</hi> yea the <hi>loss of all things,</hi> yea of those things, which once were accounted <hi>gain,</hi> to account them <hi>loss,</hi> and <hi>dross?</hi> It may be these things are a <hi>Mystery</hi> unto you, and you know them not: you have no <hi>experience,</hi> and so, no <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstanding</hi> of them; consider the matter well
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:191924:26"/> (2.) He magnifies the <hi>Righteousness of Christ:</hi> that was glorious in his eyes: <hi>the Excellency of the Knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord.</hi> Oh! Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; was the <hi>Righteousness of Christ,</hi> ever, the most glorious thing in your eye, that ever you saw; or diddest ever admire, and wonder at it. He is <hi>wonderful,</hi> Isa. 9. 6. It is his Name; and <hi>as is his Name, so is He:</hi> not only in <hi>himself;</hi> but in some measure, in the eyes of those that are <hi>His.</hi> See also 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>To such as believe, he is precious:</hi> and unless when they slumber, and neglect him, he is more and more so, unto them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This knowledge of a mans own <hi>Nothingness,</hi> is a <hi>growing thing:</hi> it still increaseth; and a Christian still groweth (as one may say) a greater <hi>Nothing.</hi> You will say, perhaps, how can this be? when a man is brought to <hi>Nothing,</hi> he can go no further: there is not any thing beyond <hi>that.</hi> Answ. Yes, there is a further, a fuller, a clearer discovery, of <hi>that</hi> which he saw before: for in this life, there is <hi>nothing perfect.</hi> And consider it, there is no <hi>growth</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> or in any good thing without a <hi>growth</hi> in <hi>this:</hi> wherefore let him that heareth consider it well: have you been <hi>growing in this thing?</hi> have you been <hi>growing</hi> less, and less since your first Conversion, and can you now say, more sensibly than ever, as he did, Phil. 3. 8. <hi>Who am less, than the least of all Saints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing is to shew, <hi>why</hi> this faith that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ath not <hi>works, Evangelically good,</hi> to be the <hi>fruits</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:191924:26"/> of it, is called a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> tho' it have with it, never so many <hi>affections and works,</hi> that are <hi>moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good?</hi> The reason is because all those <hi>works</hi> that are not <hi>Evangelically good,</hi> are but <hi>Dead works,</hi> though they may seem to be full of <hi>Life;</hi> and as the <hi>works</hi> are but <hi>Dead works,</hi> so the <hi>Faith</hi> is but a <hi>Dead Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But how can <hi>Fasting</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Mourning</hi> and <hi>Reforming,</hi> and the like, be <hi>Dead works?</hi> and how may it appear that sometimes they are such? and how may we discover and discern it, when they be such?</p>
            <p>To all this I Answer, in the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That such works are sometimes no better, no other than <hi>Dead works,</hi> may appear thus: <hi>viz.</hi> That God neither <hi>accepts</hi> the <hi>works,</hi> nor the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> with whom they are found: this is the case many times: and see, what God saith of such works, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. 13, 14, 15. He calleth them <hi>Vain, Iniquity, and Abomination;</hi> He saith, <hi>I cannot away with them; my Soul hateth them, they are a trouble to me, I am weary to bear them; and when you make many Prayers, I will not hear.</hi> Why doth the Lord speak thus of them? Oh! they were all <hi>Dead works;</hi> and hence as lothsome to him, as a <hi>Dead,</hi> rotten Carcase is unto us, and more also. By the way, Note, Oh! what disappointment will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meet with, who now think themselves <hi>Rich,</hi> as they did, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17. And in the issue, all are but <hi>Dead works;</hi> their <hi>best works</hi> as a lothsome
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:191924:27"/> Carrion. See an other example, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 11, 12, 14. He thought with himself (and <hi>thanks God</hi> for it too) that he <hi>was not as other men;</hi> &amp; yet indeed he was <hi>Nothing;</hi> blind and naked; though he <hi>fasted twice in a week,</hi> and <hi>payed tithes of all that he had;</hi> though he was <hi>not as other men,</hi> yet God accepted him <hi>not:</hi> all his works were <hi>Dead works,</hi> otherwise surely he had had accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God: who accepts of us, a little, so it be <hi>Sincere:</hi> Yea <hi>two mites,</hi> is accounted a <hi>great deal,</hi> if it be all we have; much more than the abundance of self-righteous <hi>Pharisees.</hi> The most lively, and affectionate Prayers, &amp; performances of unsound, of unregenerate ones, are but <hi>Dead works:</hi> though at present Persons don't see, or think them to be such, yet indeed they are such, and will at last appear to be such: and how much so ever such may <hi>justify themselves; yet God knows their hearts:</hi> and oftentimes, <hi>that which is highly esteemed among men, is an abomination in the sight of God:</hi> as Luk. 16. 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. These works are <hi>dead works</hi> in regard of <hi>Spiritual Life,</hi> whatever there be of any <hi>other Life</hi> in them. In a true Christian there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Life. (1.) That whereby he lives as a <hi>man.</hi> (2.) That whereby he lives as a <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> or as a <hi>sound Believer.</hi> Of this latter sort, there is nothing in Unconverted persons: see <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. a man, as he is a <hi>man,</hi> can labour, and reason, and take pains; and he hath many natural affections, as of fear, love, delight, sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:191924:27"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and these affections may be stirred, and moved (tho' as yet there be not true Grace) so as to set a man on to the doing of many things that are <hi>morally good,</hi> though there be no <hi>Spiritual Life:</hi> See Mark 6. 20. <hi>Herod heard the Word gladly, and did many things:</hi> and yet he was still <hi>Dead</hi> in his Sin. And yet this is all the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version</hi> which many have, and in which they rest: <hi>viz.</hi> through the power of <hi>common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions,</hi> they have their natural affections stirred up, and drawn forth, even towards things in themselves, spiritual, and good; &amp; hence a great Change follows, both in the Conversation <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,</hi> and in the Heart <hi>Inwardly,</hi> yet no <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Life; another heart</hi> there is, and <hi>another man:</hi> as 1 Sam. 10. 6, 9. but not a <hi>New Heart,</hi> which is necessary unto Salvation, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 31. there is nothing of that <hi>new man,</hi> of which we read, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 24. he that is thus wrought upon, is not a <hi>New,</hi> though <hi>another man:</hi> and though he walk on now, in a way not so manifestly filthy and vile; yet really and indeed, the end thereof is the <hi>Wayes of Death.</hi> as <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 12. And this woful priviledge he hath, <hi>viz.</hi> he can go down to the pit, more <hi>quietly,</hi> and with less disturbance then otherwise he could. Some make it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest what they are: Isa. 3. 9. 2 Tim. 5. 24. others (as it were) <hi>Steal down to Hell</hi> more quietly; others don't suspect them, and they themselves hope all is well, until a fearful dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>appointment. Let them see what must be thei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Everlasting Condition.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:191924:28"/> 3. <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> is an effect of <hi>Creating Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:</hi> where this Life is, there is a <hi>new Creation,</hi> a <hi>new Creature, Eph.</hi> 4. 24. 2 Cor. 5. 17. <hi>If any man be in Christ, he is a New Creature,</hi> as we have already hinted; not the <hi>old one</hi> altered, and in many respects amended, but a <hi>New One.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore consider this, it may be you are much, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps very much altered and amended, perhaps all round about, gaze upon the <hi>Change,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rejoyce to see it, but is there a <hi>New Creation;</hi> otherwise all thy <hi>works</hi> are but <hi>dead works;</hi> tho' never so good, and glorious in thine own eyes, or in the eyes of others: Oh! take heed, that you don't rest in <hi>Changes,</hi> though never so great, without a <hi>New Creation,</hi> which brings in not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly another, but a <hi>New Life.</hi> And if any one say, but how shall we know whether there be in us, this <hi>New Creation,</hi> and so any <hi>Spiritual Life,</hi> or not? I answer, attend to and consider what followeth.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Spiritual Life,</hi> may be discovered, or enquired after, in considering these things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is brought out of <hi>Death: i. e.</hi> where was nothing but <hi>Death,</hi> there is now <hi>Life;</hi> and the Soul is made sensible that it was once <hi>dead,</hi> if now it be <hi>alive,</hi> Eph. 2. 1. <hi>Ye were dead.</hi> That they were so is certain, but he speaks of it, as of a thing which they knew full well: you that never knew and felt your <hi>Spiritual Death,</hi> have none of this <hi>Spiritual Life:</hi> you have it may be had Convictions, and that many and great also;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:191924:28"/> and you have been <hi>wounded</hi> much, but never <hi>slain,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 11. you have found your selves weak and feeble, and that of your selves you could not do what you should, nor what (you think) you would; but you never found your selves <hi>dead,</hi> quite <hi>dead in Sin,</hi> and <hi>shut up under Sin.</hi> as Gal. 3. 22. if so, it is to be feared, that you are <hi>dead</hi> still: and whatever <hi>life,</hi> or <hi>religious liveliness</hi> be in you, yet that there is no <hi>Spiritual Life.</hi> And to open this a little further, consider these things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When a man sees himself <hi>dead in sin,</hi> as he must see, if good come unto him, it is by a <hi>Spirit of Conviction</hi> that he sees it: it is by a <hi>Light</hi> that powerfully breaks in upon the Soul: it is made to see, whether it will or no; there is now put forth a <hi>power</hi> irresistable, and hence comes a <hi>light</hi> unavoidable, shining into the heart; for could persons shut their eyes, and avoid this light, they would surely do it: but now, that which perhaps a person had <hi>heard,</hi> and <hi>read,</hi> full many a time, and <hi>knew</hi> it <hi>doctrinally,</hi> he now <hi>knows</hi> it otherwise: it is now (in some measure at least) plain, clear, evident unto him; in that there is both <hi>light</hi> and <hi>experience</hi> to shew it; it is a thing both <hi>seen</hi> and <hi>felt,</hi> as Rom. 7. 10. <hi>I found to be unto death</hi> See verse 21, 23. <hi>I find, I see:</hi> he <hi>found</hi> and <hi>felt,</hi> and <hi>saw;</hi> so it is in this case; it may be you think you have <hi>seen,</hi> but if you have not <hi>found</hi> and <hi>felt</hi> your own <hi>deadness,</hi> the rest will profit little.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:191924:29"/> 2. When a man sees this his <hi>deadness</hi> aright, it may be truly said, that he <hi>sees what he did not see</hi> before. Now that the <hi>Spirit</hi> is come to convince a person, he sees <hi>that,</hi> and sees <hi>so,</hi> as all his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reading, studying, could never shew him, before the <hi>Spirit of Conviction</hi> came upon him: See <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 8. it is the <hi>Spirit</hi> that <hi>convinceth of Sin;</hi> and so of our <hi>deadness</hi> in it: it may be, you think you have seen your own <hi>deadness:</hi> but I say, how came you to see it? is it by your own <hi>abilities,</hi> making improvement of means? or have you also had a <hi>Spirit of Conviction</hi> come upon you, to shew it to you? is it a work of the <hi>Spirit?</hi> is it that which you did not once see, and could not have seen, had not a work of the <hi>Spirit</hi> shewn it to you, nay would not have seen, had not a powerful work of the <hi>Spirit</hi> prevailed against all opposition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it; either from the <hi>corruption</hi> of the heart within, which make no little opposition; or from the <hi>Evil One</hi> without, who also hinders what he can? for as in other respects, so in this also, the <hi>God of this World doth blind men.</hi> 2 Cor. 44.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When a man sees his <hi>Deadness</hi> aright, then that <hi>Life</hi> which he once had, or seemeth to have had, is taken away from him. Rom. 7. 9. <hi>I was alive once.</hi> i. e. in his own conceit. So is every natural man <hi>alive,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> was, what ever he saith to the contrary. Now then consider this, hath that <hi>Life</hi> that once you had been <hi>taken away?</hi> yea the things that were once <hi>gain</hi> to you, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7. In <hi>Death</hi> there is a <hi>Privation of Life:</hi> what
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:191924:29"/>
               <hi>Life</hi> have you been <hi>deprived</hi> of? <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>the Commandment came, sin revived, and I dyed:</hi> can you say so too?</p>
            <p n="4">4. When a man comes to see himself not only <hi>sick &amp; weak,</hi> but also <hi>Dead,</hi> he is wonderfully <hi>affected</hi> with it. When he knew it only by <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say,</hi> it did not so much affect him, but <hi>now</hi> he is much moved at it: and it is a time of great difficulty and <hi>distress</hi> with the Soul; and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diverse accounts: For (1.) A Person now hath lost all his former <hi>hopes:</hi> that is, his presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and self righteous hopes. He was full of <hi>them</hi> once, and had <hi>none other:</hi> but now they are gone, they are lost, they are <hi>cut off:</hi> as they said in another case, Ezek. 37. 11. <hi>Our Bones are dryed, our hope is lost; we are cut off for our parts.</hi> The ground-work, and foundation of all former <hi>hopes</hi> faileth: A poor Creature thought that he <hi>was</hi> something that is good, or could <hi>do</hi> something, or <hi>get</hi> something: and he had light and slighty thoughts of <hi>Sin,</hi> and of <hi>God;</hi> he counted that he could easily deal with him, about his <hi>Salvation:</hi> but now he finds it far otherwise than he thought. And indeed all that <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ones, and unsound Professors have, ariseth chiefly from, <hi>a secret Contempt of God,</hi> in their hearts, and <hi>slighty thoughts of sin.</hi> See Psal. 50 21. <hi>Thou thoughtest I was altogether such an one as thy self.</hi> Ungodly ones dont <hi>know</hi> God, and hence don't <hi>fear</hi> him aright: And whatever any of them pretend or think, <hi>Atheistical Principles</hi> are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:191924:30"/> predominate, and reign in them. (2.) It is a time of distress with the Soul now: because he sees his <hi>danger</hi> is <hi>real, present, great;</hi> and he sees no way of escape: all his own wayes utterly fail him: and though there be <hi>a way of escape,</hi> yet he sees it not: God hath not yet discovered it to him. He is therefore in a sad case, in his own account and reckoning: he is going unto destruction; he is in the <hi>way of Death;</hi> he is under <hi>Wrath,</hi> and <hi>God is angry</hi> with him: and he sees no way of escape: and hence he cannot but be much affected <hi>now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> A Person comes to find and feel his <hi>Deadness,</hi> by the irritation of <hi>Corruption;</hi> the stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it up. Rom. 7. 9. <hi>When the Commandment came, sin revived, and I dyed.</hi> Many Lusts that were not seen before, now appear and shew themselves: so that a person finds himself to be such as once he little thought he was; and it is with him in this case, much like as it is with a <hi>sick</hi> man, that grows worse and worse, until he is <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Dead.</hi> He sees more and more of his own <hi>Sinfulness,</hi> until he see himself to be <hi>quite dead, in trespasses and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns.</hi> O consider these things, and weigh them deeply in your secret thoughts: you (it may be) hope you have some <hi>Spiritual Life,</hi> but how came you by it? was it brought out of <hi>Death?</hi> when did you see, and feel your selves <hi>quite dead in sin?</hi> you perhaps think your selves to be <hi>alive,</hi> but it may be, it is no otherwise then <hi>Paul</hi> was afore his Conversion. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:191924:30"/>
               <hi>I was alive:</hi> how was that? he was brought up at the feet of one that was a <hi>Doctor of the Law:</hi> Yes, and he profited much in his own Religion: but it was with <hi>him,</hi> as now a days it is with <hi>many</hi> that have a good Educatin; he was a <hi>forward Professor</hi> indeed, but without a powerful, <hi>killing work of the Law;</hi> and what he did in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting of the Church, he did it in his ignorance and in a <hi>zeal of God.</hi> See Phil. 3. 6. You have a work, it may be, unto much Conviction, and unto great awakenings, but not such as to shew you THIS DEATH: and hence though you have been much <hi>wounded,</hi> yet you have recovered again to Security by <hi>false comfort:</hi> you never came to <hi>Dy,</hi> and so are <hi>Dead still;</hi> and your <hi>best works</hi> are <hi>Dead works,</hi> and how sad is that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Where this <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> is in any, there is a <hi>double life.</hi> This we have hinted at before. See it further opened now: from that place, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20.<hi>—The life which I now live in the flesh.</hi> He now lived a <hi>life,</hi> which befoe he did not. So that where <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> is, there is a <hi>New Life,</hi> a <hi>double life.</hi> Mark, that I say not an <hi>other life</hi> only, but a <hi>new</hi> one: for in many unsound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>▪ there is a very great <hi>Change;</hi> an <hi>other</hi> man, and an <hi>other</hi> lise, but not a <hi>new</hi> one. The distinction here is good, and founded upon the word of God, as hath been already shewen. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 9. If a man be never so much, &amp; so often changed, and that for the better too, all is nothing, as to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:191924:31"/> Salvation, unless he become a <hi>New man,</hi> a <hi>New Creature;</hi> such, in the Apostles sense, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17. Many, and great <hi>Changes,</hi> some unsound ones meet with, and they live <hi>other lives</hi> than once they did, but yet still it is not a <hi>new life,</hi> which they live: it is the <hi>old life</hi> which they <hi>live still,</hi> though much altered in many things, from which alteration it is that we call it an <hi>other life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And concerning this <hi>New Life,</hi> this <hi>Spiritual Life;</hi> we may consider these few things, to make some further discovery of it, that we may know what <hi>we</hi> be, and what our <hi>faith</hi> is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It differs from the <hi>former religious Life;</hi> not in <hi>degree</hi> only but in <hi>kind:</hi> So it was with the <hi>Life</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> said he <hi>now lived;</hi> before Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, he lived a <hi>sensitive, a rational life,</hi> as other men did; and he had a <hi>Religious Life</hi> too: <hi>touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Righteousness of the Law, blameless:</hi> he was also <hi>zealous</hi> Phil. 3. 6. And so were they, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 2. But now he lived an <hi>other Life,</hi> such as he never did before: and this <hi>Life</hi> differed from the former, not only in <hi>degree,</hi> for then he had been only a <hi>greater Pharisee,</hi> and indeed a <hi>worse man</hi> than he was before: but this life differed in <hi>sort,</hi> or <hi>kind</hi> from what he had before. Now let such as hope consider this. You (it may be) have had the benefit, or advantage of a <hi>good Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and have had <hi>Convictions</hi> also, by hearing and reading of the Word, and otherwise, and thereby have been brought on to some <hi>Profession,</hi> and <hi>Practise</hi> of Religion, without being <hi>born</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:191924:31"/>
               <hi>again;</hi> this is the case with many: but know that you must have a Religion of a <hi>new kind,</hi> or else perish in your <hi>old Religion,</hi> though you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease it, or add to it never so much, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come never so fair and specious. You know, <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Beasts</hi> are both of them <hi>Animals,</hi> living Creatures, yet they differ in kind, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other agreement. So much must your <hi>Religion</hi> differ from what it once was else it will prove to be of little worth, at last, even no more than that of the <hi>Pharisees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He that hath this <hi>new Life,</hi> he lives a <hi>Holy Life, without which no man shall see the Lord.</hi> Heb. 12. 14. he is <hi>Spiritually minded,</hi> he <hi>Walks after the Spirit.</hi> Rom. 8. 1, 4, 5, 6. he minds and <hi>seeks the things above;</hi> the things of another World, <hi>where Jesus Christ is.</hi> Col. 3. 1. Phil. 3. 19. he that minds <hi>Earthly Things,</hi> his <hi>end his destruction:</hi> this is the true Word of God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 17. <hi>Thy Word <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s Truth.</hi> Let men flatter, and deceive themselves now they will; if they do not live a <hi>holy life,</hi> and <hi>walk after the Spirit,</hi> they are in their <hi>Sins</hi> still; and their <hi>saith,</hi> if they pretend to any, is but a <hi>Dead Faith.</hi> It is true, this <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> may be much clouded, and the Operations of it much impedited, and hindred, but there it is; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t is not always easy to be discovered, as it is with a <hi>Child</hi> in the Womb, if it have <hi>Life,</hi> it will <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ir,</hi> and be felt at times, though sometimes, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n some cases, it may be not of a good while: <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o it is in this case: and this <hi>Life</hi> may perhaps
<pb facs="tcp:191924:32"/> at some times be best discovered, by the opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is made against it; by that <hi>Lusting</hi> spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17. of the <hi>Flesh against the Spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit:</hi> by that <hi>Warring.</hi> Rom. 7. 23. Some persons fear they have no <hi>Life,</hi> because they have that which is indeed a <hi>good evidence</hi> of Life: if there be any thing of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in us, the <hi>Flesh</hi> will <hi>Lust</hi> against it; and so also as that we <hi>cannot do the things which we would:</hi> if there be that <hi>Law of the mind</hi> spoken of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23. there will be found <hi>another Law warring, and bringing us into Captivity, unto the Law of Sin, which is in our members:</hi> and it is true also, that a Christian must not sit down under <hi>complaints,</hi> and give way to the inward workings of Corruptions, the issue of that will be sad; yet where a <hi>Lively Faith</hi> is, that Soul is full of sad and sorrowful complaints <hi>Paul</hi> was so, and who more than he? see <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. at large: and indeed, if there be no <hi>War,</hi> there is no <hi>Life</hi> of Grace; and he that will approve himself to be a <hi>Living Christian,</hi> must be in good earnest in this <hi>Warfare,</hi> and will have a sorrowful experience daily of what it is to be brought into <hi>Captivity. Oh! wretched man that I am:</hi> be saith not, <hi>that I was,</hi> but, <hi>that I am.</hi> Let those think of this, who go on in an <hi>easy way;</hi> neither <hi>Sin,</hi> nor <hi>Satan</hi> trouble them much: <hi>Formality</hi> may pass on <hi>easily;</hi> but the <hi>Power of Godliness</hi> will meet with the sorest <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts</hi> and <hi>Oppositions;</hi> for this strikes right down blows at <hi>Sin,</hi> and meets with answerable opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:191924:32"/> who had more <hi>Grace</hi> than <hi>Paul?</hi> and who more sensible of <hi>Opposition,</hi> than he? so that <hi>when, or when ever he would do good,</hi> any good thing, <hi>evil was present with him.</hi> Rom. 7. 21. thus it was with him, thus it is with others. And for this there is a <hi>cloud of Witnesses:</hi> may the number of them be increased daily!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Where this <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> is, <hi>Christ lives in the Soul:</hi> Gal. 2. 20. <hi>Christ lives in me.—</hi>Oh! see here the priviledge, the glory, and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of a Child of God: and consider it; you it may be, have many duties, good desires and affections, and the like, in which you <hi>secret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trust:</hi> but consider, doth <hi>Christ live in you?</hi> doth he <hi>dwell,</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> in you? if not, you have no well grounded hope, Col. 1. 27. <hi>Christ in you the hope of Glory:</hi> If Christ be not <hi>in you,</hi> you have no well grounded <hi>hope of Glory.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it well; you have this in you, and that in you, and the other thing, it may be <hi>increased in Goods,</hi> as they said of themselves. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17. common Convictions have brought you on to many things; well, but is <hi>Christ in you,</hi> or not? if he be not, e're long you will be <hi>ashamed</hi> of your <hi>hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if <hi>Christ</hi> be in you, Then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You live a <hi>Life of self abasement:</hi> the more <hi>Christ</hi> lives, and rules in any one, the more mean, and low, little and <hi>not hing</hi> is such an one in his own eyes: who have had more of <hi>Christ</hi> in them than <hi>Paul</hi> had? none more; or for certain, he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:191924:33"/> had very much: yet see what he saith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 11.<hi>—I be nothing,</hi> Gal. 2. 20. <hi>I live, yet not I.</hi> Eph. 3. 8.<hi>—Who am less then the least of all Saints.</hi> When a man lives a <hi>self-righteous life,</hi> he exalts himself; all his abasements and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, are in the issue, but his exaltation, and as a stepping stone to raise himself upon; the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret language of his heart is, <hi>I, I:</hi> I am this, and I am that, and I can do, and do do these and those things: But when Christ comes in to the Soul, there is a great change, then the language is still; <hi>Not I, not I!</hi> then <hi>Christ</hi> is all in all: a person desires to acknowledge him in all: and to set the Crown upon his head; and the Soul seeks it self, in <hi>abasing</hi> it self, and in exalting of the Lord <hi>Christ:</hi> and fain would do so, more, and better; and if this be not the frame of out hearts, and the <hi>Spirit of our Religion,</hi> we indeed may call it <hi>Christian,</hi> but the Lord will not call it as we do. Wherefore consider this; did you ever find any thing of this <hi>Change,</hi> of this <hi>new way of living;</hi> do you grow still less and less, and doth <hi>Christ</hi> grow greater &amp; greater in your hearts as <hi>John</hi> said of Christ; <hi>he must increase, but<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> must decrease.</hi> Joh. 3. 30. and as verse 29. there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in he would <hi>rejoice:</hi> know you what it is, thu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>rejoice?</hi> did you ever feel any of this kind o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> joy? the Lord help you rightly to reflect upo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> your selves, and to consider thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>Christ live</hi> in you, there will be a <hi>dyin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> unto the world.</hi> Gal. 2. 20. <hi>I am crucified with Christ</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:191924:33"/> Crucifyed, unto sin, and unto the <hi>World.</hi> If Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons <hi>Love the World, and the things of it,</hi> as I Joh. 2. 15. <hi>Christ</hi> doth not live in them: in this case the word is plain, let persons look to themselves as well as they can. Also see <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14. If you be not <hi>Crucified unto the World,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> to <hi>you,</hi> you have as yet no saving acquaintance with the <hi>Cross of Christ.</hi> And yet we would have none of the Children of God discouraged: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any such object, and say, <hi>I can find but little or nothing of this dying unto the World, yea rather there seems to be much of the contrary.</hi> viz A heart much cleaving unto these things. I answer, yet it may be God is carrying on this work: you know there is <hi>pain</hi> upon the <hi>Cross,</hi> and so, it may be (1) The Lord is embittering unto you, all these things, in which you have been too much seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>rest:</hi> it may be you have seldom had any outward <hi>Comfort,</hi> but you have had your <hi>Cross</hi> with it; yea the greatest <hi>Comforts,</hi> and <hi>Sweets,</hi> have had their <hi>bitters</hi> with them. All thy <hi>Roses</hi> have had their thorns; and (2.) It may be God hath made you weary of the <hi>worldliness,</hi> and <hi>carnalness</hi> of your own hearts; and also shewen unto you <hi>a better way of living;</hi> though you cannot come at it, at you would, yet you can account it precious, if you could attain it: and you say, <hi>Oh! how happy should I be, if I could live in a Spiritual Frame, and walk after the Spirit.</hi> as Rom. 8. 1. Now ask your selves, what you would have, if you might have what you
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:191924:34"/> would; cannot you say as he did. Psal. 119. 30. <hi>I have chosen the way of truth.</hi> Perhaps you will say, I find a strong desire after the things of this <hi>World,</hi> and I doubt, I <hi>chuse</hi> these things. <hi>Answ.</hi> But are there not times when it is otherwise; and hath not God shewn unto you, <hi>a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way?</hi> perhaps it is <hi>now</hi> a dark time, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what <hi>hath</hi> been; remember the times, of which you are ready to say, <hi>then</hi> it was better with me, than <hi>Now:</hi> had you never any sensible fellowship with the Father, and with his Son Christ Jesus? yea, doth not your <hi>judgment</hi> still stand for a <hi>Spiritual way of Living,</hi> though you cannot regulate, and command your <hi>affections</hi> as you would, but are daily brought into <hi>Captivity unto the Law of Sin,</hi> as he complains. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>Christ</hi> live in you, he will sometimes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest himself unto you. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 21. he will not be wholly a <hi>Stranger</hi> unto you, he will sometimes let you see something of his <hi>face,</hi> and <hi>some times</hi> more than at <hi>other times.</hi> Sometimes you shall sit down under his <hi>shadow,</hi> if not with <hi>great,</hi> yet with <hi>some delight</hi> at least. as <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 3 and his <hi>Fruit shall be sweet unto your tast.</hi> Yea, he will bring you into his <hi>Banqueting House,</hi> though your Entertainment there may not be so full, and large, as some have experience of. And to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, consider these things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes he manifests himself to his by a <hi>sudden</hi> and <hi>sensible</hi> breaking in of <hi>light</hi> upon the Soul, 2 Cor. 4. 6. As in the <hi>first Creation,</hi> so in this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:191924:34"/> second. <hi>God who Commanded the light to shine out of darkness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the Glory of God, in the face of Jesus Christ.</hi> This is sometimes <hi>sudden,</hi> it is <hi>e're a person is aware.</hi> As Cant. 6. 12. The <hi>Word</hi> of God is <hi>Light.</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 19. And one principal use of it, unto us, is to <hi>give us light:</hi> Even Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual light, and Spiritual discerning of Spiritual things. <hi>Psal.</hi> 19. 8. &amp; 119. 130. <hi>It doth enlighten the eyes, and giveth light:</hi> and if it have not this effect in us; we have no real benefit by it: if thus it be <hi>hid to us, we are lost.</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 3, 4. But that which I shew is, that the Lord can, &amp; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times doth make the light of his word, <hi>suddenly</hi> and <hi>gloriously</hi> shine in upon the hearts of them that are his. Oh! how precious is a word, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made to be unto a Child of God, which he hears or reads, or is made to come, into his mind! And he thinks he shall never forget such a word, and such a time. And many times, these breakings in of light are at such times, when they are least of all expected. And he that hath any tast of this, will desire more of this <hi>light,</hi> and enlightning. Thus he Psal. 119. 18. <hi>Open thou mine eyes that I may behold wondrous things out of thy Law.</hi> And all these <hi>Openings</hi> and <hi>Enlightnings,</hi> come from above; they can in no wise be <hi>gotten,</hi> unless they be <hi>given.</hi> Jam. 1. 17. And doth any poor Soul that hath had them, fear they are of his <hi>own making?</hi> let him then, if he can <hi>make more.</hi> The Lord gives them, how, &amp; when, &amp; to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:191924:35"/> whom, and in what degree, he pleaseth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes by a more <hi>gradual discovery</hi> of the <hi>way of the Gospel,</hi> whereby the Soul comes to see more clearly into it. This is sometimes, as the <hi>dawning</hi> of the day, by <hi>degrees,</hi> and hence less sensible unto them that have it; but yet hereby Christ is more known; and the Soul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaseth in <hi>Spiritual knowlege,</hi> or understanding, as it is called. Col. 1. 9. There is a <hi>notional know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of Spiritual things; and a <hi>Spiritual under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing;</hi> this is only found with true Believers. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14, 15. And some thing of it, with all such: and where it is, it shall be <hi>increased:</hi> and this should be much endeavoured by all such. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> And this is that which the Apostle so much desireth for them, in <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 17. By the improvement of Sanctified reason, called by the Apostle, <hi>the Spirit of Wisdom</hi> (for so I understand it) Christians grow into a further measure of the knowledge of God, and of his Son Christ Jesus, <hi>whom to know, is life eternal.</hi> Joh. 17. 3. And so are by degrees further <hi>rooted and built up in him,</hi> and more established in the faith. Compare <hi>Col.</hi> 2. &amp; <hi>Verses</hi> 2, 7.</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>USE. <hi>I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Try</hi> your selves whether your <hi>faith</hi> be a <hi>Dead faith,</hi> or no: I suppose you to have <hi>faith,</hi> to be believers, and to have hopes that your condition, God ward, is Good; and it may be you say
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:191924:35"/> you will trust in Christ, and whatever come of it, you will do so; and for all the World, I would not willingly stagger the hopes, and make sad the heart of the meanest of those that are indeed <hi>true Believers</hi> in Christ Jesus. Nevertheless (these times abounding with such as be but <hi>formal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors)</hi> let us search and <hi>try</hi> the matter, and not lightly pass it over. And Consider,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trial.</hi> 1. It may be your trust in him ariseth from <hi>one,</hi> or <hi>all</hi> of these things: and so it is with many, and if so, with you? your faith is a <hi>Dead faith;</hi> and what ever else you be, you are <hi>yet in your sins.</hi> (1) Perhaps it ariseth from <hi>ignorance</hi> of your selves, and of sin, and of God &amp;c. It will one day appear, that the very bottom and found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation or some mens <hi>faith,</hi> the <hi>Corner stone</hi> of it is laid in, and springs from <hi>ignorance</hi> of themselves, and of sin; and from secret, unseen, but a real <hi>Contempt</hi> of God, whom they seem to fear, and pretend to trust in: they <hi>trust</hi> in him, so did they, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. 11. Not because they <hi>knew</hi> him, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because they <hi>knew him not.</hi> Oh! consider it, you say you trust in Christ, but it may be you never saw <hi>your selves</hi> yet, nor the <hi>Plague of your own hearts.</hi> The Commandment never came, &amp; <hi>sin never revived,</hi> as he speaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9. It may be you never saw the <hi>evil of sin.</hi> You neither <hi>know</hi> God, nor have seen your <hi>ignorance</hi> of God. Now while a man is thus without a thorow Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, it may be a thing of no great difficulty
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:191924:36"/> for him, to <hi>trust</hi> in Christ; as he thinks: but when he comes to see <hi>himself,</hi> and the <hi>Law,</hi> his <hi>faith</hi> and trust will vanish; and he must begin again upon a new bottom: and now it appears that his former trust and faith, was nothing, but <hi>Presumption,</hi> rashness, folly, delusion: all which had its foundation laid, in a destructive, ruining <hi>ignorance</hi> of himself, and of that, holy, holy dreadful Majesty with whom we have to do, &amp; who will <hi>by no means clear the guilty.</hi> (2) Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it ariseth only from an <hi>Historical, notional knowledge,</hi> of the way of the Gospel. It may be you have read, and heard much of this way, and seemed to fall in with it, and there you rest, but know nothing of the <hi>power</hi> of it, of the <hi>difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> that be in it. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 20. <hi>The kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.</hi> 1 Thes. 1. 5. <hi>Our Gospel came, not in word only, but in power.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> must come in power to <hi>kill</hi> us, that we may <hi>Live</hi> unto God, Gal. 2. 19. And so must the <hi>Gospel</hi> come in <hi>power</hi> too, or else we shall have no saving benefit by it. <hi>In power.</hi> (1) To <hi>overcome the heart,</hi> that we may submit to it: for the heart is ever full of opposition to the way of the Gospel; and that upon diverse accounts. 2 Cor. 10. 4, 5. <hi>Pulling down strong holds, casting down imaginations, or reasonings, and every high thing that exalts it self,</hi> &amp;c. (2) To <hi>affect the heart</hi> much; it is an affecting thing, when the Gospel comes in power, An excellent, and wonderful thing is in the way of the Gospel: in it self it is so,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:191924:36"/> and to all that have a right understanding of it. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8. Also it is powerful in <hi>melting</hi> the heart for, and <hi>turning</hi> of it from <hi>sin.</hi> Tit. 2. 11, 12. (2) Perhaps your <hi>faith</hi> is a cover of, and a pillow for <hi>Spiritual sloth;</hi> and then it is surely a <hi>Dead faith.</hi> Sometimes persons being unsound, they are lazy and slothful; they will not <hi>watch,</hi> and <hi>war,</hi> and <hi>work,</hi> as they ought; they secretly mentain a <hi>Truce</hi> with their lusts, they will not be at <hi>pains</hi> to purge themselves, and to mortify their lusts; which yet they must do, or <hi>dy</hi> in them, and for them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. Well, what rest can they have in that way, and how can they be quiet? Answ. They <hi>trust in Christ,</hi> as they say, and will venture themselves there, and this quiets them. <hi>Oh! Adulterous Generation!</hi> Do you make Christ a Pillow for <hi>sloth,</hi> a Patron of <hi>sin?</hi> It is no better: will ye fight against him with his own Weapons? Cry, <hi>Hail Master,</hi> and betray him? he knows how to discover, and to deal with such well enough; and will do it in due time; he will discover the guile and treachery of their own hearts to themselves, and to all the world. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that place, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 3. <hi>He that hath this hope</hi> (which springs from a lively <hi>faith) purifies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</hi> But he that sits down in <hi>sloth,</hi> and loves his sin, hath a <hi>Dead faith.</hi> I say not, he that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains</hi> of <hi>Spiritual slothfulness</hi> in himself: for what almost do many Godly ones complain of more? and they account that it is never better with them, then when they can get some power against it.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:191924:37"/> How often doth the Psalmist beg, and pray, <hi>Quicken me:</hi> And see <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 32. <hi>When thou shalt enlarge my heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trial</hi> 2. If your Faith be not a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> it will have <hi>fruits:</hi> even such as we read of. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Fruits unto holiness:</hi> I shall instance in three things. (1.) <hi>Repentance.</hi> (2.) <hi>Mortification.</hi> (3) <hi>Vivification.</hi> Now these are great points, and to open fully any one of them, requires a treatise by it self. I mention them only by way of trial, to discover whether our Faith be a <hi>Dead Faith</hi> or not. And therefore must pass over them briefly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fruit</hi> 1. One fruit is <hi>Repentance;</hi> and this makes way for, and unto <hi>holiness</hi> of heart and lite. Acts 11. 18. it is therefore called <hi>Repentance unto Life. Repentance</hi> (if it be true) and <hi>Faith</hi> go together. Mark 1. 15. <hi>Repent ye, and beeieve,</hi> &amp;c. there is a <hi>Repentance</hi> preparatory, and ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaneous unto <hi>Faith:</hi> and there is a <hi>Repentance</hi> that is a consequent, and a fruit of it. Now 'tis this <hi>Repentance</hi> of which I am to speak; and I shall consider these few things only, in speaking to which yet I may take in, some of those things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which are <hi>preparatory</hi> to, tho' chiefly I shall speak of those things which follow <hi>Faith:</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of the whole is, to discover to us what our <hi>Faith</hi> is, whether a <hi>Dead Faith</hi> or not. (1.) A sight of sin. (2.) A sorrow for sin. And (3) A shame, or self-abasement for it. (4.) The main, or principal spring and rise of that sorrow or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:191924:37"/> shame, <hi>viz.</hi> some Gospel consideration, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing seen of Christ, and of the Gospel.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There must be a <hi>sight of sin:</hi> until a man <hi>sees sin,</hi> he will never, he can never <hi>repent</hi> of it: and he must <hi>see</hi> it aright, e're he can <hi>repent</hi> of it aright: and to that end there must be an <hi>enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and an <hi>opening</hi> of the eyes: a <hi>turning from darkness unto light,</hi> which is a main work, and fruit of the Ministry of the Word. Acts 26. 18. Mans natural state, is a state of <hi>darkness, blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, ignorance,</hi> though he know it not, yet so it is: now when God will do good to any, <hi>He calleth them out of darkness into his marvellous light:</hi> but that which I shew is, that when God will do good to any, by giving them <hi>Repentance</hi> unto life, he gives them a <hi>sight of sin:</hi> till they <hi>see it,</hi> they will not <hi>repent</hi> of it; and when they do <hi>see it,</hi> they will <hi>repent</hi> of it, and turn from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But don't all men own themselves to be <hi>Sinners,</hi> and most men own themselves to be great <hi>Sinners</hi> too; what is this <hi>sight of sin,</hi> of which you speak?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> There are (among the rest) these three things in it, which I shall observe from that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> where <hi>Paul</hi> sheweth how it was with him, when God came to do him good. (1.) Such a <hi>sight</hi> as came from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>Commandment,</hi> verse 9. <hi>the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment came.</hi> How? Why, it came with light, and was set on with power upon his heart: there is no thorow knowledge of our selves, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:191924:38"/> of sin, without this. verse 7. <hi>I had not known sin, but by the Law: i. e.</hi> by its coming thus: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise he knew the <hi>Law</hi> before, and <hi>Sin</hi> too; and thought he knew all that he had need to know: this is therefore to be considered; you say, you <hi>know,</hi> and <hi>see</hi> sin, but I ask, how did you come to see it? did the <hi>Commandment</hi> ever come with light, and power? hath the <hi>Word</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been a powerful, enlightning word unto your Souls? Psal. 19. 8. yea, hath there been such a <hi>sight,</hi> as could never have been obtained, by all reading, hearing studying, and use of means, without this <hi>work</hi> of which we speak? (2) Such a <hi>sight</hi> as comes from the <hi>reviving of sin: sin revived</hi> saith <hi>Paul:</hi> the <hi>Commandment</hi> came, and <hi>sin revived:</hi> what is that? <hi>Answ.</hi> See verse 8. <hi>Without the Law, sin was dead:</hi> the <hi>Sin</hi> before that seemed to be <hi>dead,</hi> was now <hi>irritated,</hi> now it revives, it appears to be alive, and shews it self. You may understand it thus; I will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it in three things only, and briefly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There be all <hi>sorts of sin,</hi> there is every lust in the heart of every man: there is a mighty <hi>Host,</hi> and Army of Sins, and Lusts in the heart; and hence the heart is said to be <hi>full of evil.</hi> Eccles. 9. 3. and hence when he had a sight of himself in such renewed convictions as God saw meet to give him, he saw his Sins to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numberable, <hi>even more than the hairs of his head:</hi> Psal. 40. 12. and so <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7 8. saw in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self all <hi>manner of concupiscence;</hi> and it is frequent
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:191924:38"/> with persons under convictions, to say that they find in themselves all manner of sin: but that which I say is, what-ever they see, every sin is there <hi>really,</hi> and they shall know it too, e're the Lord have done with them, if he mean to make thorow work with them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All these particular <hi>Lusts</hi> that be in the heart, do not always actually <hi>stir</hi> or <hi>work;</hi> they are like to Enemies that Ly Entrenched, all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, upon the <hi>Watch word,</hi> or <hi>Alarm</hi> given, to shew themselves, and to make a fierce assault, as occasion may be; whereas many of them Ly still, and stir not at all, or but little, <hi>of a long time</hi> together: much so it is here, in this case. <hi>All</hi> men are by nature, what any <hi>one</hi> is; Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, Drunkards, Murderers, and the like; all these, and all other sins are in them, they Ly Encamped, and Entrenched in the heart, all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy when a <hi>Temptation</hi> shall come, and <hi>restraints</hi> be removed, which are many, and various, and of which, I cannot now speak in particular; they will surely shew themselves, as much as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sins, which do stir, and work in the heart or life. <hi>Hazael</hi> will shew himself to be a <hi>Dog,</hi> though at present he himself cannot think it. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the <hi>Commandment comes,</hi> there is as it were a great <hi>Alarm</hi> given to <hi>Corruption,</hi> and hence there is a great <hi>stir</hi> in the Soul, as it were a rally, and up rising of Corruptions; and hence <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that <hi>when the Commandment came, it</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:191924:39"/>
                  <hi>wrought in him: i. e.</hi> it did irritate, and stir up in him, <hi>all manner of Concupiscence,</hi> or <hi>Corruption.</hi> Sin was now, (if I may so express it) all up in Arms; when the <hi>Commandment</hi> came, it fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sin in good earnest to destroy it, and to root it out; and hence <hi>sin,</hi> did (as it were) stand up for its <hi>Life:</hi> it shewed it self, its strength, its rage unto the utmost; before this the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> did nothing to the purpose, it made no vigorous on set upon the Soul; the most it did, was to bring the Soul to some <hi>Outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> to the Law, which <hi>Sin within</hi> might the more easily dispence with, because it might still live, and reign in the Soul, notwithstanding that: but when indeed the <hi>Commandment comes,</hi> the case is otherwise; sin perceives it self to be in real danger, its very life and being is sorely struck at; and hence it will stir, work and shew it self, even all that it can. Alas, what do many persons think of <hi>Sin!</hi> will it dy easily, and quietly leave its station, will it do nothing? and speak never a word for its life? are our Lusts such tame and seeble things? Oh! no <hi>Paul</hi> found it otherwise; and so shall any one that shall indeed put the matter upon tryal: yea after Conversion, tho' sin, and formality may tollerably agree together; yet where-ever th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Power of Godliness,</hi> is in any good measure, there ensueth a sore <hi>war</hi> with Sin; and the more there is of the <hi>Power of Godliness,</hi> the more sore an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> close will the <hi>Combate</hi> and <hi>Conflict</hi> be: who com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plains
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:191924:39"/> more, than that great Christian. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23, 24. and in the foregoing verses? and why doth he thus complain? was it because he was weaker, and had less Grace? No, it was just the contrary. In a word, let us be sincere, and in good earnest with our <hi>Lusts,</hi> to destroy them, and we shall then have a very humbling, aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing experience of their strength and power in us: while in the mean while <hi>Formality</hi> may pass along in the world, and thorow all our religious performances much more quietly.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It must be a <hi>killing sight of sin.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9, 10, 11, 13. <hi>Sin revived, and I dyed—I found to be unto death—and by it slew me-working death in me.</hi> Here is a heap of expressions, all of them shewing the same thing in general; we must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider therefore the more deeply what may be the meaning of them. This then I say, this sight must be a <hi>killing sight,</hi> such as will <hi>slay a man: It slew me.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> saw himself full of all manner of <hi>Concupiscence;</hi> and when he saw sin appearing in its own colours; it had no viz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard on, it did but look like it self; it did appear <hi>sin,</hi> verse 13. he immediately falleth down <hi>dead</hi> at the sight of it; <hi>it wrought death in him, it slew him.</hi> And note here, it is a great thing to <hi>dy,</hi> and it is more terrible still to be <hi>slain.</hi> Now to open this a little, this <hi>dying, killing, slaying,</hi> hath these things in it, besides what else might be named.</p>
               <p n="1">1. it takes away from a person the <hi>life</hi> which once he thought he had, and in which he trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:191924:40"/> every man naturally thinks himself to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,</hi> though indeed he be <hi>dead in sins.</hi> Rom. 7. 9. <hi>I was alive once; i. e.</hi> in his own conceit: so are many: and they trust in this life, they lean, and live upon it, it is their confidence, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, they account it <hi>gain,</hi> as he speaks, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7. and this many do, whatever they think, pretend, or profess to the contrary: now this <hi>Life</hi> is taken away, when a person comes to see himself, and his sin aright. Consider then these things, know you what this meaneth to have this <hi>life taken away?</hi> else you be <hi>alive</hi> still, as <hi>Paul</hi> before Conversion was: that is, in conce it <hi>alive,</hi> but <hi>dead indeed;</hi> and on some accounts in a worse condition, then many of those, who are yet far from Christ: you must <hi>dy,</hi> you must be <hi>slain,</hi> that so you may be quickened, and may <hi>Live</hi> unto God. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 19. mark what he saith,<hi>—I am dead▪that I might live.▪</hi>q d. It was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that I should <hi>dy,</hi> that I might <hi>live:</hi> a man without this may indeed <hi>live</hi> unto himself, but not unto God, how religious, soever he may be, or seem to be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It leaves a man without the least ability, or hope to <hi>help himself:</hi> he saith, he findeth, and feeleth that he hath no ability to help himself, no more than a dead man hath: and he hath no <hi>hope</hi> in that matter; we say, as long as there is <hi>life,</hi> there is <hi>hope;</hi> but when a man is once <hi>dead,</hi> there is no <hi>hope:</hi> so it is here, while a man is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live</hi> in himself, he hath many self-righteous hopes;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:191924:40"/> but when the <hi>Commandment comes,</hi> and <hi>sin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives,</hi> and <hi>he dyes,</hi> all these <hi>hopes</hi> are gone; and truly persons do not easily come to say there is no hope. Isa. 57. 10. Men indeed do easily own themselves, many times, to be wholly <hi>helpless</hi> in themselves, but when they come indeed to <hi>feel,</hi> and find it so, it is grievous, it is a <hi>killing</hi> thing to them, and cannot be otherwise; but I shall not enlarge in this point, yet a word of it; wherefore I say,</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a <hi>terrible</hi> thing unto the Soul to come unto this, as we have formerly, and but now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so hinted; and that for these reasons. (1.) The Soul is now under the deepest sense of <hi>Soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns,</hi> &amp; highly engaged to seek for <hi>help;</hi> he cannot make a <hi>light thing</hi> of perishing, as many do, and as perhaps himself once long did; no, it is now unto him, as indeed it is in it self: <hi>a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> Heb. 10. 31. he cannot bear the thoughts of <hi>perishing for ever:</hi> he lies under a deep sense of a necessity of having <hi>help;</hi> he hath no <hi>rest because of sin, and his iniquities are an heavy burden, too heavy for him.</hi> Psal. 38. 3, 4. the <hi>Spirit is wounded,</hi> and he <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear it;</hi> a sense of <hi>wrath</hi> lyes on him, so that now he can no more rest, and sleep as in dayes past. (2.) All that he hath <hi>built,</hi> and <hi>leaned</hi> upon, now faileth him: he would have done what they endeavoured. <hi>Rom</hi> 10 3. <hi>viz.</hi> have <hi>established his own righteousness.</hi> There is not one man among all <hi>Adams</hi> Posterity, that is not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:191924:41"/> very strongly inclined this way; but he sees now that he cannot do it; he cannot make his own way stand; he labours in vain; and instead of growing better, he complains that all is worse and worse, and therefore now knows not what to do, nor what course to take, nor which way to turn himself. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 37. and then (3) He sees <hi>no other way of help</hi> as yet: the right way he knows not. <hi>Isa.</hi> 59. 8. and as yet there is <hi>no judgment in his goings:</hi> all his own wayes fail him; and hence he must needs be distressed; and a thorow sight of sin doth not come off lightly with any; though some have more grievous, and sorer travel than others have Oh! consider these things, it may be, you have not taken the first step towards <hi>Repentance,</hi> you have not had a thorow <hi>sight of sin:</hi> if so, the rest is wanting, and your <hi>Faith,</hi> but a <hi>Dead Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Another thing in this <hi>Repentance,</hi> which is a fruit of a lively <hi>Faith,</hi> is <hi>Sorrow for Sin;</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture abundantly makes mention of this; and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten sets it forth in very high Expressions. See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7 16. Where true <hi>Repentance</hi> is, there is a <hi>Mourning</hi> for sin.<hi>—All of them mourning, every one for his iniquity:</hi> and Zech 12. 10. <hi>They shall mourn, as one mourneth for his only son, and shall be in bitter ness.</hi> 2. Cor. 7. 9. <hi>Yee sorrowed unto Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Another thing in this Repentance is <hi>Shame,</hi> and <hi>Abasement</hi> of Soul for <hi>Sin.</hi> See Rom. 6. 21.<hi>—Those things whereof yee are now ashamed.</hi> When God gives <hi>Repentance</hi> to a Person, he is <hi>ashamed</hi> of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:191924:41"/> his former wayes and courses; whether he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a way of <hi>grosser sinning,</hi> or in a way of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risaism,</hi> and self righteousness, as <hi>Paul</hi> once did, trusting in a <hi>blameless Life,</hi> as he calls it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 6. When his eyes are opened, he will be <hi>ashamed</hi> of himself, his sin &amp; folly, shewing it self, in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wayes and courses. And of this sorrow and shame I shall say these things briefly; a little to open, and enlighten the things we are upon, as we go along. (1.) This <hi>sorrow</hi> and <hi>abasement</hi> arises from an <hi>enlightning</hi> to shew a man more of sin, than once he saw in himself; and to shew him the <hi>evil</hi> that is in sin. First there must be an <hi>enlightning,</hi> Act. 26. 18. <hi>To open their eyes, and to turn them from darkness to light.</hi> There must then be an <hi>enlightning,</hi> as also we have already hinted: and they have nothing of this <hi>enlightning,</hi> that know nothing of their own <hi>blindness</hi> and <hi>darkness,</hi> who never saw, felt and mourned under <hi>that:</hi> And this <hi>enlightning</hi> is to shew a man more of <hi>himself,</hi> that once he did see: for this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, persons though they live under the light of the Gospel, yet they don't know how bad and vile they be, until God open their eyes, and cause them to know their <hi>abominations;</hi> which is usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the work of the Ministry, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 2. The <hi>Spirit</hi> working with the word; otherwise all is nothing: or the most that a person will attain, is an <hi>Historical knowledge</hi> of himself, and of his own vileness; and his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> will be answerable. Also the <hi>evil of sin</hi> (as we said)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:191924:42"/> must be seen: sin must be seen in another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and look with another face, than once it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id: it must appear <hi>sin,</hi> which it doth but to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w, and become <hi>exceeding sinful.</hi> Rom. 7. 13. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen a man will be ashamed and mourn, and not else. (2.) This sorrow and mourning hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a great mixture of <hi>hardness</hi> and <hi>pride of heart</hi> with it: for in nothing are we <hi>perfect</hi> in this life; and what is there almost that a humbled Soul complains of more, and desires to get rid of more, than of an <hi>hard,</hi> and a <hi>proud</hi> heart; and so much of this is sometimes seen, and felt, that a person fears there is <hi>nothing else.</hi> See <hi>Isa.</hi> 63. 17. This is certainly one part of a Christians work, and his <hi>Warfare</hi> is within his own heart, with the pride, hardness, unbrokenness, and other distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers thereof. Some Professors indeed find no hard work with their own hearts, they think they have <hi>all things,</hi> and have <hi>need of nothing;</hi> but these are indeed <hi>miserable, wretched, blind and naked,</hi> Rev. 3. 17. They indeed <hi>Pray</hi> for many things, but not from a sight and sense of their <hi>wants:</hi> they are only <hi>empty words,</hi> which they speak and the lord abhors their best Prayers. (3.) This sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and abasement is a <hi>growing thing:</hi> if other Graces grow, this doth; and as this groweth so do all other: if a person don't grow in <hi>Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> he groweth not at all, so <hi>as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to increase with the increase of God.</hi> Now this growth in some, indeed is very little; as some men, so some Christians are very low in stature:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:191924:42"/> and there are <hi>Winter seasons</hi> in many Christians lives, in which they grow but little, or not at all: yet in their general course they do grow. Joh. 15. 2. <hi>He purgeth them that they may bring forth more fruit.</hi> Now consider this; some say, they have <hi>Repented</hi> of sin; and hence sit down, as if all the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were over, and they had no more to do: but if their work be right, it must continue, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and <hi>grow.</hi> If your <hi>Repentance</hi> be all <hi>over,</hi> and <hi>done,</hi> it was never yet well <hi>begun:</hi> Alas you have deceived your selves: think of it, while time lasteth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The main <hi>spring</hi> of this sorrow and abase<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is some <hi>Gospel Consideration:</hi> something of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Grace</hi> of God in him. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12. What is that which effectually teacheth a person to <hi>deny</hi> his sin, and to <hi>repent</hi> of it? Truly nothing so much as this: <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Grace of God appearing.</hi> There be other things, but this is the main. See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. two last verses. Consider then what influences, and motives you are under? is it things <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>Evangelical?</hi> is it <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Gospel</hi> that chiefly moves you? you will say, how shall I know that? <hi>Answ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Hath the light of the glorious <hi>Gospel.</hi> ever been made to shine in unto your hearts? To some it is <hi>hid.</hi> See 2 Cor. 4. 3, 4, 6. But <hi>God shines into the hearts of some to give light.</hi> Hath he ever shined into thy heart? Hath the light of the Gospel been unto thee, the most glorious light?</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Do <hi>Gospel Considerations</hi> influence, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:191924:43"/> work on your hearts? it may be you can some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>fear:</hi> but doth the <hi>Love</hi> of Christ ever <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain</hi> you. 2 Cor. 5. 14, 15. If you do live at all a <hi>Spiritual Life,</hi> you <hi>Live to him that dyed for you,</hi> and <hi>his Love constrains you:</hi> and indeed whatever we do in Religion, if it be not a fruit of <hi>Faith,</hi> and of <hi>Love;</hi> (for <hi>faith works by Love,</hi> Gal. 5. 6.) all is nothing; and whatever, and how much soever it be, the Lord accepts it not with any good will.</p>
               <p>Now here is a <hi>Knot</hi> that should be untied, as we go along lest we leave matters too dark. <hi>viz.</hi> Some think they have <hi>Love to Christ,</hi> when indeed they have <hi>none:</hi> and some fear they have <hi>none,</hi> when indeed they have <hi>much,</hi> at least <hi>some.</hi> A word of each.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some think they have much <hi>Love to Christ,</hi> but they have <hi>none</hi> in truth: or no <hi>true Love.</hi> for as we read of <hi>true holiness:</hi> or <hi>holiness of truth.</hi> Eph. 4. 24. So there is a <hi>true Love;</hi> and a <hi>Love</hi> that is not of <hi>truth;</hi> and the <hi>Love</hi> which many have to Christ is no better than that which they had of old, who one while Cryed, <hi>Hosanna to the Son of David;</hi> and alterward, <hi>Crucify him, Crucify him, away with him:</hi> or that of the young man that came <hi>running</hi> to Christ, with much zeal, and by and by, he turns his back on him; <hi>he went away sorrowful.</hi> So it is with many, they seem to have much <hi>Love</hi> for a season, but in time it <hi>withers,</hi> as Joh. 5. 35. The reason is, they never <hi>know Christ,</hi> nor themselves neither, not thorowly: and hence it is with them, as with the <hi>stony ground.</hi> Matth.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:191924:43"/> 13. 5, 20, 21. There wanted <hi>deepness of earth:</hi> thorowness of Conviction; and hence though the word were received with joy, yet all dureth but for a while; <hi>he hath no root in himself:</hi> no inward <hi>principle</hi> of Spiritual life &amp; love; only the <hi>natural affections</hi> are raised, by the power of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, and turned (in some sort) another way than formerly; but there being no Sanctifying change, in time, all turns again to the old Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel: or else a person contents himself with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon love, and affections, instead of that which is Spiritual, and flows from a <hi>Sanctifying change</hi> in the Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are some that have <hi>much Love,</hi> or at least <hi>true Love</hi> to Christ, that fear that they have <hi>none</hi> at all. <hi>Obj.</hi> How can this be? if a man have <hi>true Love,</hi> he may know it, one would think. <hi>Answ.</hi> No, not alwayes: we can neither discern <hi>Christs Love</hi> to us, nor <hi>our Love</hi> to him, unless the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, discover the same unto us. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 12. We are said to receive the Spirit, <hi>that we may know the things that are freely given to us of God.</hi> So also those things that are <hi>freely wrought in us,</hi> will be all clouded &amp; in darkness, unless the <hi>Spirit</hi> do enlighten our minds, and discover them unto us. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 16. <hi>The Spirit it self bears witness with our Spirit.</hi> Our <hi>Spirit</hi> will, it can witness nothing to us, for our comfort, unless the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> joyn &amp; witness together therewith: if this <hi>Spirit</hi> as to this work of it, be withdrawn (as many times it is) we are all in <hi>darkness,</hi> and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:191924:44"/> have no light, though we <hi>fear God and obey him;</hi> there is no light sufficient to discover that to us, which indeed is in us. A persons love to Christ is always seen, and discerned by <hi>Christ,</hi> but not always by <hi>himself,</hi> yet we should seek to find it out in our selves: and therefore as we pass along in our work, consider only these two things in this place.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Have you <hi>seen Christ?</hi> if you have, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but <hi>Love,</hi> and believe in him: and so <hi>e' contra. Seen</hi> him? how is that? <hi>Answ.</hi> Not with <hi>bodily eyes:</hi> for when he was on earth, many saw him so, and perished for ever: and to see him now with out <hi>bodily eyes,</hi> would be like to <hi>confound</hi> us, rather than <hi>profit</hi> us; however it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by us. Not by <hi>hear-say,</hi> and <hi>report</hi> only: for so all see him under the Gospel: but have you seen him, by a <hi>work of the Spirit revealing Christ in you?</hi> Gal. 1. 15, 16. <hi>When it pleased God to reveal his Son in me, or to me.</hi> Christ is never seen, or known by any, how much soever they hear of him, till God reveal him. Now, if you have seen him, there is at least a latent, rooted <hi>Love</hi> to, and belief in him, which shall never utterly fail, but in due time appear, and at last be found unto Salvation. And if you have seen him, you have seen your <hi>Spiritual ignorance</hi> of him; and that ignorance that yet remains, is among your <hi>chief complaints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If you <hi>Love</hi> him, you will <hi>Love</hi> those that are <hi>his</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14. And on this account, for that of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:191924:44"/>
                  <hi>him,</hi> that is in <hi>them:</hi> and he that doth not <hi>Love the people of God,</hi> doth <hi>not Love God himself</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 20. <hi>If we Love him,l we shall Love them that are his,</hi> because they are his: and they are one, as God and Christ are one. <hi>John</hi> 17. 11, 21. 22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The second fruit to be considered of (by way of tryal) is <hi>Mortification</hi> of sin, or the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of the Soul from it, which is a <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>faith.</hi> Acts 15. 9. <hi>Purifying their hearts by faith.</hi> The <hi>heart</hi> is never <hi>purified;</hi> and <hi>sin</hi> is never <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,</hi> until <hi>faith</hi> come: and that always doth something this way, unless it be a <hi>Dead faith.</hi> Sin may be as it were stunned, and knockt on the head, by <hi>Convictions,</hi> and legal terrors, but is never <hi>mortified,</hi> until <hi>faith</hi> come, and then some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is done indeed.</p>
               <p>Now, having mentioned this, as one thing to try our selves by, we must clear and open the point, and endeavour to free it, ere we leave it, from whatsoever might cloud and darken it: And the difficulty is to shew the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the effects of <hi>Legal terrors,</hi> and <hi>Common Convictions</hi> in <hi>restraining sin,</hi> and that of <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>mortifying sin:</hi> and the difference between that effect which that <hi>faith</hi> which is yet indeed but a <hi>Dead faith</hi> may have upon <hi>sin,</hi> and that which a <hi>Lively faith</hi> hath in <hi>mortifying</hi> of sin.</p>
               <p>And first we shall consider the difference that is between <hi>Legal Terrors restraining</hi> Sin; and that of <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>mortifying</hi> it. And here I premise
<pb facs="tcp:191924:45"/> this one thing: <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>particular Lusts,</hi> by <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Terrors,</hi> and common convictions, are many times, as it were <hi>benummed,</hi> in a <hi>swound,</hi> when not at all <hi>mortifyed;</hi> and here many deceive themselves; they find no present disposition, or inclination to their former lusts, but some <hi>aversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from them, and hence they think they are throughly reformed, and <hi>mortified,</hi> when as there is no such thing; they have only changed their <hi>way of sinning;</hi> as he that was a gross Sinner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, is now a <hi>formal Professor,</hi> a <hi>self-righteous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</hi> Sin in him now runs out in <hi>another channel;</hi> he is as much a Sinner as ever, tho' in another way, and he sees it not.</p>
               <p>Now when sin is only <hi>stunned</hi> and <hi>benummed</hi> with <hi>Legal Terrors,</hi> and forced as it were to pull in its head, and to shrink back into the deep, &amp; dark corners of the heart, and so to find another vent, a more secret, and undiscovered passage. Then,</p>
               <p n="1">1. A mans life in <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>mercenary;</hi> all his Obedience is <hi>Legal,</hi> and <hi>Servile;</hi> not <hi>filial:</hi> such a persons Obedience is but an endeavouring to pay the <hi>debt</hi> of Satisfaction for Sin which he ows to God, and to pacify his <hi>anger,</hi> which he hopes to do, by a better walking then formerly; and though such persons do not profess so, yet really it is so, with them. And hence one of these things following, may be said of them: either (1) They deceive themselves in thinking all is <hi>well</hi> with them, when it is not. (2) They
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:191924:45"/> find that they cannot make their <hi>peace</hi> with God, and so return again to folly; or else (3) Spend their time in a <hi>wearyish formality,</hi> and so perish for ever at last.—(1) Some think they have paid their debt, by their <hi>repentings,</hi> and <hi>reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and other <hi>good works;</hi> and hence their minds are at rest, in some measure; but there comes an <hi>after reckoning</hi> at death, when it appears that their coin is not current: &amp; what they trust to will not be accepted; the Lord abhors all that they have offered to him for <hi>payment;</hi> and hence they are <hi>cast into Hell,</hi> where they are for ever <hi>tormented;</hi> for they can never pay the debt. (2) Some find that by all they do, they cannot make their <hi>peace</hi> with God; they are still running into arrearages: still God is <hi>provoked</hi> by them dayly; and hence complain that their <hi>labour is in vain,</hi> that they serve an <hi>hard master.</hi> Mat 25. 24. that gathers where he had not sowen; that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires obedience, but gives not strength answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; and hence grow discouraged, and like the <hi>Israelites</hi> of old, finding the difficulties of the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> would return into <hi>Egypt</hi> again: so these forsake the Lord, and his Service, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their <hi>old wayes</hi> again, or some other as bad: as the <hi>dog to his vomit.</hi> 2 Pet. 2. ult. (3) Some wear out their time in a heartless, uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and unprofitable attendance to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Religion;</hi> they do <hi>hope,</hi> and <hi>fear</hi> much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as be the wainings or increase of their own righteousness, or <hi>legal performances:</hi> for the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:191924:46"/>
                  <hi>way of peace they have not known;</hi> and there is no <hi>judgment in their goings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now the true believer, his obedience is <hi>filial:</hi> he goes to <hi>work,</hi> but not to <hi>pay his debt:</hi> for he hath seen that done already by <hi>another,</hi> or knows that if ever it be done, it must be by <hi>another;</hi> and hence the main spring of his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebce, is <hi>Love</hi> to God, and his great Redeemer; <hi>his faith works by love.</hi> Gal. 5. 6. it will work, or set a man on work; but how? by <hi>love.</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 14. <hi>The love of Christ constrains us,</hi> saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle. This <hi>Faith</hi> then doth not set a man on work, to pay old debts, or new, which no man can do any thing of, either more or less: though many attempt it daily, who yet perhaps under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand not what they do, and so undo themselves, but see not how, until it be too late.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then a mans <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> is not like that of a true believers: What is the <hi>legal</hi> mans <hi>hope? Answ.</hi> That God will not cast him into <hi>Hell,</hi> hen he dyes. What is his comfort in this world? <hi>Answ.</hi> His comfort is partly that <hi>hope,</hi> and partly somew <hi>lust,</hi> or creature-comfort, that he feeds upon, and commits Spiritual <hi>Adul tery</hi> with every day, continually. What do these <hi>hopes</hi> stand on? What are they built on? <hi>Answ.</hi> His own <hi>Obedience</hi> and something in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and hence as he find things there, <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worse</hi> as he reckons, so his <hi>hopes</hi> are higher, or lower, they ebb or flow accordingly, as we have but now intimated. Well, how is it with the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:191924:46"/> true believer, what are his <hi>hopes? Answ.</hi> That God is at <hi>peace</hi> with him throuh his Son, <hi>Christ Jesus:</hi> and also that he shall see, and enjoy him for ever, of which <hi>Inheritance</hi> he hath some <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest</hi> here; and hence <hi>hopes,</hi> and sometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>longs</hi> also for the full possession. Phil. 1. 23. <hi>Having a desire to depart, and to be with Christ, which is far better,</hi> than any thing, than all, than every thing that ius here in this World to be had <hi>Obj.</hi> But do all true believers find in themselves, this <hi>desire to be with Christ? Answ.</hi> No, unless it be at times? In some, the love of <hi>this World</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails, and that sadly, and that for a long time; one would hardly think, that there were any <hi>Grace</hi> in them: Others are almost always under <hi>clouds</hi> and <hi>darkness.</hi> Isa. 50. 10. <hi>they walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and have no light;</hi> and hence <hi>dying</hi> is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto them: but they have all that <hi>principle</hi> in them, which (if the actings of it were not one way or other obstructed in them) would shew it self in such <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>desires,</hi> as we have mentioned. But what is the true believers <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> here in this World, for the present, so far as he is, and acts like a believer, like himself? <hi>Answ.</hi> One main thing in which is lies, is this: <hi>viz.</hi> in what he can get and enjoy of <hi>God</hi> here: hence let his hopes stand never so fast, he can mourn for his want of getting more of <hi>God</hi> here; that he can find so little of him in his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> of his Worship: if the Lord be much, or long absent, he will <hi>lament</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:191924:47"/> after him; if he cannot see, as he hath <hi>seen</hi> in <hi>his Sanctuary;</hi> yea though he do <hi>dwell in his house,</hi> yet if there he cannot <hi>behold his beauty,</hi> he will complain, Cant 5. 6. <hi>my Beloved had withdrawn himself, and was gone,—my Soul failed when,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Legallist</hi> mourns not if his <hi>hopes</hi> will bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> stand: for his <hi>comfort</hi> lies in that, and in an <hi>Adulterous Communion</hi> with Creature comforts, and the <hi>vanities</hi> of this World: And if you ask, what the believers hope is built on? <hi>Answ. Christ,</hi> and <hi>Free Grace</hi> is the foundation of it. Col. 1. 27 <hi>Christ in you the hope of glory.</hi> 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. <hi>penult. Good hope through grace.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Jesus Christ which is our hope.</hi> Nothing so <hi>hard,</hi> nothing so <hi>sweet,</hi> as to live on the free, rich <hi>Grace</hi> of God in Christ Jesus only; and nothing so pleasing unto God, as that we should do so; and hereby he hath more glory by us, then if we could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent him a perfect Obedience of our own.</p>
               <p n="3">3 When sin is only <hi>benummed, &amp;c.</hi> whatever convictions there have been, yet the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> never so came, as to make <hi>sin revive,</hi> and so as to work in a man, all manner of <hi>Concupis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> so as to make a man feel <hi>sin,</hi> in its <hi>strength▪</hi> and dominion in him: for this would bring him to <hi>despair in himself,</hi> and spoil all his own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, and <hi>self righteous hopes;</hi> and prepare him to seek a <hi>remedy,</hi> not in himself, but out o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> himself, in the Grace of God in Christ Jesus when discovered to him; and unto unprepared ones, it is not wont to be discovered. Luk. 3. 5.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:191924:47"/>
                  <hi>Every vally shall be filled, and every mountain, and hill shall be brought low;—</hi>and then, <hi>All flesh shall see the Salvation of God. It is through the Law that we are dead unto the Law. And the Law is our School master to bring us unto Christ. Gal.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 24. we then must come under a work of the <hi>Law,</hi> that we may be prepared, for the light of the <hi>Gospel;</hi> its shining into our hearts, which many wanting, whatever they profess, the <hi>Gospel</hi> is hid unto them; it shines not. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. not as to the <hi>hear say</hi> of it, but as to the <hi>power,</hi> and saving efficacy of it.</p>
               <p>The next thing to be spoken to is this, <hi>viz.</hi> the difference between that effect which that faith, which is indeed but a <hi>Dead faith</hi> may have upon sin, and that which a <hi>Lively faith</hi> hath in <hi>mortifying</hi> of sin: for there is in some a work; not only meerly <hi>legal,</hi> or rather, in that degree <hi>legal:</hi> for some <hi>legallists</hi> are more gross than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but together with it, there is a <hi>Faith,</hi> though indeed, but a <hi>Dead faith,</hi> and even this <hi>faith</hi> hath in them, some effects on <hi>sin,</hi> to <hi>restrain</hi> it, though it never <hi>mortify</hi> it. Thus, I conceive it was with them, Psal. 78. 34, 35, 36. <hi>They sought him; and they returned, &amp; enquired early after God:</hi> and not only so; <hi>but they remembred that God was their rock, and the high God, their Redeemer.</hi> What then is, and how may we discover the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference? In true <hi>faith</hi> there is <hi>Love;</hi> so in that which is yet but A <hi>Dead faith,</hi> there is A <hi>Love</hi> too, though not such a <hi>Love,</hi> as is in the former:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:191924:48"/> we must then see, if we can make the difference, or shew it, in some few things at least.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Where this <hi>true love,</hi> or <hi>lively faith</hi> is, which <hi>purifies the heart,</hi> and engageth the Soul in <hi>mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of sin,</hi> there is an <hi>hatred</hi> to <hi>All sin.</hi> Psa. 119. 104 <hi>I hate every false way.</hi> In others there may be a falling out, with a sin, a quarrel with it for a season; as true <hi>Lovers</hi> may have their fallings out: but here is a real, and a rooted <hi>Hatred.</hi> Now it must needs be a <hi>great work</hi> whereby, &amp; a <hi>great change</hi> wherein a person is brought to <hi>Hate</hi> that which he once <hi>Loved</hi> above all other things. To <hi>Hate</hi> those things which once he delighted in, and which were to him as a <hi>Right Eye, or a Right Hand; yea as his very self.</hi> Math. 16. 24. <hi>Let him deny himself.</hi> How impossible is this to every man, and how far is he from it, until a great work, and change be wrought in him? he may think he can do it, and doth do it, but if eer the matter come indeed to tryal, he will find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self as far from it, as unable to do it, as a <hi>dead man</hi> from raising himself out of the Grave, and doing the works of the living. It is God only, by his <hi>mighty power,</hi> that can give life unto the <hi>Spiritually dead.</hi> Eph. 2. 1. 5. <hi>When ye were dead in sins.</hi> And where this <hi>hatred</hi> is, there are these things. (1.) A sensible mixture of <hi>Love</hi> to that which a man <hi>hates:</hi> so that he <hi>loves</hi> what he <hi>hates,</hi> and <hi>bates</hi> What he <hi>loves,</hi> and <hi>abhors</hi> himself for that <hi>love</hi> he finds unto sin. Rom. 7. 15. <hi>What I hate that do I.</hi> And he not only did it, but there
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:191924:48"/> was also some <hi>love</hi> to it: for his <hi>hatred of sin</hi> was not <hi>perfect,</hi> though <hi>sincere.</hi> Phil. 3. 12. <hi>Not already perfect:</hi> no, not in any one point; he was yet <hi>carnal and sold under sin,</hi> as to the unregenerate part, <hi>vere</hi> 14. though as to the <hi>inward man,</hi> it was otherwise, as <hi>verse</hi> 22. As long as we have sin in us, we shall have some <hi>love</hi> to it: those then that think they have <hi>no love</hi> to sin, in them, do deceive themselves; they do not know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and it is to be feared, that they have no <hi>true hatred.</hi> (2.) A making out, in the use of <hi>means</hi> after, an <hi>utter abolition,</hi> and <hi>rooting out of sin:</hi> so that nothing will give the heart full rest, or content, while any thing of <hi>sin</hi> still remaineth. Outward comforts, inward affections, and enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and assistances in duties, and such like are things in which many unfound ones rest. But he that <hi>Hateth all sin,</hi> will never rest, until it is <hi>All gone:</hi> yea the more help he hath against sin, and the more it <hi>dyes</hi> in him, he more he is set against it still: whereas it is contrary with others, that take up their stand, and make their rest in Reformation, without Mortification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This true, lively <hi>faith,</hi> which makes a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to seek to <hi>Mortify</hi> his sin; it sets him on <hi>work,</hi> as Gal. 5. 6. He will up, and be doing. That he may <hi>mortify</hi> his lust; he must <hi>work,</hi> Phil. 2. 12. And not only so, but it teaches him, as to <hi>work,</hi> so to look beyond all his own <hi>works,</hi> and doings and to own himself to be a poor <hi>Nothing</hi> else it is but (as I may call it) a <hi>legal faith. Pau<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:191924:49"/> did much, and so did <hi>Apollos</hi> too, yet neither of them were <hi>any thing,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 5, 6, 7. So in this case, for a person to do much, and yet after all to say, <hi>I am nothing,</hi> as he did, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 11. is a Mystery, which <hi>faith</hi> only teaches; and few know what it is, to be <hi>diligent</hi> in doing, and to rely only, on the <hi>power &amp; grace</hi> of God in Christ for supply of all <hi>wants.</hi> We may have a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral notion of this, but a lively sense and feeling of it, is both bitter and sweet, and an effect of a <hi>Lively faith</hi> only.</p>
               <p>Now it is true that an unsound Professor may <hi>do many things,</hi> as <hi>Herod</hi> did, <hi>Mark</hi> 6. 20. he may <hi>abound</hi> with Religious performances, as they <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. 11. had <hi>multitude of sacrifices,</hi> yet to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: the Lord saith that he was <hi>full of them:</hi> So they Isa. 58. 2. <hi>Sought him daily.</hi> Yet there is this difference also, besides what hath been said. (1.) Such as be unsound ones, usually rest in the <hi>External performance</hi> of dutis; and much farther from that they never go. But true <hi>faith</hi> teaches a man to look chiefly where God looks chiefly, <hi>viz.</hi> to the <hi>manner</hi> of performance, to the sincerity and uprightness of the heart in all duties. And hence what complaints do true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers many times make of <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> and <hi>by ends</hi> in duties, of <hi>self seekings,</hi> and the like, which they cannot wholly lay aside &amp; free themselves from? Something of this nature no doubt he found which brought forth that cry, Psal. 119. 80. <hi>Let my heart be sound in thy statutes, that I be not ashamed.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:191924:49"/> A true Christians great work in all his religious Services, is with his <hi>own heart,</hi> that in all he may approve himself unto God. (2.) Unsound ones do seek, and rest in <hi>themselves</hi> in all they do. <hi>Zech.</hi> 7. 5, 6. They did <hi>fast,</hi> and mourn &amp;c. but saith God, <hi>did ye at all do it unto me, even unto me?</hi> they did aall for themselves. A sound believer hath respect to God, and the pleasing of him, and finds rest in this. Psal. 19. <hi>ult. Let the words of my mouth, and the meditations of my heart, be acceptable in thy sight, O Lord my strength, and my Redeemer.</hi> q. d. if God accept me, if I may please him, it is well, it is enough; he hath been good to me, <hi>my Redeemer,</hi> and if I may but please him, that is the great thing that I seek. Here, understand aright.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is no man that can <hi>deny himself,</hi> so as not to <hi>seek himself</hi> more than he should: <hi>self</hi> will be rising up, but <hi>grace</hi> will snub and rebuke it, and say to it, <hi>get hence!</hi> and would have <hi>no more to do with it;</hi> as they said of their <hi>Idols.</hi> Hos. 14. 8. <hi>Self</hi> is the great <hi>Idol</hi> which almost all men, worship and serve.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No man is bound not to ahve any <hi>Eye</hi> to <hi>himself</hi> at all, in what he doth. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 26. yet a <hi>gracious respect to God,</hi> should and doth influence every gracious Soul, in what he doth, in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And many there be, I doubt not, that if called to it, would deny themselves, so as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake all for Christ, yea, to dy in his cause, however they have jealous, and low thoughts of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:191924:50"/> and so it is with many that hold on in a steady way of obedience, attending consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiously to all the ordinances of God, and known duties of his Worship; what they do, is in some measure from their good respect, and love to God, and his wayes, who yet cannot say it of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and not from <hi>servile fear</hi> only. And that appears thus. (1) If it were from <hi>servile fear</hi> only, they would in time grow <hi>weary,</hi> of Gods wayes, as many do. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 13. &amp; <hi>Isa.</hi> 43. 22. it is true, there is often some, yea much <hi>servile fear</hi> in a <hi>Child</hi> of God, and there is also a <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riness</hi> in Spiritual work; but then how is this complained of? do not they loath themselves for it? are not they <hi>weary</hi> of that <hi>weariness?</hi> and God makes good that promise unto them. <hi>Isa.</hi> 40. <hi>ult.</hi> the meaning is, not that they shall find no <hi>weariness,</hi> or <hi>faintings</hi> at all, who <hi>wait on God,</hi> but that it shall not prevail so, but that as in the beginning of the verse, they shall <hi>renew their strength,</hi> and go on still. 2 Cor. 4. 1.<hi>—we faint not:</hi> but hold out still: so here; but as verse 16. they don't faint, because the <hi>inner man is renewed day by day.</hi> Yet <hi>David</hi> complained that his Soul <hi>fainted</hi> for Gods Salvation. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 81. (2) If it were only from <hi>servile fear,</hi> a <hi>Form of Godliness</hi> would content them, they would not still be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after, and prizing the <hi>Power of Godliness,</hi> in their own hearts, and lives, and in others too: yea, the <hi>Power of Godliness</hi> would be a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to them; as it is unto many: and there
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:191924:50"/> be these things in it. See <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 13, 14. (1) A <hi>forgetting the things that are behind,</hi> contrary to a resting in present attainments, as they did, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17. who <hi>had enough, and need of nothing:</hi> as a man that runs in a race, he minds not what is <hi>behind</hi> him: and when a man forgets the things that are behind him, he sees a need to be doing still, and is desirous of <hi>getting more still,</hi> as well as of getting some at first: for what profit is it, to set out in a <hi>Race,</hi> if a person do not hold out, and go on in it? (2) A clear conviction of a <hi>persons imperfections,</hi> and a sight of things yet <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> which are precious in his eyes; as more <hi>strength,</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> in duties; more <hi>conformity</hi> unto the will of God; a further <hi>rest,</hi> and a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler contentment, and satisfaction in God, as a <hi>mans portion.</hi> Psal. 16. 5. these are things <hi>before a man,</hi> and precious in his eyes, if the <hi>Power of Godliness</hi> be in him: Hence (3.) There is a <hi>reaching</hi> after these things: a <hi>pressing on</hi> towards them: a person doth not only use means, but in them he seeks after these things: if the question be as to them of old, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 28. <hi>Whom seek ye?</hi> the answer will be as before; more of <hi>God,</hi> and more of <hi>Christ, &amp;c.</hi> these are the things which they so much seek; to whom it may be said, as to them, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 5. <hi>fear not, ye seek Jesus;</hi> and that they so did, appears in those sad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints which tehy made, when Ordinances are, or seem to be, <hi>empty things</hi> to them; and him whom they <hi>seek,</hi> they do not there find. Oh!
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:191924:51"/> consider it; you attend means, but <hi>what seek ye?</hi> is it to pacify <hi>Conscience,</hi> and to satisfy <hi>Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> only, and to patch up a <hi>self-righteous peace</hi> only; or is it <hi>Jesus</hi> that you seek, and more of him? Let your <hi>peace</hi> be, according as you find in these things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third <hi>Fruit</hi> mentioned by way of Tryal; (for it is an Use of Tryal that we are upon) is <hi>Vivification,</hi> or a <hi>living,</hi> or a being <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live</hi> unto God, as it is called. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 11. Gal. 2. 19. Now seeing there is such a thing as <hi>living unto God,</hi> or being <hi>alive unto God,</hi> and that it is, where-ever true <hi>Faith</hi> is, as appears from the last named place, verses 19, 20. compared together; it concerns us to consider, whether we have any thing of this <hi>Living to God,</hi> or no. Let us then consider a few things, as briefly as we can, out of this last named Text, which may help us to discover whether we be <hi>alive to God,</hi> or not.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A man must be <hi>dead unto the Law,</hi> before he can be <hi>alive unto God:</hi> he that is <hi>alive unto the Law,</hi> is alive unto <hi>himself,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> once was. Rom. 7. 9. and indeed such an one <hi>lives unto himself,</hi> while he seems most of all to e <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live unto God;</hi> and the Lord abhors even the best, that is to be found with such a man: well then; a man must be dead unto the Law, be-fore he <hi>can,</hi> I say, <hi>can</hi> live unto God. Now this is a great thing, and it is a <hi>great work</hi> of God, to bring a person to it: <hi>viz.</hi> to be <hi>dead unto the</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:191924:51"/>
                  <hi>Law,</hi> none but he that made Heaven and Earth, can do it: for consider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Every man naturally is <hi>alive unto the Law,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> saith he <hi>once</hi> was; and to take away <hi>life</hi> is a great thing, and makes a very <hi>great change,</hi> in what sense soever you understand it: it is great in respect of the <hi>change,</hi> that is made; and in respect of the <hi>reluctancy</hi> and <hi>opposition</hi> that is made against it: indeed there is a difference, some die more easily than others do. Now I say, that every man naturally, is <hi>alive unto the Law: i. e.</hi> he <hi>seeks life by the Law,</hi> as they did. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>penult.</hi> many times persons don't know that they do thus; they may profess, and protest against it, and yet do it; and it is surely so with persons, when they have only a <hi>doctrinal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of the way of the Gospel, but never saw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>need</hi> of, or never came under a powerful work of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to convince them of <hi>righteousness,</hi> as well as of <hi>sin:</hi> there is as much need of the one, as of the other: for if there be any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (as I think there is, on divers accounts) we are more easily convinced of <hi>sin,</hi> then of the <hi>way of the Gospel:</hi> for we naturally know some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of he <hi>Law,</hi> but of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> we know nothing by nature: and all the whole <hi>body of death</hi> in us, opposes it, unto the utmost; there is nothing in us, but as it is under the management and influence of <hi>Corruption,</hi> opposes the <hi>way of the Gospel,</hi> not only much, but unto the utmost, or as much as can be: it is far easier to convince a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:191924:52"/> man, that he is a <hi>Sinner,</hi> and <hi>deserves to dy;</hi> than convince him, that he may be <hi>Saved by Faith in Christ Jesus:</hi> yet how many know nothing of the <hi>Plague of their own hearts</hi> in this matter!</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that is <hi>Dead unto the Law,</hi> hath experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced his own <hi>inability</hi> to perform, or <hi>keep the Law.</hi> It is not persons having heard, or having been told, that will suffice thorowly to convince them, of their inability to <hi>keep the Law:</hi> for they will not throughly believe it, until they have <hi>tryed</hi> it, and have an Experimental knowledge of it. This we see by constant Experience; &amp; it may be otherwise evidenced also: though persons have <hi>Lived</hi> all their dayes under the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and have had a good Education, and have gathered much head knowledge, yet when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, and awakenings come upon them, the first thing that they do, is to <hi>seek Righteousness, as it were by the works of the Law.</hi> Some indeed have a notion, and also some experience, of their own inability to <hi>keep the Law;</hi> but yet for want of a thorow awakening, and thro' the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a Spirit of <hi>slothfulness,</hi> and averseness unto Spiritual work, they never make thorow tryal and so never come to a thorow sight of them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selves, and of their own <hi>Nothingness:</hi> they say <hi>Oh! they can do nothing of themselves!</hi> and that they find it so too: but it is no otherwise with them, than with a <hi>slothful Servant,</hi> that lifts a little at a heavy burden, and crys out, thyat he cannot stir, or move it, whereas he never put forth hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:191924:52"/> strength, to try what he can do; a cudgil or whip would make him do more, a great deal. So it is here, small awakenings, bring forth small endeavours, and leave persons alive unto the Law still. Consider this then, it may be thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of thy own nothingness are but what the <hi>slothful Servant</hi> hath; if so, thou must go to work again: and get thee to thy old fears and terrours, which were smothered, by one means or other, and dyed away too soon. There be many that dy in the birth; many whose Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions issue in <hi>formality,</hi> refined <hi>self righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and <hi>self deceiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. He that is <hi>dead unto the Law,</hi> is convinced of the <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> of <hi>seeking righteousness</hi> by it. He hath been made to see the pride and folly of his own heart in that matter, and is ashamed of it. Persons must be <hi>ashamed</hi> of their <hi>own wayes,</hi> before they will come to <hi>God way.</hi> You that say, you never <hi>sought righteousness, as it were by works of the Law,</hi> you always knew better than to do so; you may do well to consider deeply whether you do not deceive your selves. And this know for certain, that whatsoever your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, progress, &amp; attainments therein be; you don't <hi>live to God,</hi> and your <hi>faith</hi> is but a <hi>Dead faith,</hi> if you be not <hi>Dead unto the Law;</hi> all you have (if it be much) will be found at last to be, no better, no other, than a fine spun thred of <hi>Pharisaism,</hi> and self delusion; and after all you have done, a fearful perdition, will be the issue.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:191924:53"/> 2. He that <hi>lives unto God,</hi> lives a <hi>Life of faith;</hi> or, the <hi>life that he now lives is by the faith of the Son of God,</hi> as he speaks, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. Not a <hi>Dead faith;</hi> but that of the <hi>Son of God.</hi> And where this <hi>faith</hi> comes and prevailes in the Soul.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It doth as it were <hi>Annihilate</hi> the Creature 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 11. It <hi>Empties a man,</hi> it (as it were) takes him off his own legs: it makes a man, in his highest attainments, to be <hi>nothing</hi> in his own eyes. So, in that second of Gal. <hi>I live, yet not I.</hi> This is a Mystery, <hi>I, and yet not I.</hi> Before faith comes, or before a man is humbled, he is A <hi>Great Something,</hi> in his own eyes, though indeed worse than <hi>Nothing.</hi> Rev. 3. 17. But when <hi>faith</hi> comes, he is both a real something, and a <hi>great nothing.</hi> And this, as I said, is a great Mystery; a piece of unintelligible <hi>nonsense</hi> to a carnal heart. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5. E're <hi>faith</hi> comes a mans <hi>felf sufficiency</hi> is gone, and all his <hi>sufficiency is of God;</hi> he hath <hi>no suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency in himself,</hi> no, no not so much as to think a good thought.</p>
               <p>And in this <hi>Annihilation</hi> of the Creature, there are these things to be considered, besides what else might be named.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A disappointment of <hi>Expectation,</hi> as to the way of liveing a <hi>Life of Religion.</hi> First, a man thinks he hath something of <hi>himself,</hi> and he will not easily think otherwise; and then he expects to have something given to him, whereby he may set up again, and <hi>live upon himself;</hi> but when the matter comes to tryal, he finds that he must live
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:191924:53"/> upon <hi>another;</hi> and live (as we say) from hand to mouth: <hi>Yesterdayes Assistance,</hi> will not help him for <hi>this dayes work.</hi> He that could do all things <hi>Yesterday,</hi> can do nothing <hi>this day,</hi> unless he have Assistance from the same hand, which is <hi>Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> given or taken or denyed, as he pleaseth from whom it is. And hence often arise great discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements. A person saith, <hi>I thought ere now, I should have been able to do more, than, I find, I can: I am still vile, still a poor wretched Creature; I can do nothing, perform no duty, as I ought:</hi> yea the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, are oft left to themselves, that they may know themselves, and where their <hi>dependance</hi> is. See 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. 31. And in a Christians or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary course, wonted Assistance may now and then be withdrawn, on the same account.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>An Abasement of Soul:</hi> A person is brought to be <hi>poor in Spirit:</hi> he hath a low esteem of himself. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 8. is exceeding <hi>vile in his own eyes.</hi> Job 40. 4. Faith indeed <hi>purifies the heart,</hi> but it also opens a persons eyes, so that he sees some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the sin that still dwells in them; and <hi>great Faith,</hi> and a little sight of that, will hardly consist together: sometimes, where true <hi>faith</hi> is, there is a great mixture of <hi>presumption,</hi> which makes faith seem to be much more, and greater than indeed it is.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>An Inward Contest,</hi> or <hi>Strife</hi> in the Soul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting this <hi>Nothingness</hi> and <hi>Abasement;</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate part reluctates, and opposes, this way of abasement; the <hi>now man</hi> closes with it, as the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:191924:54"/> best way, as an <hi>excellent way.</hi> Phil. 3. 8. the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>way of the Gospel,</hi> hath an Excellency in it. And the knowledge of our selves, <hi>Christ,</hi> and of our own <hi>Nothingness</hi> go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: He that <hi>Exalteth Christ</hi> must <hi>debase him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self;</hi> he that prizeth Christ, must deny and abhor himself: <hi>Self exalting,</hi> and <hi>Christ exalting,</hi> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent, in the power thereof.</p>
               <p>Now consider this; you that can easily exalt, and magnify <hi>Christ</hi> (as you think) verily you have cause to fear that you never knew what it was: you are utter strangers to a <hi>Life of Faith,</hi> Which though it be sweet, and precious, yet by reason of <hi>Corruption,</hi> and through <hi>Temptation,</hi> it is usually very difficult, especially at times.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This <hi>Faith</hi> carries out the Soul unto God, and that in these three respects. (1.) As look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Him for all it wants. (2) In acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, in All it hath. (3.) In uniting the heart to God in <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In Looking to <hi>Him</hi> for all it <hi>wants: Faith</hi> leads the Soul to <hi>Wisdoms Gates,</hi> to the posts of her door, and there it stands and <hi>knocks,</hi> and <hi>waits,</hi> as Prov. 8. 34. the heart will be stealing out, and turning aside to <hi>other doors,</hi> but when this is seen, the Soul rebukes it self for it, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of its own folly. Now is it thus with you? whither go you for <hi>help?</hi> perhaps you you will say, <hi>I go to God alone?</hi> but do not you turn aside elsewhere sometimes: if you say <hi>no:</hi> you do not know your own hearts: and it is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:191924:54"/> as if you should say, <hi>you have no unbelief,</hi> no self righteousness working, and prevailing in you; and who shall believe you in that? this sin, if any, dwells in you, and will carry you <hi>Captive,</hi> sometimes: But I say, <hi>Faith</hi> carries the Soul out of it <hi>self,</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> in Christ Jesus, for supply of <hi>wants;</hi> and therefore in this respect it doth two things. (1.) It shews the Soul its own <hi>empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> (2.) Christs <hi>fullness,</hi> or all sufficiency.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Soul is made to see its own <hi>emptiness,</hi> and <hi>nothingness:</hi> It may be you will say, this you have seen, and do see this: but I say, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, whether it be so indeed, or not: have you ever seen a need of Almighty <hi>Power</hi> to make you see it, to <hi>cause</hi> you to see it. Ezek. 16. 2. have you seen the <hi>enmity</hi> and <hi>opposition</hi> of your hearts against this sight of your selves: <hi>Doctrinal Knowledge</hi> of Spiritual Things, is more easy, but <hi>Experimental Knowledge,</hi> and clear convictions, affect mens hearts, and break them to pieces; and there is much in the heart to oppose, and withstand the same.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Soul is shewen, or made to see the <hi>Sufficiency of Christ Jesus:</hi> it could never see it, or believe it, if it were not shewen, by a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful work of the <hi>Spirit:</hi> yea, the heart of man makes strong opposition against the <hi>way of the Gospel,</hi> it hates the knowledge thereof. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 29. and the secret language and voice of the heart is, as <hi>Job</hi> 21. 14. <hi>we desire not the knowledge of thy wayes.</hi> It is true, there is in the heart an <hi>enmity</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:191924:55"/> against God, and all of God; all his Wayes and Laws, and people; but especially against <hi>Christ,</hi> and a saving knowledge of him: and hence I say, there must be a mighty work of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to shew <hi>Christ,</hi> and his fitness, and sufficiency to <hi>Save Lost Sinners;</hi> and it is a glorious fight when see. Joh. 1. 14. <hi>We beheld his glory, the glory,</hi> &amp;c. consider it then, hast thou ever seen the <hi>Glory of Jesus Christ?</hi> you have heard of him, read of him, spoke of him; but hath he been <hi>revealed</hi> to you, and have you seen him? Joh. 6. 40. you must see him, not with bodily eyes, for that would confound you: and <hi>God</hi> must shew him, else you cannot see him: and if you <hi>see</hi> him not, you cannot <hi>believe</hi> in him: Hence if <hi>the Gospel be hid</hi> (which sets him forth) <hi>it is to suh as be lost</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 3. and hence in verse sixth, <hi>God who commanded the light to shine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ.</hi> Here mark; it is <hi>God</hi> that gives this <hi>light;</hi> it is he that <hi>shines in our hearts;</hi> and there must be an <hi>Almighty Power</hi> put forth, else to us the <hi>Gospel will be hid.</hi> He must <hi>command</hi> the Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> else the <hi>God of this World will blind us,</hi> so as that, the <hi>Light of the Gospel of the glory of God</hi> (for so I read the words) shall not shine unto us, or in our hearts: in darkness we be by nature, and so abide, until he do powerfully call us into <hi>his marvellous light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>In acknowledging</hi> him in all it <hi>hath:</hi> as the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:191924:55"/> Soul receives all from God, by <hi>Faith:</hi> so <hi>Faith</hi> leads it, to acknowledge him in all it hath; as he said; <hi>I live, yet not I, but Christ lives in me;</hi> and again, else-where, he saith, <hi>he could do all things through Christ strengthening him:</hi> Still whatever he did, he ascribes all to <hi>Christ:</hi> so he, Psal. 144. 1, 2, 3. <hi>The Lord my strength, who teacheth my hands to war,—my goodness,</hi> &amp;c. mark, how he ascribes all to God. Now this the believing Soul doth in some measure, and desires to do it more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: it is a pleasure to a Believer to be doing for <hi>Christ,</hi> and when he hath done all, to be setting the <hi>Crown</hi> still upon the head of <hi>Christ; I, yet not I but Christ;</hi> it is the voice and language of <hi>Faith.</hi> Indeed to acknowledge <hi>Christ</hi> in all a person hath, or doth, in <hi>words</hi> only, is easy; but really and sensibly to do it, is difficult, and much averseness is in the heart of a man against it. Consider then, how you find it, do you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg <hi>Christ</hi> in all? do you find it a <hi>hard thing</hi> so to do? do you bewail the contrary, and beg help against it? if you think it an easy thing, you know not what it is?</p>
               <p n="3">3. In uniting the heart to God by <hi>love: Faith</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> alwayes go together; they cannot be separated. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14. he that <hi>believes,</hi> he also <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>oves:</hi> as soon as a man hath a sight of Christ, he falls in <hi>love</hi> with him: <hi>he is altogether lovely:</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s soon as the <hi>Grace of God that brings Salvation,</hi> doth appear unto the Soul, it doth unite the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eart unto him, by <hi>love.</hi> Eph. 6. 23. <hi>Peace be</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:191924:56"/>
                  <hi>unto the brethren, and love with faith;</hi> he means an increase of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>faith:</hi> and puts them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, because they are never separated; and hence he curseth all that don't <hi>Love the Lord Jesus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, (as we go along) because that many a gracious Soul may be at a loss, and unable to find their love to Christ, and thereupon be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged; we shall mention some things, in which, it usually discovers it self, and may some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be found, when persons cannot look di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly on it, and find, and feel those sensible workings of it in their Souls, which at some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times perhaps they can; and therefore tho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> they have it, they can't discern it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In a desire of <hi>fellowship,</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> with him in his ordinances, as Cant. 1. 1. <hi>Let him kiss me with &amp;c. his Love is better than wine—</hi>this was a sign, and an evidence of <hi>Love</hi> in them, and so was that in verse fourth, <hi>Draw me &amp;c.</hi> so here when the Soul desires Christ in his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and breaths after, or accounts precious, the discoveries and manifestations of Christ unto the Soul, in hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Ordinances,</hi> this is <hi>better than wine;</hi> when though many will say, <hi>who will shew us any good;</hi> yet the Soul joyns with them that say, <hi>Lord, lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us,</hi> Psal. 4. 6. And it is not <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and duties that will satisfy the Soul, but <hi>Christ</hi> in them; this is an evidence of <hi>Love.</hi> Cant. 3. 1. <hi>I sought him whom my sou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> loveth:</hi> that <hi>seeking sheweth love.</hi> You then tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:191924:56"/> wait on, and attend to these and those <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and duties of Gods Worship, what, or whom <hi>seek</hi> yee? is it, the Lord <hi>Jesus Christ?</hi> or is it some what else? if it be him you seek; it is from a likeance of, and a <hi>love</hi> to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This love appears sometimes, in that they are so deeply <hi>sensible</hi> of it, when they see any <hi>wrong</hi> offered unto the Lord, his name, wayes, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eople, or institutions, <hi>Psal.</hi> 69. 9. And that this <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s from <hi>Love</hi> to God, and his wayes, appears in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat they are so ready to Condemn <hi>themselves,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s well as others: they are grieved at the <hi>evil wayes of others,</hi> Psal. 119. 158. But they judge <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hemselves as <hi>chief of sinners,</hi> abhor and loth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elves, especially at times. <hi>Job</hi> 42. 6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In their <hi>following after God,</hi> in all the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ayes</hi> that he hath appointed, Cant. 31. <hi>I sought HIM whom my soul loveth.</hi> I sought <hi>Him</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat by <hi>night</hi> too, on her bed: this was an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ence of <hi>Love.</hi> So when the Soul seeks <hi>God,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ot only in <hi>Publick duties,</hi> but also, where no eye <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f man sees; and it is the <hi>Lord himself</hi> that is here sought; this is an evidence of much <hi>love</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ometimes. I say not when much pains in duties <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> taken; for that may come from other causes, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ut when also <hi>CHRIST</hi> is sought for in them: <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>sal. 63. 8. His <hi>soul followed hard after God. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>lothfulness</hi> in duties argues little, or no <hi>love;</hi> but when <hi>God is sought,</hi> and that <hi>diligently</hi> too, it is <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n evidence of <hi>love:</hi> especially when not his
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:191924:57"/>
                  <hi>favour</hi> only, but his <hi>holiness</hi> is sought for, to be partakers of that. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>USE. <hi>II.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Of <hi>Exhortation</hi> and Direction.</head>
               <p>Take heed of resting in a <hi>Dead faith;</hi> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for a <hi>Lively faith.</hi> In other words, see that you accept the <hi>Offers of the Gospel,</hi> sincerely; or that you <hi>submit</hi> to, accept of <hi>Christ</hi> as offered in the Gospel: I use that word <hi>submit:</hi> the Apostle uses it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 3. We cannot find a better word. You will say, how is Christ <hi>Offered<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Answ.</hi> As a <hi>Prophet,</hi> as a <hi>Priest,</hi> as a <hi>King.</hi> Thes<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> things, I shall briefly open, when first of all,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> have premised these things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is the <hi>Person</hi> of the Lord Christ that true <hi>faith</hi> closes with: it is <hi>Him</hi> that true faith look to. <hi>Isa.</hi> 45. 22. <hi>Look unto ME. HE is the Prop<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiation: as many as received him,</hi> Joh. 1. 12. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is the portion of the Soul, and in <hi>Him</hi> it hope<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 24. In <hi>Him</hi> the Soul doth acquiesce an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>rest.</hi> Psal. 73. 25. And hence the Counsel, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Direction here is this, <hi>viz.</hi> See that you don<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> fall short of <hi>Christ himself;</hi> for nothing else b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Christ himself,</hi> will stand you in any stead. Yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have it may be many things; as gifts, commo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> graces, affections, and enlargements, comfort and the like: but have you <hi>Christ himself?</hi> a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> you married unto <hi>him?</hi> have you closed wit<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:191924:57"/>
                  <hi>him? He that hath the son hath life, and he that hath not the son, hath not life; for life is in the son.</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 11, 12. But it comes to none, but to such as receive <hi>him.</hi> If a woman be never so rich, he only hath <hi>hers,</hi> that hath <hi>her,</hi> or matcheth with her. Would you have Christs <hi>benefits</hi> (he is <hi>rich)</hi> than match with <hi>him;</hi> if you have <hi>him,</hi> you have <hi>all;</hi> miss of <hi>him,</hi> nd you have <hi>nothing,</hi> but conceit.</p>
               <p>If you say, how shall I know whether I have <hi>Christ</hi> or no? I <hi>Answ.</hi> As your <hi>Conviction</hi> is, such your <hi>faith</hi> is: as is the <hi>preparation work,</hi> such is the <hi>closing</hi> with Christ. It is a <hi>sure rule;</hi> and this is the reason, why we so much, and so often press for <hi>preparation work.</hi> The Soul must be <hi>prepared for Christ,</hi> before it can <hi>come to Christ,</hi> or <hi>close with Christ.</hi> See Luk. 3. 4, 5, 6. And there is more <hi>preparation</hi> needful, than many think for: it is a great work of God to <hi>prepare</hi> the Soul for Christ, which is naturally full of all <hi>enmity</hi> and <hi>opposition,</hi> against Christ: the heart being every way, on every side, straitly shut up, and fortified against Christ; and there are <hi>strong holds</hi> to be pulled down. Consider that place, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4, 5. Here then Consider whether you have <hi>seen Christ</hi> or not: for till a person see him, he cannot come to, or close with him, as <hi>Joh</hi> 6. 40. as we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready intimated. Persons do not use to <hi>match</hi> with a person, whom they have never <hi>seen;</hi> or if they do, it seldome proves well afterwards: so in this case: Christ must be <hi>seen,</hi> and then the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:191924:58"/> Soul will <hi>love,</hi> and chuse, and close with him: otherwise it may match indeed with him, after a sort, through common Convictions <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but it will not prove well; in a time of tryal and temptation, such an one will <hi>forsake Christ,</hi> and his cause: and thus many do, that do not openly Apostatise, yet their hearts are secretly withdrawn from him, and his works, and they inwardly cast off his yoke: and will not <hi>mortify</hi> their lusts, and <hi>purify</hi> themselves, as he is pure; as all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers do, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 3. Now if you have <hi>seen Christ,</hi> you have seen your <hi>ignorance</hi> of him. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 2, 3. That <hi>light</hi> which discovers Christ unto the Soul, shews a person both his former, &amp; yet abiding <hi>ignorance</hi> of him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. This light comes out of darkness.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you have <hi>seen him,</hi> it hath been a <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sight.</hi> Jesus Christ is a <hi>wonderful</hi> one; his name is <hi>wonderfull.</hi> Isa 9. 6. And when he is seen, he appears so to be unto the Soul: he is so in himself, and will be so to <hi>his</hi> for ever. His Prayer for his was, that they might <hi>behold his glory.</hi> Joh. 17. 24. A little glimmering of which, here, at times, outbids all that the world hath to give; and makes us despise the one, and long for more of the other. See Rom. 8. 23. <hi>We have the first fruits,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>seen,</hi> it makes a person <hi>vile</hi> in his own eyes, <hi>Isa.</hi> 6. 5. When his <hi>eyes</hi> had seen the King, the Lord of Hosts, he crys out, <hi>I am unclean</hi> &amp;c. The more any one knows of Christ,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:191924:58"/> the <hi>viler</hi> he is in his own eyes: who ever knew more of Christ than <hi>Paul</hi> did? yet see what he saith of himself. See 1 Tim. 1. 15.<hi>—Chief of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> And Eph. 3. 8. <hi>Less than the least of all Saints.</hi> Hence several sorts of Persons may receive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such as close with Christ only upon a <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> historical <hi>knowledge</hi> of him: they have had, it may be great Convictions, and much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward trouble, about their own sinfulness, and guiltiness; and hence fly to and catch hold of Jesus Christ; and the bottom of all is (if they could see it) to <hi>Ease</hi> them in, and not to <hi>Save</hi> them from their sins: and this <hi>faith</hi> of theirs smothers their Convictions; and they are <hi>healed slightly;</hi> and cry <hi>peace, peace</hi> to themselves, when there is <hi>no peace.</hi> Consider what <hi>knowledge</hi> of Christ you have, is it more than may be obtained by common industry, without a <hi>Supernatural work</hi> of the Spirit of God? it is true; you may have great enlightnings, and yet fall short of Christ: such as hardly fall short of a miracle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 5, 6. yea, you may work <hi>miracles,</hi> and yet perish for ever. As <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 22. Wherefore consider further.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such as close with <hi>Promises,</hi> but not with <hi>Christ</hi> in them. Thus do many: there be <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Promises</hi> in the word; as to such as <hi>mourn;</hi> to such as <hi>hunger and thirst after righteousness</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I am such an one,</hi> saith a person, and hence takes <hi>comfort,</hi> but takes not <hi>Christ.</hi> Perhaps you have
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:191924:59"/> read many <hi>Promises,</hi> and have had much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from them, but have you had <hi>Christ</hi> in them? <hi>Comfort</hi> without <hi>Christ,</hi> is but like a <hi>Shaddow</hi> without <hi>substance,</hi> or worse. Many there be that catch at, and take hold of <hi>Promises,</hi> that do miss of <hi>Christ,</hi> and hence have <hi>nothing,</hi> when they think they have <hi>all things.</hi> Rev. 3. 17. Among the rest that might be named, I shall mention one sort. <hi>viz.</hi> Such as look at <hi>peace</hi> more than <hi>holiness?</hi> Consider wherein is your <hi>rest?</hi> is it in peace and satisfying Convictions, or in <hi>conformity</hi> to the will of God? to be conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereto, is this glory, and happiness in your account? Christ came to <hi>Save his people from their sins,</hi> Matth. 1. 21. And to unlose, or <hi>destroy the work of the Devil in them,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 8. To set men at liberty from <hi>sin,</hi> as well as to deliver them from <hi>wrath to come.</hi> Is he then, on that account dear, and precious unto you? And consider all that hath been said; and what is it, that you have closed with? is it Christ himself, or is it not? And I further add two things.</p>
               <p>If you close with, and love the Lord Christ himself.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You will <hi>abhor</hi> your selves; and there will be a continual contest with, and opposition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your <hi>own righteousness:</hi> you will still en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be beating down that: as he <hi>Phil.:</hi> 3. 8, 9. and you will never wholly get clear of a <hi>self righteous principle,</hi> and the workings of it while you live; it will still be working, and
<pb facs="tcp:191924:59"/> making <hi>trouble</hi> one way or other, more or less when you would reject it, and think perhaps yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have, it will arise again, and be <hi>present.</hi> Rom. 7<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you <hi>Love</hi> him, you will <hi>Love what i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> his:</hi> his <hi>House.</hi> Psal. 26. 8. his <hi>Laws.</hi> Psal. 119<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 97. his <hi>People.</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 14. here note, that <hi>tru<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> love</hi> springs out of a seen, felt <hi>enmity</hi> against God and all of God, which the Soul hath been great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly humbled, and abased for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you <hi>Love</hi> him, you will <hi>Love his Holi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness,</hi> his <hi>Graces;</hi> and seek to keep all his Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandments: see Joh. 14. 21. <hi>he that hath m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Commandments, and keeps them, he it is that lovet<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> me.</hi> And there will be not only some outward conformity thereto; but more than that; as he said, Psal 119. 129. <hi>Thy Testimonies are wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, therefore doth my Soul keep them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have shewen that <hi>Christ</hi> himself is close<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with by a true <hi>Faith;</hi> now I add more particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larly; in all his <hi>Offices</hi> he is closed with, or ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepted of, otherwise we fall short of him a last.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As a <hi>Prophet:</hi> Jesus Christ is a <hi>Prophet;</hi> an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> it is a precious consideration: it was foretold o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> him that he should be so. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15. Acts<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 22. and he executeth this Office in <hi>revealing</hi> t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his people the will of God, and their duty t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards him: this he doth, not only in his <hi>Wor<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (for so it is revealed unto multitudes of repr<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bates)
<pb facs="tcp:191924:60"/> but by a mighty work of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hem that are his: else his <hi>Word</hi> would be as a <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lasped or <hi>sealed book</hi> to them, and the <hi>Gospel be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>id,</hi> as to any saving knowledge thereof; and so <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n seeing, they should <hi>see and not perceive,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s the woful condition of many. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 14.</p>
               <p>I shall open this particular thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We have the Will of God revealed to us, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n the <hi>Word</hi> of God: and the <hi>Word</hi> of God is <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ompleat,</hi> and <hi>perfect;</hi> thre is no need to have it <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ltered, by <hi>adding</hi> to it, or <hi>taking</hi> from it. <hi>Prov.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>0. 5, 6. Rev. 22. 18, 19. so that if in any case we would know what our duty is, what we be, or what God would have us be, we must look into the <hi>Word</hi> of God. Isa. 8. 20. <hi>to the Law and Testimony:</hi> and if we will follow the <hi>guidance</hi> of the Word of God, we shall <hi>walk safely:</hi> in all our difficulties, temptations, dangers, we shall at last be <hi>more than conquerors;</hi> and he took that course, <hi>Psa.</hi> 119. 24. <hi>Kings</hi> use to have their <hi>Counsellors,</hi> and so had <hi>David;</hi> but above all, in all his difficulties, which were many, he sought his guidance in, and from the <hi>Word</hi> of God; his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>estimonies were his Counsellors;</hi> and verse 105. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>is word a Lamp to his feet, and a Light to his path.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence all that do indeed believe, have a great <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>espect unto the <hi>Word</hi> of God: have they been <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>orn again?</hi> It is by the <hi>word</hi> of God. 1 Pet. 1. 23. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> have begotten you through the Gospel,</hi> saith <hi>Paul</hi> unto
<pb facs="tcp:191924:60"/> them, in 1 Cor. 4. 15. And have they found th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>narrow way</hi> which <hi>Leads to Life,</hi> which <hi>few d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>find,</hi> Mat. 7. 14. It is the light of the gloriou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Gospel of Christ,</hi> which shewed them the way and led them by Christ, to God, whom they had lost, and were meer strangers to, when there was <hi>no judgment,</hi> or nothing right <hi>in their goings,</hi> but they made crooked paths unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, <hi>not knowing the way of peace.</hi> Isa. 59. 8. and had wandered and wildered all their dayes, and perished for ever, had not <hi>the Word of Christ</hi> been a <hi>light unto their path:</hi> it is from the <hi>Word</hi> that they seek the mind, and will of Christ their <hi>Prophet:</hi> and it is by that, that he teaches them, that are his: it was by that, that he <hi>got under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing;</hi> and hence the <hi>Word</hi> was so <hi>sweet to his tast:</hi> Psal. 119. 103, 104. and hence that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, verse 133. <hi>Order my steps in thy Word.</hi> The best and sweetest life is when a persons steps are most of all <hi>ordered</hi> in, or according to <hi>Gods word:</hi> hence a true believer loves, and esteems much of Gods Word: as Psal. 119. 127, 128. <hi>Teach me the way of thy statutes, give me understanding, and I shallkeep thy Law; yea, I shall observe it with my whole heart: make me to go in the way of thy Commandments, for therein do I delight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then consider what <hi>esteem</hi> you have o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Word,</hi> by which Christ reveals his, and his Fathers Will unto his people? if you accept o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> him, as your <hi>Prophet,</hi> you will regard his <hi>Word</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:191924:61"/> and hence we enquire what esteem you have thereof? hear what he said, Job 23 12. <hi>I have esteemed the word of his mouth, more than my neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ry food.</hi> it may be you will say, I hope I love and prize, and esteem his <hi>word</hi> much more: but to some I may reply, how is it then that you look into <hi>it no more?</hi> that you medicate in it so little? perhaps you can let the <hi>Book</hi> of God ly by you day after day, and not so much as <hi>Look</hi> into it at all: others there be that do indeed read in it dayly, by course, but <hi>improve</hi> it not; they labour not to find the <hi>power</hi> of it in their hearts: and when so, is it not a <hi>Dead Faith</hi> that such rest in; or in great measure a Religion of <hi>words</hi> without <hi>works,</hi> or such <hi>works</hi> as may evidence a <hi>Lively Faith?</hi> the matter should be considered by them, whom it doth concern.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Christ reveals things to us by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and hence we have the Promise of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> Joh. 16. 7. And we read of the <hi>Spirit of Wisdom, and of revelation.</hi> Eph. 1. 17. The <hi>word</hi> indeed is full of <hi>light.</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 19. It is <hi>a light thta shineth</hi> &amp;c But the misery is, our <hi>minds</hi> are full of <hi>darkness:</hi> we walk in the thick, dark shades of our natural blindness, until God call us out of it: and though the <hi>light</hi> shine in the <hi>word,</hi> and in the dispensation of it, never so brightly, our <hi>darkness comprehendeth it not,</hi> as Joh. 1. 5. Hence we need the <hi>Spirit</hi> to enlighten; and a great work of the <hi>Spirit</hi> it is to <hi>Call us out of darkness,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:191924:61"/> as the phrase is 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. It is a work of the <hi>Spirit</hi> to give us eyes: we have much <hi>light</hi> in the word, But alas we want <hi>Eyes:</hi> Sin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, hath put out our <hi>Eyes,</hi> and <hi>blinded</hi> us. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 4. And it is the work of the <hi>Spirit</hi> to open the <hi>blind eyes.</hi> See <hi>Isa.</hi> 42. 7. And if your <hi>faith</hi> be right, it will lead you to Christ for this: for the <hi>Spirit</hi> will never come unless he send it.</p>
               <p>And of these that come to him, for this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, these things may be said.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They have seen their <hi>need</hi> of it: how else should they go to him, for his help? did you ever mourn under your <hi>darkness,</hi> and find a <hi>need</hi> of the Spirit to enlighten you? did you ever see your selves to be in <hi>darkness,</hi> in the midst of light? do you know what that means, to <hi>see,</hi> and yet <hi>not to see?</hi> Matth. 13. 14.<hi>—Seeing ye shall see, and shall not perceive.</hi> Did you ever see a <hi>need</hi> to <hi>know</hi> the things, that you knew before: to <hi>know Spiritually,</hi> what you <hi>know Doctrinally;</hi> there is a <hi>form of knowledge,</hi> and <hi>of the truth.</hi> Rom. 2. 20. And there is a <hi>Spiritual discerning</hi> of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things,</hi> Which no natural man hath. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14, 15. In haven, we shall see <hi>Christ</hi> with <hi>bodily eyes:</hi> Job 19. 27. But even there, there is a <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual fight</hi> of him, and of <hi>Spiritual things,</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of which is <hi>here;</hi> and before Conversion there is nothing of it: but when it comes it is <hi>life eternal.</hi> Joh. 17. 3.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:191924:62"/>
               <p> They know something of the <hi>necessity</hi> thereof. There is not only some <hi>need,</hi> but a Great <hi>necessity</hi> thereof. He that walks in much <hi>darkness,</hi> will quickly come into much <hi>deadness;</hi> and formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spirit will grow upon him: and hence that request of <hi>Paul</hi> for them, in the forenamed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 17. This <hi>light</hi> is indeed, in some sort, the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>strength</hi> of the Soul: where there is no <hi>light,</hi> there is no <hi>life,</hi> no <hi>strength.</hi> See Psal. 36. 9. <hi>With thee is the fountain of life, in thy light</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They have tasted the <hi>sweetness</hi> of this <hi>light:</hi> it is a <hi>pleasant thing to behold the Sun:</hi> much more to have the light, which comes from the <hi>Son of God,</hi> the <hi>Sun of Righteousness.</hi> Mal. 4. 2. when so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he shall <hi>arise</hi> upon the Soul; for there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>healing in his wings,</hi> and such shall <hi>go forth, and grow up:</hi> if you would <hi>grow,</hi> labour for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of Spiritual Light.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They have seen something of the <hi>enmity,</hi> and <hi>opposition</hi> of their hearts against the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Light</hi> of the Gospel; the heart naturally is full of this <hi>enmity,</hi> and <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position.</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 4, 5. the true believer knows something of this, of those <hi>strong holds,</hi> of those <hi>reasonings,</hi> of those <hi>high things,</hi> which exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves (in the Soul) against the <hi>Knowledge of God,</hi> and the things of God: and he sees the more a need, a necessity of <hi>Christ,</hi> of going to, and closing with him, for his help: mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:191924:62"/> frame is that in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 29. he <hi>hates</hi> life, but Christ teaches powerfully, commands the light to shine. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
               <p n="1">2. As a <hi>Priest:</hi> He is a <hi>Priest,</hi> and as such to be looked to, and closed with. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 17. 21. the <hi>Priests</hi> work was to <hi>Offer Gifts and Sacrifices for Sins.</hi> Heb. 5. 1. now <hi>Christ Offered up Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</hi> Heb. 7. 27. His design therein was to <hi>take away our sin.</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 5. and hence <hi>he is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our sin.</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 2.</p>
               <p>Christ Suffered for us, in our <hi>room,</hi> and <hi>stead:</hi> and for our <hi>Sin.</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 21, 24.<hi>—that also Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us—his own self hear our sin—</hi>and chap. 3. 18. <hi>Christ also hath once Suffered for sins;</hi> and he hath fully satisfied for <hi>Sin,</hi> there is nothing left for us to do in that matter, if there were, he would not be a perfect <hi>Priest,</hi> if he needed any of our help: and hence I say, we must look to him, and to him only, for pardon of <hi>sin,</hi> and acceptance with <hi>God.</hi> Wherefore accept him and his <hi>righteousness,</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and all is well: And this is the next thing that you are to be Exhorted to, and directed in.</p>
               <p>And here consider these things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Every man, one as well as another, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined naturally to seek <hi>righteousness,</hi> by the <hi>works of the Law,</hi> as they did. Rom. 9. 31, 32. and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:191924:63"/> 10. 3. men are not at any time more addicted to their <hi>vile lusts,</hi> which they hardly part with, than unto this; how hard is it to bring persons off from their <hi>Lusts?</hi> and it is as hard, or more hard in some respects, to bring them off from their own <hi>rightteousness;</hi> it is (and on sundry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts) of the two more hard to deny <hi>righteous self,</hi> then to deny <hi>sinful self:</hi> it is naturally so to any man, and to all men. Do you find it thus, o be you a stranger to these things? Consider further,</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any man think he be not <hi>strongly incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this way;</hi> it is because he doth not know <hi>himself,</hi> and because the matter never came in-deed to tryal, in the Soul. Many there be that have a national knowledge of the way of the Gospel, and they seem to fall in readily with it, as the only way. But two things are to be considered, wherein they miss it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Those that thus fall in with the way of the Gospel, do indeed but <hi>abuse</hi> it, while they seem to <hi>close</hi> with it; they make it an <hi>Asylum,</hi> or <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> for them to shelter themselves in, while in the mean time, they live in <hi>Sin,</hi> and so fight against God, and (as one saith) they <hi>take the Light of the Gospel, to let them see by, to Sin the more securely;</hi> they secretly fight against God with his own weapons: a deep ditch of deceit it is, in which many lurk, and ly hid,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:191924:63"/> until a dreadful day discover them. And here consider that nothing sets a man more against <hi>Sin,</hi> and strengthens him in his <hi>Warfare,</hi> then a true discovery of the <hi>way of the Gospel.</hi> Tit. 2. 11, 12. the <hi>Grace of God teaches us to deny ungodliness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Such persons never had the <hi>matter</hi> brought to <hi>tryal,</hi> in their own Souls: persons may think, that they can do this, or that, until the matter be brought to <hi>trial,</hi> and then they find it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, than they thought: so here, the matter (in this point) was never brought to <hi>trial: i. e.</hi> they were never throughly convinced of <hi>Sin:</hi> of the strictness of the <hi>Law:</hi> their consciences (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever convictions they have had) were never throughly enlightened, and awakened, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew what it was to have Sin <hi>revive</hi> in them, and to <hi>work death</hi> in them; as he speaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9, 13. to <hi>take hold</hi> on them, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 40. 12. No, they would then know what he did mean, when he said, <hi>his heart did fail him,</hi> and he was not <hi>able to look up:</hi> before a mans eyes are opened to see himself, and his Sin, he can <hi>look up</hi> well enough, his <hi>heart don't fail him:</hi> but when <hi>Sin</hi> is seen, there is a great change: if God do not some way or other uphold him, he sinks into the lowest bottom of <hi>despair,</hi> And no man can help him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When persons make <hi>Objections</hi> against be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving from their own <hi>sinfulness</hi> and <hi>vileness,</hi> it is from their ignorance of, and opposition against the <hi>way of the Gospel:</hi> it is not, because they are
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:191924:64"/> deeply <hi>humbled,</hi> (as some may think) but rather because they are <hi>not humbled enough;</hi> it is from their <hi>ignorance,</hi> and Spiritual <hi>Pride</hi> which still pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails in them: to <hi>believe,</hi> is an act of <hi>Obedience.</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 2, 3. <hi>this is his Commandment, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve;</hi> and what <hi>Humility</hi> is that which leads us to disobey the <hi>Commandment</hi> of God? you say, perhaps that you <hi>dare not believe,</hi> you <hi>dare not</hi> cast your selves upon Jesus Christ, and you think you are much <hi>humbled;</hi> but the truth is, you are full of <hi>ignorance,</hi> and Spiritual <hi>Pride,</hi> and in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of eternal ruin. See <hi>Mat</hi> 16. 16. Joh. 3. <hi>ult.</hi> the <hi>wrath of God abides upon you,</hi> while you abide in <hi>Unbelief:</hi> and abiding in that condition there is no hope, nor help for you.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The way to have a Saviour is to accept him on <hi>free gift:</hi> and consider what should hinder your <hi>acceptance.</hi> (1.) Are your <hi>sins</hi> many and great? <hi>Christ</hi> hath done enough to satisfy for them <hi>all.</hi> See <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. 18. &amp; 55. 7, 8, 9. The <hi>number</hi> and <hi>greatness</hi> of your sins, should not in the least hinder you from coming to <hi>Christ:</hi> his <hi>Blood cleaneth from all sin.</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 7. <hi>All manner of sin.</hi> Matth. 31. You dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor him, if you think otherwise; and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not to the way of the <hi>Second Covenant,</hi> and see not the vileness of so doing: and wo to you if you do not see, and bewail it, before you go hence and appear in another world. (2) Do you want a <hi>Righteousness</hi> to render you acceptable unto God? the righteousness of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:191924:64"/>
                  <hi>Christ,</hi> which is the righteousness of <hi>God.</hi> Rom. 10. 3. is a <hi>perfect righteousness,</hi> every way sufficient. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 18. (3) Do you say, <hi>but I do and shall sin still.</hi> Answ. See 1 Joh. 2. 1, 2. <hi>If any man sin we have an Advocate with the father.</hi> One that is every way able to plead, and manage our case. (4) You object, <hi>Oh! but I cannot come to, and believe on Jesus Christ. Answ.</hi>It is true; but consider what hinders you? The main thing is, you will not come to him Joh. 5. 40. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. <hi>Whosoever will let him come: The Spirit and the Bride, say come.</hi> God &amp; Christ, and all that are friends to him, say, <hi>Come,</hi> and if you do not, it is because your Will is not bowed there unto; and from your <hi>Ignorance</hi> of Christ. Hence the Exhortation is, <hi>Come unto Jesus Christ.</hi> See Isa. 55. 1, 2. And here mind, first the invitation, <hi>Come,</hi> let him <hi>Come;</hi> arise then, and <hi>Come;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he calls thee; even thee, whoever thou art: and then mind the terms propounded, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst which no Objection can be made, except what proceeds from <hi>Pride, Ignorance</hi> of, and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> against the way of the Gospel, Come <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Money, and without price:</hi> have you no <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness,</hi> none at all? than come <hi>without:</hi> yea, <hi>so come,</hi> or you will <hi>never come,</hi> or not aright. And why do you <hi>spend your labour for that which is not bread, and which satisfyeth not!</hi> The things of this world are such, and your own <hi>righteousness</hi> is such: you would fain make your selves better, but you <hi>labour in vain,</hi> you can
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:191924:65"/> never do it: when will you see the fruitlesness, folly, and sinfulness of your own way? And if any obstinately stand out, they must perish: yea the Lord saith, let them perish; he will not pitty them. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 22. Let them be <hi>Anathema Maranatha;</hi> it is just they should, and they must perish for ever and ever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Jesus Christ is a <hi>King,</hi> and a such to be submitted to, and is so, where true <hi>Faith</hi> is: and this submission also you are to be exhorted <hi>to,</hi> and directed in. Concerning which I will express my self thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Jesus Christ is a <hi>King:</hi> as he is a <hi>Prophet</hi> and a <hi>Priest,</hi> so he is a <hi>King.</hi> Psal. 2. 6. Act. 17. 7. 1 Tim. 6. 14, 15. 1 Cor. 15. 25. He is the <hi>blessed, and only potentate, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> and he must reign: and <hi>let his Kingdom come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We must submit to his <hi>Government:</hi> he must <hi>rule</hi> us; dispence to us, dispose of us, and of all that doth concern us, as he will: and he that will be his <hi>disciple</hi> must <hi>deny himself,</hi> take up his <hi>Cross</hi> and <hi>follow him.</hi> Matth. 16. 24. This is difficult, and yet it must be done, and that <hi>daily,</hi> Luk. 9. 23. This submitting is in a <hi>low degree</hi> in some of the Children of God: but where there is <hi>nothing</hi> of it, thre is no <hi>true faith.</hi> And he lives the sweetest life of all, that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:191924:65"/> lives most in a a real <hi>resignation</hi> of himself, and of all his concerns, into the hands of Jesus Christ, submitting all unto the will, and wisdom of this <hi>King of Kings:</hi> and this is to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by all that profess faith in Christ Jesus. To <hi>believe</hi> in him, and <hi>rebel</hi> against him, how do these agree? or to say, he shall be <hi>King,</hi> but yet not <hi>rule</hi> us: but we will direct him in his dealings with us, or with ours, or with the Church of God. It is certain that there are many that reject the <hi>Government</hi> of Christ, and hence whatever they pretend, their <hi>Faith</hi> is not right. And when I have opened this a little, you will further see what it is, that I exhort, and direct you to.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some do openly and manifestly <hi>reject</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> of Christ Jesus: they live in <hi>open rebellion</hi> against him. <hi>Isa.</hi> 3. 9. They practically say as Luk. 19. 14, 27 <hi>We will not have this man to reign over us;</hi> and he calls them his <hi>Enemies.</hi> Some do <hi>openly,</hi> and manifestly cast off his Government. (1) Sometimes by living in sins of <hi>Commission.</hi> (2) Sometimes by living in sins of <hi>Omission;</hi> when they will not attend to every <hi>known duty.</hi> Luk. 1. 6. They did <hi>Wal<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in all the Ordinancs, and Commandments of t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Lord:</hi> when any <hi>known duty,</hi> or ordinance Christ is neglected, and men continue so to do how doth Christ <hi>rule</hi> in them; do not th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cast off his yoke?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:191924:66"/> 2. Some do <hi>secretly</hi> cast off his <hi>Government;</hi> though they make an <hi>outward profession</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and be <hi>outwardly</hi> conformable unto his Laws; yet <hi>inwardly</hi> they reject him, and cast off his Government. Thus do many, as.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such as live in any <hi>particular known sin,</hi> though it be <hi>secret:</hi> thus do many. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17. 9. There is <hi>secret</hi> Drunkenness, and <hi>secret</hi> Uncleanness, and <hi>secret</hi> neglets of duties, and Closet work: now when persons live in <hi>secret sins,</hi> they do really though not manifestly cast off the yoke and <hi>Government</hi> of Chris. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>It is a shame to speak what some do in secret.</hi> And what some do actually, others do in their <hi>secret thoughts</hi> and cogitations: there is <hi>heart</hi> Adultery, and <hi>heart</hi> Murder, and <hi>heart</hi> Pride, and the like; little or nothing of which appears <hi>outwardly:</hi> but the day comes, when the <hi>bidden things of darkness, shall be brought to light,</hi> and the <hi>counsels of the heart made manifest.</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 5. And then it will be seen that many that now carry a <hi>fair face</hi> among men, are <hi>abominable Creatures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Such as are not at all <hi>kept at work with their own hearts</hi> day by day: these <hi>secretly</hi> cast off his <hi>Government:</hi> it appears thus; our great work every day is with our own <hi>hearts,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd we must <hi>watch</hi> them, and <hi>keep</hi> them for
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:191924:66"/> Christ. He hath so commanded, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 23. The <hi>heart</hi> is the <hi>Temple</hi> of God in which he desires to dwell; and we must endeavour to <hi>keep</hi> it for him, least we prove treacherous and traitors. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 16, 17. We may talk of <hi>trusting</hi> in him, but we deceive our selves; we have faith, but it is a <hi>Dead</hi> faith. It is in vain to cry, <hi>Hail Master,</hi> to make a <hi>fair Profession,</hi> while our <hi>hearts</hi> are in a manner only a possession of <hi>unclean,</hi> or <hi>vain things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Such as quarrel with <hi>crosses</hi> and <hi>afflictions. Amos</hi> 3. 6. <hi>no evil in the City, but the Lord hath done it; no cross,</hi> but he hath sent it; it is <hi>his cross;</hi> now when persons will not <hi>take up</hi> the Cross, but their <hi>hearts</hi> will <hi>break,</hi> before their <hi>wills</hi> will <hi>bow,</hi> how doth Christ now <hi>reign,</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> in their hearts? it is true, much <hi>unsubduedness</hi> is in some of the Children of God, even <hi>Jonah</hi> was very froward. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. 9. but when persons will not <hi>labour</hi> to ly under the will of Christ, &amp; so to do is not <hi>precious</hi> to them; truly they cast off his <hi>Government,</hi> and may consider whether or not there is cause to fear that <hi>he</hi> will reject, and cast off them at last, as such as would not deny them selves, and submit to his Cross.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Such as seem to <hi>submit</hi> themselves unto the <hi>will</hi> of Christ, but not by the <hi>power</hi> of Christ: what they do is by their <hi>own power,</hi> and ability: this is to bring in a <hi>forreign power</hi> secretly, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:191924:67"/>
                  <hi>Christ</hi> is not <hi>King</hi> in that Soul, he doth not <hi>reign</hi> there. See 2 Thes. 1. 11, 12. He must work all, by <hi>his power,</hi> that he may be glorified. Now consider this; you say, you do this or that, and you submit to the will of God, but by what <hi>power?</hi> is it by the <hi>power of Christ?</hi> you will it may be, say, <hi>Yes:</hi> but I answer, consider it well: if it be, then the more you attain, the <hi>meaner</hi> and <hi>lesser</hi> you will be in your own eyes, as <hi>Paul</hi> that had attained unto <hi>much,</hi> yet saith, <hi>I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 11. do you find it thus? as I may say, <hi>gaining</hi> one way, and <hi>loosing</hi> another, <hi>growing greater,</hi> and yet withal <hi>growing less?</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand aright, and consider it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Such as seem to submit to Christ, but not out of <hi>respect,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> but in all they do, they seek <hi>themselves,</hi> as they did. Zech. 7. 5, 6. <hi>did you do it unto me, even unto me.—</hi>So here, you read, you pray, you do <hi>many things,</hi> which Christ comands; did not <hi>Herod</hi> as much. <hi>Mark</hi> 6. 20 but if the Lord say at last, <hi>did you do it unto me, even unto me,</hi> that will be said, Again, some seem to submit under Crosses, and Afflictions, but sometimes it is rather <hi>hardness</hi> of heart, than submission; <hi>they cry not when he binds them; they despise the chastisement of the Lord;</hi> and then seem to submit: in other-some it is more from <hi>natural temper,</hi> than from <hi>Grace.</hi> And often there is no <hi>Submission,</hi> where there
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:191924:67"/> seem to be a great deal; and that which is a <hi>great tryal</hi> to <hi>one</hi> man, is none at all to <hi>another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to close, and shut up all that I sall say on this Subject, consider only this word; <hi>viz.</hi> if your <hi>Faith</hi> be found at last to be a <hi>Dead Faith,</hi> it will be dreadful: for consider what else might be said.</p>
               <p n="1">1. These few <hi>Sermons</hi> will be so many <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi> against you that have heard them; they will rise up in Judgment against you: He that <hi>Uttered</hi> them, and all they also that <hi>profited</hi> by them, shall appear in <hi>Judgment</hi> against you; and perhaps these and those whom you now <hi>despise,</hi> shall one day be your <hi>Judges.</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It shall then appear that you had <hi>means</hi> of <hi>Conviction:</hi> but you would not see that you <hi>held fast deceit,</hi> as they did. Jer. 8. 5. that you would not come unto the light; now it may be, you say, you are <hi>willing</hi> to see, but then it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that you <hi>refused Conviction;</hi> and being evil, <hi>chose darkness rather than light,</hi> and indeed <hi>hated knowledge.</hi> Prov. 1. 29.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your <hi>Damnation</hi> will be the greater, your <hi>Hell</hi> the hotter, your <hi>punishment</hi> the heavier, and <hi>torment</hi> the more intollerable: you may now neglect <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> and make light of <hi>Sermons,</hi> and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:191924:68"/> soon forget all Searching Truths; but there is a day coming, when persons shall be judged, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what they have been, and done, and means of <hi>Grace</hi> which they have enjoyed': it is good to think much of that great and dreadful day, and thereby be stirred up to labour for, and to make sure of, <hi>A Faith in Christ,</hi> which will not at last be found a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> all such will be <hi>Led forth with Workers of Iniquity:</hi> as Psal. 125. ult. whose <hi>Faith</hi> is when tried, but a <hi>Dead Faith.</hi> Let your great care be to be <hi>Sound in the Faith,</hi> as the phrase is. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 13. and <hi>Examine your selves dayly, whether you be in the Faith; prove your own selves.</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 5. all we can do here, is little enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and provide for that <hi>one hour of Death;</hi> that time when we must go hence, and be no more seen in this World.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:191924:68"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191924:69"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191924:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>